<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson - Latest Links]]></title>
	<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/atom-latest-links.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
	<updated>2015-02-12T19:29:54-05:00</updated>
	<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
	<author>
		<name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
		
	</author>
	<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Accessible Toggle-style Checkbox]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/accessible-toggle-style-checkbox/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-12T08:41:36-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/accessible-toggle-style-checkbox</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is, by far, the best implementation of a toggle slider checkbox replacement I&rsquo;ve seen.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://codepen.io/personable/pen/stpwD">Read on Codepen&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Let’s Write Fast JavaScript]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/lets-write-fast-javascript/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-11T10:13:53-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/lets-write-fast-javascript</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You may have already seen this piece from <a href="https://medium.com/@mdibaiee">Mahdi Dibaiee</a>, but if you haven’t it’s definitely worth a read. I also highly recommend <a href="https://twitter.com/slicknet">Nicholas Zakas</a>’ <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/059680279X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=059680279X&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=easydesign-20&amp;linkId=EIBQXEP7I2PP5RQE">High Performance JavaScript</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/amyhoy">Amy Hoy</a> &amp; <a href="https://twitter.com/thomasfuchs">Thomas Fuchs</a>’ <a href="http://javascriptrocks.com/">JavaScript Performance Rocks</a>.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="https://medium.com/the-javascript-collection/lets-write-fast-javascript-2b03c5575d9e">Read on Medium&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[This Uncanny Valley of Voice Recognition]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/this-uncanny-valley-of-voice-recognition/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-11T10:09:17-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/this-uncanny-valley-of-voice-recognition</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am incredibly excited about the future of voice-based user experiences, but I also fully recognize that we’ve got a long way to go. This post from <a href="https://twitter.com/holman">Zach Holman</a> does a great job illustrating the issues we are currently dealing with. And it’s a fun read to boot!</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://zachholman.com/posts/uncanny-valley/">Read on Zach Holman’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Social Class, Power, and Selfishness: When and Why Upper and Lower Class Individuals Behave Unethically]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/social-class-power-and-selfishness/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-11T09:53:53-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/social-class-power-and-selfishness</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this fascinating paper, David Dubois, Derek Rucker, and Adam Galinsky explore the interplay between socioeconomic status and selfishness (or cheating). In the course of their study, they discovered that people at both ends of the spectrum cheat, but for different ends:</p>

<blockquote><p>[S]ocial class positively predicted unethical behavior; however, this relationship was only observed when that behavior was self-beneficial. When unethical behavior was performed to benefit others, social class negatively predicted unethical behavior; lower class individuals were more likely than upper class individuals to engage in unethical behavior. Overall, social class predicts people’s tendency to behave selfishly, rather than predicting unethical behavior per se.</p></blockquote>

<p>The second thing they discovered was that the cause of selfishness came from an individuals’ sense of power:</p>

<blockquote><p>Evidence for this relationship was provided in three forms. First, income, but not education level, predicted unethical behavior. Second, feelings of power mediated the effect of social class on unethical behavior, but feelings of status did not. Third, two distinct manipulations of power produced the same moderation by self-versus-other beneficiary as was found with social class.</p></blockquote>

<p>Fascinating stuff!</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://psycnet.apa.org/?&fa=main.doiLanding&doi=10.1037/pspi0000008">Read on Journal of Personality and Social Psychology&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[The “Web Application” Myth]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/the-web-application-myth/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-10T19:39:53-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/the-web-application-myth</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Christian Heilmann is dead-on in this post. It’s a long one, but worth reading. Here’s my favorite bit:</p>

<blockquote>
<p><em>What is an application?</em> To me, it is a tool that allows people to reach a certain goal in the most effective fashion. What matters is not what language or technology you build it in. What matters most is:</p>
<ul>
<li>that it is the right tool for the right audience,</li>
<li>that it does what is expected of it and not more,</li>
<li>that it is safe to use,</li>
<li>that it works in the environment it is most used in,</li>
<li>that it can be easily maintained without dependencies that only a few people know how to use,</li>
<li>that it is built with components that are reliable to use and not a “alpha” or “beta” or “not production ready” experimental technology</li>
<li>that we know how to maintain the thing, how to add new functionality and above all, fix security issues in the future without replacing it as a whole.</li>
</ul>

<p>These are the things we should concentrate on. To find the answer as to what format this “application” will be, we need a mixture of skills of people working on the product:</p>

<ul>
<li>researchers,</li>
<li>designers,</li>
<li>UX people,</li>
<li>content writers,</li>
<li>trainers to show people how to use the tool and how to put content in it afterwards and,</li>
<li>yes, of course, developers.</li>
</ul>

<p>And this is the scary part: <strong>this costs money and a lot of effort</strong>. It also means that we have to think about communicating and building teams that are good at bouncing ideas off one another and find a good consensus. It also means it will take longer to build this.</p>

<p>All of this is <em>anathema</em> to people who have to show off to venture capital companies and stakeholders. We have to move faster, we have to be better. Less people, more products, quicker iterations, more features. It doesn’t matter what the product does: the most important part is that you show that it evolves and changes constantly.</p>

</blockquote>

<p><a rel="full-article" href="https://medium.com/@codepo8/the-web-application-myth-69c6b1506515">Read on Medium&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Designing for the Elderly: Ways Older People Use Digital Technology Differently]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/designing-digital-technology-for-the-elderly/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-06T17:51:36-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/designing-digital-technology-for-the-elderly</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We’re all aging. There’s no way to avoid it, no matter how much <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Growth_hormone">HGH</a> you consume. And as we age, our eyesight typically worsens, we lose some motor control, and our brains often don’t process data quite as fast as they did when we were 18 or even 30. As designers, we need to be cognizant of the needs of aging computer users.</p>

<p>Ollie Campbell has put together a great read on creating digital products that accommodate the aging population (estimated to top 19% of the US population by 2030). In it, he discusses things we should consider with respect to</p>

<ul>
<li>vision and hearing,</li>
<li>motor control,</li>
<li>device use,</li>
<li>relationships,</li>
<li>life stage,</li>
<li>experience with technology,</li>
<li>cognition,</li>
<li>memory,</li>
<li>attention, and</li>
<li>decision-making.</li>
</ul>


<p>It’s pretty exhaustive. You should definitely give it a read.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.smashingmagazine.com/2015/02/05/designing-digital-technology-for-the-elderly/">Read on Smashing Magazine&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[When Browsers Don’t Play Nicely in the Open Source Sandbox]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/when-browsers-dont-play-nicely-in-the-open-source-sandbox/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-06T10:07:36-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/when-browsers-dont-play-nicely-in-the-open-source-sandbox</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Passive aggression at its best:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">console.log('Google, please make sure your obfuscator does not change class names, so our patch continues working (or stop browser-sniffing as we both use and contribute to Blink!) - love, Opera.');</code></pre>

<p><a rel="full-article" href="https://github.com/operasoftware/browserjs/blob/master/OPRdesktop/browserjs-25.0.js#L252">Read on Github&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Reframing Accessibility for the Web]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/reframing-accessibility-for-the-web/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-05T21:05:36-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/reframing-accessibility-for-the-web</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lots of great stuff here from Anne Gibson:</p>

<blockquote><p>We need to change the way we talk about accessibility. Most people are taught that “web accessibility means that people with disabilities can use the Web”—the official definition from the W3C. This is wrong. Web accessibility means that people can use the web.</p>

<p>Not “people with disabilities.” Not “blind people and deaf people.” Not “people who have cognitive disabilities” or “men who are color blind” or “people with motor disabilities.” People. People who are using the web. People who are using what you’re building.</p>

<p>We need to stop invoking the internal stereotypes we have about who is disabled.</p></blockquote>

<p>Anne goes on to offer a lot of practical and helpful advice around how to change the way you think about accessibility and how to act upon that change. You should definitely read it.</p>

<p>For similar content on this site, see <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/the-web-is-for-everyone/">my keynote from A11yQC</a> and <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/egalitarianism/">my post on egalitarianism</a>.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://alistapart.com/article/reframing-accessibility-for-the-web">Read on A List Apart&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[You’re Missing the Point of Server-Side Rendered JavaScript Apps]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/youre-missing-the-point-of-server-side-rendered-javascript-apps/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-05T19:20:05-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/youre-missing-the-point-of-server-side-rendered-javascript-apps</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I agree with Tom Dale. Yup, you read that right: I agree with Tom Dale. Well, he finally said something sensible:</p>

<blockquote><p>Say what you will about server-rendered apps, the performance of your server is much more predictable, and more easily upgraded, than the many, many different device configurations of your users. Server-rendering is important to ensure that users who are not on the latest-and-greatest can see your content immediately when they click a link.</p></blockquote>

<p>You might remember Tom as the guy who <a href="http://tomdale.net/2013/09/progressive-enhancement-is-dead/">declared progressive enhancement dead in late 2013</a>. He’s apparently seen the light and has been hard at work to get Ember ready for server side rendering.</p>

<p>I’m shocked, but glad he finally came around. Progressive enhancement FTW!</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://tomdale.net/2015/02/youre-missing-the-point-of-server-side-rendered-javascript-apps/">Read on Tom Dale’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Power of the Platforms]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/power-of-the-platforms/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-05T13:11:05-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/power-of-the-platforms</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a great post from Simon St. Laurent on how isolated Web &ldquo;platforms&rdquo; have come and go while the &ldquo;tangled mess&rdquo; that is HTML, CSS, and JavaScript soldiers on. It’s a must read.</p>

<blockquote><p>The web bends with the wind, supporting incredibly diverse use cases across a wide variety of environments. Your code should, too.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://radar.oreilly.com/2015/02/power-of-the-platforms.html">Read on O’Reilly Radar&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Truth About Multiple H1 Tags in the HTML5 Era]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/the-truth-about-multiple-h1-tags-in-the-html5-era/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-03T16:14:54-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/the-truth-about-multiple-h1-tags-in-the-html5-era</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a beautiful and exhaustive survey of heading level usage before HTML5 and in HTML5. Sadly, <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html5/sections.html#outlines">no one implements the HTML5 scenario yet</a>. But it’s nice to dream. Maybe one day.</p>

<p>For more:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.paciellogroup.com/blog/2013/10/html5-document-outline/">The HTML5 Document Outline</a></li>
<li><a href="http://blog.adrianroselli.com/2013/12/the-truth-about-truth-about-multiple-h1.html">The Truth about “The Truth About Multiple H1 Tags”</a></li>
</ul>

<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://webdesign.tutsplus.com/articles/the-truth-about-multiple-h1-tags-in-the-html5-era--webdesign-16824">Read on Tuts+&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Emulating Failure]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/emulating-failure/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-02T07:09:54-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/emulating-failure</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another beautifully-eloquent post about the potential perils of <a href="http://www.w3.org/wiki/WebComponents/">Web Components</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>HTML has a problem. As implemented in browsers many interactive elements cannot be styled as desired by web developers, or developers as directed by designers, marketing or any of the numerous others whose wishes code cutters must abide by.</p>

<p>…</p>

<p>Now in 2015 we have web components re-inventing native HTML buttons, radio buttons and checkboxes, for relief from the scourge of divitis, perpetrated upon us by the as shipped inability to style a native HTML element as desired.</p>

<p>Is it just me, or are new web UI technologies continuing to try to solve the wrong problems?</p></blockquote>

<p>Now, the <a href="http://glazkov.com/2011/01/14/what-the-heck-is-shadow-dom/">Shadow DOM</a> (and <a href="https://gist.github.com/webtobesocial/aefd6e25064c08e0cc9a">associated pseudo-elements</a>) should allow us to control the style of these elements. The deeper problem is functionality. Take <a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/forms.html#the-datalist-element">the <code>datalist</code> for predictive typing</a>. What if you want fuzzy search instead of initial search when someone types. That’s not supported. This is where Web Components get interesting.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.paciellogroup.com/blog/2015/02/emulating-failure/">Read on The Paciello Group&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Accessible Timeout Notifications]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/accessible-timeout-notifications-tink/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-01T13:23:17-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/accessible-timeout-notifications-tink</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m not generally a fan of session timeouts, but if you have to do it, Léonie Watson has outlined a pretty good route to go. My only nit might be using a <code>role</code> of &ldquo;alert&rdquo; or &ldquo;alertdialog&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;group&rdquo;, but that’s because it would trigger an audible chime and get read by assistive tech. But that’s pretty minor.</p>

<p>Pay particular attention to the keyboard focus stuff too.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://tink.uk/accessible-timeout-notifications/">Read on Tink&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Browser Accessibility Tree]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/the-browser-accessibility-tree/"/>
				<updated>2015-02-01T13:20:41-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/the-browser-accessibility-tree</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A clear and concise overview of browsers’ accessibility trees, using the <code>video</code> element as an example. Yet another reason to love <a href="https://twitter.com/stevefaulkner">Steve Faulkner</a>.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.paciellogroup.com/blog/2015/01/the-browser-accessibility-tree/">Read on The Paciello Group&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Extensibility]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/extensibility/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-30T09:44:38-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/extensibility</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Great post from Jeremy on Web components. I couldn’t agree more:</p>

<blockquote><p>I was looking forward to getting really stuck into Web Components and figuring out ways of creating powerful little extensions that I could start using now. But if Web Components turn out to be an all-or-nothing technology—a “platform”, if you will—then I will not only not be using them, I’ll be actively arguing against their use.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="https://adactio.com/journal/8276">Read on Adactio’s Journal&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on Pagination]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/thoughts-on-pagination/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-28T17:51:36-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/thoughts-on-pagination</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pagination is pretty arbitrary. Could it be better? Probably.</p>

<blockquote><p>For example, take your average photo site that displays the content in a reverse chronological order: that is, newest to oldest. Let&rsquo;s say your friend has posted 2000 photos to this site. The site shows the viewer 10 things per page. With our prolific user, this gives us 200 pages.</p>

<p>Going to the middle of this content takes us to page 100. What does this mean, beyond we&rsquo;re at the middle? Not much.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="https://nolancaudill.com/2012/03/24/pagination/">Read on Nolan Caudill’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Why All Three Game Consoles Have Now Ditched the TV]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/why-all-three-game-consoles-have-now-ditched-the-tv/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-28T17:48:16-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/why-all-three-game-consoles-have-now-ditched-the-tv</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I hadn’t really thought about it with respect to gaming, but this has definitely been an interesting trend:</p>

<blockquote><p>More and more so, the programming we once watched on TV is migrating to our tablets and phones. Cable providers have apps that let customers access live television, and even the contents of their DVRs, on their personal devices. Comcast et al realize they must let you access that content where your eyeballs are, or you’ll find other content. Ditto Nintendo, Microsoft and Sony. Game consoles cannot be married to the TV.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.wired.com/2015/01/xbox-streaming-windows-10/">Read on Wired&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[WhatsApp Doesn't Understand the Web]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/whatsapp-doesnt-understand-the-web/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-27T11:35:18-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/whatsapp-doesnt-understand-the-web</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am not a WhatsApp user, but I have long been impressed with the way they embrace operating systems others ignore. I think it has been a key to their success and speaks to the &ldquo;accessibility&rdquo; (in the broader sense) of their service.</p>

<p>I am completely baffled by the design decisions they made in their Web client, as is Andre Alves Garzia.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://andregarzia.com/posts/en/whatsappdoesntunderstandtheweb/">Read on Andre Alves Garzia’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Inside Microsoft’s New Rendering Engine for the &quot;Project Spartan&quot;]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/inside-microsofts-new-rendering-engine-for-the-project-spartan-smashing-magazine/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-27T11:32:05-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/inside-microsofts-new-rendering-engine-for-the-project-spartan-smashing-magazine</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is Microsoft’s Jacob Rossi on how “Project Spartan” came to be and what is going on inside the browser that comes after Internet Explorer.</p>

<p>On that elated feeling of removing legacy code:</p>

<blockquote><p>[S]wathes of IE legacy were deleted from the new engine. Gone were document modes. Removed was the subsystem responsible for emulating IE8 layout quirks. VBScript eliminated. Remnants like attachEvent, X-UA-Compatible, currentStyle were all purged from the new engine. The codebase looks little like Trident anymore (far more diverged already than even Blink is from WebKit).</p></blockquote>

<p>On a faster dev cycle for the new browser:</p>

<blockquote><p>[W]e’ll treat Windows 10 as a service—keeping users up to date and delivering features when they are ready (“auto-update”), not waiting for the next major release. This means the new rendering engine will always be truly evergreen.</p></blockquote>

<p>On opening up the process:</p>

<blockquote><p>Another welcomed change that we’ve been rolling out over the past year is a promise for increased openness about our web platform plans and roadmap. Over the last year, you’ve hopefully experienced some of this through our open standards roadmap15 (one of my personal side projects), our Reddit AMA16, regular dialog through @IEDevChat17, and sharing preview builds18 very early in our development process. You’ll see more of this over the next year.</p></blockquote>

<p>Promising stuff all around. I am still wondering if we’ll eventually see the new browser appear on other operating systems (even if it’s  just the browser chrome and not the rendering engine—like Chrome on iOS). Time will tell.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.smashingmagazine.com/2015/01/26/inside-microsofts-new-rendering-engine-project-spartan/">Read on Smashing Magazine&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
</feed>
