<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]> Latest Posts &amp; Links</title>
	<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
	<updated>2015-01-19T14:06:46-05:00</updated>
	<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
	<author>
		<name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
		
	</author>
	<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Egalitarianism]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/egalitarianism/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-19T10:32:20-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/egalitarianism</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today in Martin Luther King in the United States, so I thought I’d take a moment to reflect on one aspect of equality I think is incredibly important: egalitarianism.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>According to <a href="http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/egalitarianism"><cite class="book">Merriam Webster</cite></a>, egalitarianism is:</p>

<blockquote>
    <ol>
        <li>a belief in human equality especially with respect to social, political, and economic affairs;</li>
        <li>a social philosophy advocating the removal of inequalities among people.</li>
    </ol>
</blockquote>


<p>It’s a simple philosophy inspired by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Rule">the Golden Rule</a>, an ethical code which is central to most major religions:</p>

<dl>
    <dt>Buddhism</dt>
    <dd>Hurt not others in ways that you yourself would find harmful.</dd>
    <dt>Christianity</dt>
    <dd>Do unto others as you would have  them do unto you.</dd>
    <dt>Islam</dt>
    <dd>No one of you is a believer until he desires for his brother that which he desires for himself.</dd>
    <dt>Judaism</dt>
    <dd>What is hateful to you, do not to your fellow man. That is the entire law; all the rest is commentary.</dd>
</dl>


<p>Heck, even Confucius said “Never impose on others what you would not choose for yourself”.</p>

<p>With so much emphasis on treating others with the sort of respect that we would like to be given, you’d think that inequality would be a non-issue. Obviously that’s not the case.</p>

<p>For centuries, we humans—even those of us who ascribe to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Rule#Religion_and_philosophy">these and the other countless Golden Rule abiding religions and philosophies</a>—have failed to recognize ourselves in others and have erected barriers (both physical and societal) to their ability to lead the sort of happy, fulfilled life that we want for ourselves and our families.</p>

<p>Almost every way we mistreat others—from rude or snarky comments to genocide—stems from our inability to empathize with another person or group of people. It’s hard to connect with people who are different than us—people who have different life experiences, people who have different perspectives, people who are challenged in ways we have never been—and when we struggle to create a connection, it becomes easy for us to view them as “the other”. And when we begin to look at other people this way, we lose sight of their humanity and we lose sight of all of the things that make us similar.</p>

<p>While it is completely true that I have a very different life than a woman growing up in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dharavi">Dharavi</a>, I have to believe that we have a lot in common too. We both want a good life for our families. We both want to feel safe. We both crack jokes. We’re both human. Our respective societies may view us very differently, but she is no less valuable than I am.</p>

<p>And this is why I am so passionate about the philosophy of egalitarianism. It grounds us in the notion that we are all equally valuable and should be granted equal opportunity to all that life has to offer.</p>

<hr>


<p>John Rawls has a great thought experiment that I often cite in <a href="http://vimeo.com/70018634">my talks on empathy</a>. In it, he would ask you to imagine your ideal society. It could be a monarchy, anarchy, capitalist, or communist. It could be ruled by people of one particular gender or color. It could be governed by people of a particular tribe. It could be <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hunger_Games_universe#Panem">Panem</a>. It could be <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erewhon">Erewhon</a>. It could be <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brobdingnag">Brobdingnag</a>. The choice is yours.</p>

<p>Once you’ve been ruminating on this a bit, he drops the bombshell: You have no control over or knowledge of where you fit in this society. This is called the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veil_of_ignorance">Veil of Ignorance</a>, a creation of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Harsanyi">John Harsanyi</a> (an economist and early father of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Game_theory">game theory</a>). Rawls found that, with the Veil of Ignorance in play, people who participated in this thought experiment gravitated toward creating the most egalitarian societies possible.</p>

<p>It makes complete sense: What rational human being would create a society that enslaves people if they themselves could turn out to be a slave? Who would create a society that excludes women if they might be female? Who would build a world full of stairs if they could be in a wheelchair?</p>

<p>I love this exercise because it makes it easy to create at least basic connections between you and a wide variety of people who are different than you. It helps you realize that we are all equal and all worthy of consideration.</p>

<hr>


<p>What is interesting about egalitarianism, as opposed to similar sounding philosophies like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Communist_Manifesto">modern communism</a>, is that it recognizes that equality of opportunity does not necessitate equality of outcome. In other words, while pushing for equality,  it simultaneously recognizes that we have differences in capability, capacity, and interest.</p>

<p>We are different. We are similar in more ways than we are different, but to ignore our differences is to deny us our  individuality, our personhood, our true selves. But recognizing differences is not the same as assigning a value to those differences. That’s an incredibly important distinction and bears repeating: Just because you recognize that someone is different does not imply you should view or treat them as any more or less human on account of what makes them different. That said, recognizing differences is the first step towards being able to create equality of opportunity.</p>

<p>This is such an important concept in life, but I was not a philosophy major, so I’ll stick to discussing it in terms of what I know a lot about: The Web. Specifically, Web accessibility.</p>

<p>For a great many of us, ensuring our websites are accessible is an afterthought. We talk a good game when it comes to “user centered” this or that, but often treat the word “accessibility” as a synonym for “screen reader”. It’s so much more than that. “Accessibility” is about people. People consume content and use interfaces in many different ways, some similar and some not so similar to how we do it.</p>

<p>Sure, people with visual impairments often use a screen reader to consume content. They might also use a braille touch feedback device or a braille printer. They probably also use a keyboard. Or they may use a touchscreen in concert with audio cues. And yes, visual impairment affects a great percentage of people, but they are only part of the “accessibility” puzzle.</p>

<p>The dimensions of interactive elements—links, buttons, etc.—and their proximity to one another is an important factor in ensuring an interface actually registers our intent (i.e. it helps us avoid <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Typographical_error">fat fingering</a>). <em>Design</em> is an accessibility concern.</p>

<p>The color contrast between text and the background is an important factor in ensuring content remains readable in different lighting situations. <em>Color</em> is an accessibility concern.</p>

<p>The language we use on our sites and in our interfaces directly affects how easy it is for our users to understand what we do, the products we are offering, and why it matters. It also affects how we make our users feel. <em>Language</em> is an accessibility concern.</p>

<p>The size of our Web pages and their associated assets has a direct affect on how long our pages take to download, how much it costs our customers to access them, and (sometimes) even whether or not the content can be reached. <em>Performance</em> is an accessibility concern.</p>

<p>I could keep going, but I’m sure you’re starting to get the point. “Accessibility” is ultimately about ensuring people have equal opportunity to access your content while simultaneously recognizing that we all have special needs—physical limitations, bandwidth limitations, device limitations, etc.—that lead us to have different experiences of the same Web page.</p>

<p>Accessibility <em>is</em> egalitarianism.</p>

<hr>


<p>We are all different, but we all human. We all deserve respect. We all deserve to be treated equally. To be treated fairly.</p>

<p>We need more egalitarianism in this world and the good news is that <em>we</em> can make it happen.</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Problem With Angular]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/the-problem-with-angular/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-16T15:37:16-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/the-problem-with-angular</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this extensive piece, PPK does a brilliant job voicing the thoughts and feeling I think a lot of us front-enders have when it comes to Angular. You should do yourself a favor and read the whole thing. Seriously. Especially if you are in IT in a large company that is using or thinking of using Angular. Seriously.</p>

<p>Go. Read. It.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.quirksmode.org/blog/archives/2015/01/the_problem_wit.html">Read on PPK’s QuirksBlog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Spelling Errors, Exclusions, and Packages, Oh My—Working Drafts at the W3C]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/spelling-errors-exclusions-and-packages-oh-my/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-16T07:15:12-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/spelling-errors-exclusions-and-packages-oh-my</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week the W3C published a couple of really cool new Working Drafts I wanted to bring to your attention (just in case you missed them).</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css-pseudo-4-20150115">CSS 4 Pseudo-elements</a>.</h2>

<p>Most of this is stuff you know: <code>::first-line</code>, <code>::first-letter</code>, and <code>::selection</code>. But what magic is this? <code>::spelling-error</code> and <code>::grammar-error</code> too! What?! Now I know I may be a little too excited about this, but it’s not because spelling and grammar errors are going to solve all of our design problems; I am excited about this because it points to us being granted more control over how more of the internals of browser operations are rendered to our users.</p>

<p>Obviously <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/native-vs-stylable-tug-of-war/">this is a double edged sword</a> and could be abused to the detriment of the user experience, but it may also lead to someone coming up with clearer conventions for indicating spelling and grammar errors than the ones we’ve been using since the early days of Microsoft Word.</p>

<h2><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css3-exclusions-20150115/">CSS 3 Exclusions</a></h2>

<p>This has been a long time coming. The idea is pretty simple: Within a flow-type element (think <code>p</code>, <code>div</code>, etc.) you can apply <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css3-exclusions-20150115/#wrap-flow-property">the <code>wrap-flow</code> property</a> to children in order to control where content can go in relation to them. Here’s an example from the spec:</p>

<figure id="fig-2015-01-16-1">
    <img src="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css3-exclusions-20150115/images/exclusions-illustration.png" alt="Four boxes layed out roughly diagonally from the upper left to the lower right within a larger container. A flow of blue color shows where text is allowed to flow.">
</figure>


<p>In this example, child A is set to <code>wrap-flow: both</code>, allowing content to flow on both sides of it. Child B is set to <code>wrap-flow: start</code> meaning content should only be allowed on the starting side of the element (based on text direction, in this case left to right). Child C is set to <code>wrap-flow: end</code> meaning content can only appear after it in terms of text-direction. And child D is set to <code>wrap-flow: clear</code> which, as you might expect based on your existing CSS knowledge, ensures no content appears on either side of it.</p>

<p>There is <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css3-exclusions-20150115/#wrap-flow-property">another, more thorough example in the Working Draft</a> (scroll down a little bit), but it uses grid layout as well and is a little more complicated that I want to get into today.</p>

<p>On the flip side of the equation, there is <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css3-exclusions-20150115/#wrap-through-property">the <code>wrap-through</code> property</a> which allows other elements to control whether or not they pay attention to the <code>wrap-flow</code> property of another element. A <code>wrap-through</code> value of &ldquo;wrap&rdquo; adheres to what they are calling the &ldquo;wrapping context&rdquo; of the parent element (which basically means it behaves as you’d expect, being a child element). Setting a <code>wrap-through</code> value of &ldquo;none&rdquo; on the child element, however, would make it ignore the parent element’s wrapping context and allow this child’s content to flow through (hence <code>wrap-through</code>) the excluded element.</p>

<p>It’s a lot to take in and (of course) still subject to change, but I just wanted to bring this concept to your attention as it is pretty cool stuff and is a nice complement to <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/css-shapes-1/">CSS Shapes</a>, which landed early last year.</p>

<h2><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-web-packaging-20150115/">Streamable Package Format</a></h2>

<p>This one is pretty crazy and I am still tucking into it, but here’s the gist: You could provide a &ldquo;package&rdquo; or rolled up collection of files necessary to render your page—think CSS, images, fonts, etc.—in <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-web-packaging-20150115/#streamable-package-format">Streamable Package Format</a> which would allow a browser to download them all in one go rather than having to request each resource individually. This could be really useful from a performance standpoint on high-latency connections as it cuts down on the number of round-trips the browser must make to the server before it can render the page. And, since the package can be streamed, we can optimize the contents to provide the most important bits first so the browser can go about rendering the document as quickly as possible.</p>

<p>This is a very cool concept with a lot of potential benefit to our users. Of course, as the document acknowledges, it’s also possible to abuse this and adversely affect performance by including a lot of unnecessary content. Kinda like <a href="https://www.polymer-project.org/articles/spa.html">that guy who made his whole single-page app into a Web Component</a>. Just because you can do something doesn’t make it a good idea.</p>

<p>Still, there’s a lot of potential here and I’m excited to see where it goes.</p>

<hr>


<p>Now the caveat: all of these are Working Drafts, not Technical Recommendations, so <em>they are not final by any means</em>. That said, they do point to a pretty interesting not to distant future.</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[An Onslaught of Low-cost Smartphones]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/an-onslaught-of-low-cost-smartphones/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-15T11:58:11-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/an-onslaught-of-low-cost-smartphones</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It seems every week we are seeing more and more low-cost devices being launched in an effort to connect the unconnected. For instance, this past week  saw the announcement of <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2015/1/14/7544107/microsoft-lumia-435-532-launch-specs-price-release-date">two new entries in the Microsoft Lumia line, the 435 and the 532</a>, and the announcement of <a href="http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2015/01/samsung-finally-puts-tizen-on-a-smartphone-launches-the-z1-in-india/">Samsung’s first Tizen phone, the Z1</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The two Lumia devices are the cheapest Windows Phone offerings to date: The Lumia 435 is €69 (about US$80) and the Lumia 532 is just slightly more expensive at €79 (about US$94). By comparison, the Lumia 535 was the previous low-cost Windows Phone winner at US$135. And Samsung’s Z1, which is aimed at the Indian market, runs a mere Rs 5,700 (roughly US$92).</p>

<p>Now if you’ve read this far, you are probably wondering why this matters. Well, spec-wise, many of these lower-end devices are far from what we are used to. All of these devices are running a resolution of 800×480. And their processing speeds are slower than the device you likely have in your pocket. But they are all far cheaper too. And remember that people in China and India have <a href="#fig-2015-01-15-01">far less disposible income than we do</a>.</p>

<figure id="fig-2015-01-15-01" class="media-container">
    <img src="http://aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2014-11-06/05-sm.jpg"
         srcset="/i/posts/2014-11-06/05-lg.jpg 1920w, /i/posts/2014-11-06/05-md.jpg 600w, /i/posts/2014-11-06/05-sm.jpg 320w"
         alt="A bar chart comparing the average monthly incomes of people living in the U.S., Canada, China, and India."
         >
</figure>


<p>If you only earned US$295 a month, a US$799 smartphone would likely be out of the question.</p>

<p>As Web designers and developers, we need to expose ourselves to the Web as others see it. This is why we need to view our sites and applications on lower-end devices and over lower-speed—2G, 3G, etc.—connections. Only by testing our wares can we truly ensure our content and services are available and accessible by anyone, anywhere, on any device. You know, <a href="http://webfoundation.org/about/vision/">the vision for the Web</a>.</p>

<p>Of course you probably don’t have the budget to purchase a bunch of devices, no matter how cheap they are. So how do you test on them? <a href="http://opendevicelab.com/">Visit a local Open Device Lab</a> like <a href="http://chadevicelab.org">the one we have here in Chattanooga</a>. Or if you don’t have one near you, consider getting together with some colleagues and <a href="http://lab-up.org/">starting an ODL in your area</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Where Cellular Networks Don&#039;t Exist, People Are Building Their Own]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/where-cellular-networks-dont-exist-people-are-building-their-own/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-14T09:35:30-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/where-cellular-networks-dont-exist-people-are-building-their-own</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a beautiful account of the struggles of bringing cellular networks to poor, rural areas that are uninteresting (e.g. unprofitable) to the major providers.</p>

<blockquote><p>Of the world’s 7 billion or so cell phones, a few hundred of them are already in Yaee—they’re just not connected to a network. Kids use them as cameras and mp3 players, and Hernández, like many adults, bought his to use in Oaxaca City, a seven-hour bus ride away. When he’s there, his cell phone can connect to plenty of base stations, which, in turn, link him to his choice of commercial network. But back in Yaee, there are no base stations and therefore no network. Every time Hernández wants to make a call in his hometown, he hikes for 20 minutes to the top of the highest hill around and hopes to catch some signal trickling in from a faraway base station, installed in a place deemed more profitable for telecoms than small towns like Yaee.</p></blockquote>

<p>Articles like this are a great reminder of how fortunate we are and how our experiences are not universal. They help us empathize with the struggles others must overcome to participate in the “modern world”.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.wired.com/2015/01/diy-cellular-phone-networks-mexico/">Read on Wired&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[9 of the World&#039;s Leading Designers Talk About What Matters Now]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/9-of-the-worlds-leading-designers-talk-about-what-matters-now/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-14T09:35:19-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/9-of-the-worlds-leading-designers-talk-about-what-matters-now</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A good collection of design-related thinking. Here are some highlights:</p>

<blockquote><p>Great design often disappears, leaving the user with no more than a simple and intuitive experience.</p></blockquote>

<p>From <a href="https://twitter.com/gentry">Gentry Underwood</a> of Dropbox. <a href="https://twitter.com/jmspool">Jared Spool</a> has been <a href="http://www.uie.com/articles/experiencedesign/">beating this drum for ages</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>When things are going well in a design, we don&rsquo;t pay attention to them. We only pay attention to things that bother us.</p></blockquote>

<p>Jack Schulze of Berg offered an interesting perspective on design permenance:</p>

<blockquote><p>When I was studying graphic design in the late &lsquo;90s, there was a dream that as a designer, if you were good enough, you might create an archetype for the age—the sorts of things you see in <cite class="movie">Mad Men</cite>, artifacts and images that characterize an era. But when I graduated, it became abundantly clear that when people looked back on the decade to come, they would not be looking at record covers or chairs. It was going to be glowing rectangles and software. People would remember the aesthetics and noises of operating systems, the first time they pinch-zoomed something, the aesthetics of Google Maps, the Nokia ringtone, and Candy Crush Saga.</p></blockquote>

<p>Closing out the piece, <a href="https://twitter.com/alexislloyd">Alexis Lloyd</a> of the <cite>New York Times</cite> R+D Lab offered an area of concern (and a challenge to designers everywhere):</p>

<blockquote><p>We&rsquo;re seeing new relationships emerging between people and technology. Algorithms influence an ever-increasing number of facets of our lives: the media we consume, what our health insurance knows about our physical condition, whether we&rsquo;re approved for loans or hired for jobs, and whom we may date or marry. But we don&rsquo;t have much agency in those interactions. These “smart” systems are black boxes, eschewing transparency in favor of simplicity. But when we can&rsquo;t interrogate a system, that disenfranchises us. Designers now must facilitate interactions that balance ease of use with transparency.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.wired.com/2015/01/what-matters-to-the-worlds-most-important-designers/">Read on Wired&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Histories]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/personal-histories/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-14T09:34:56-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/personal-histories</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a bautiful post from Sara that takes a deep dive into the impersonal nature of forms. I could not put it more bautifully and succinctly than her introductory tweet:</p>

<div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Every question we ask is part of a personal history—and lives are so much messier than a form field. New from me: <a href="http://t.co/g04bu3isqy">http://t.co/g04bu3isqy</a></p>&mdash; SaraWachterBoettcher (@sara_ann_marie) <a href="https://twitter.com/sara_ann_marie/status/555007063873818624">January 13, 2015</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>

<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.sarawb.com/2015/01/13/personal-histories/">Read on Sara Wachter-Boettcher&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Linkblog]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/the-linkblog/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-14T09:34:34-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/the-linkblog</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since re-starting my blog I’ve been continuing to tinker with Octopress and Jekyll in an effort to customize things a bit more to my liking.</p>

<p>I recently began posting links (with commentary) in a bit of a link blog, but I wasn’t really happy with having it mixed in with the rest of my Notebook posts. I finally took a few minutes to formally bust out the links into <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/">their own paginated section</a>, so you can keep up with them independently. I also set up a three distinct Atom feeds to let you consume this site’s content how you want to: <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/atom.xml">Latest 20 posts and links</a>, <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/atom-latest-posts.xml">latest 20 posts</a>, and <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/atom-latest-links.xml">Latest 20 links</a>.</p>

<p>I’m hopeful this organization will prove as helpful to you as it is for my compartmentalization anxiety.</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[webOS Is Back]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/webos-is-back/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-08T10:17:09-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/webos-is-back</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You may not remember it, but Palm’s groundbreaking—yes, I said groundbreaking—operating system, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebOS">webOS</a>, has been resuscitated yet again. This time by LG.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>For those of you who may have missed out on webOS in the past, here’s a primer: webOS was developed by Palm and debuted on the Palm Pre in 2009. It was the first “HTML5-based” operating system. Yes you read that right: the OS was built on HTML, CSS, and JavaScript. In 2009. Six. Years. Ago.</p>

<p>Applications for webOS were written using the front-end Web stack, with the JavaScript application logic tied into the device via the Mojo—and later Enyo—JavaScript application framework. Though novel at the time, this concept has since taken off in the intervening years. <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/dn631758.aspx">Windows</a>, <a href="https://marketplace.firefox.com/developers/">Firefox OS</a>, and <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=build%20native%20apps%20with%20html5">countless “unified” native app development platforms</a> have embraced the front-end Web stack as a means of building software.</p>

<p>webOS also supported multitasking, which was not common back then. And to make it easy to manage, webOS introduced the brilliant card metaphor for viewing and switching between running applications. Apple, of course, ripped that idea off for iOS 7. If you dig that feature on your iPhone you have Palm to thank.</p>

<p>Sadly, Palm usage was on the decline when webOS debuted so operating system never really took off. Eventually Palm was engulfed by HP, which launched the ill-fated HP TouchPad. It too failed to gather any steam and we thought webOS was dead (despite many proclamations to the contrary from well-meaning folks at HP).</p>

<p>In 2013 <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2013/2/25/4027814/hp-emerges-as-big-winner-in-webos-sale">HP announced it was selling parts of webOS to LG</a> for use in smart TVs. It was a glimmer of hope for the beleaguered OS. And now, not only do we have webOS based <a href="http://www.lg.com/uk/smarttv/webos">smart TVs</a>, but <a href="http://gizmodo.com/lgs-new-smart-watch-is-powered-by-webos-1678191522">LG’s new smart watches are sporting the OS as well</a>. And LG has not ruled out bringing it back for a phone either.</p>

<p>I’m happy to see webOS sticking around. It may have been the laughing stock in the app development community back in the day, but I’ve always had a soft spot in my heart for it.</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Living on the Edge – Our Next Step in Helping the Web Just Work]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/living-on-the-edge-our-next-step-in-helping-the-web-just-work-ieblog-site-home-msdn-blogs/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-07T08:42:43-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/living-on-the-edge-our-next-step-in-helping-the-web-just-work-ieblog-site-home-msdn-blogs</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the holidays, I completely missed this announcement from IE team. In IE for Windows 10, we’re getting:</p>

<ol>
<li>All public (i.e. non-intranet) sites will render in &ldquo;Edge mode&rdquo; meaning they get the latest standards implementation. <em>Note: It will ignore <a href="http://alistapart.com/article/beyonddoctype">X-UA-Compatible version targeting</a>.</em></li>
<li><a href="https://status.modern.ie/csstransformspreserve3d">CSS Preserve-3D</a></li>
<li><a href="https://status.modern.ie/contentsecuritypolicy">Content Security Policy 1.0</a> sandboxing</li>
<li><a href="https://status.modern.ie/mediaquerieslevel4interactionmediafeaturespointerandhover">CSS Interaction Media Queries (Level 4)</a> &ndash; pointer type &amp; hover testing!</li>
<li><a href="https://status.modern.ie/gamepadapi">Gamepad API</a></li>
<li><a href="https://status.modern.ie/selectionapi">Selection API</a></li>
<li>ECMAScript 6 features including <a href="https://status.modern.ie/classeses6">classes</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/promiseses6">promises</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/jsiteratorsietheforoffeature">iterators</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/arrowfunction">the arrow function</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/mathbuiltinses6">Math utility functions</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/numberbuiltinses6">Number utility functions</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/objectbuiltinses6">Object utility functions</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/stringbuiltinses6">String utility functions</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/es6objectliteralenhancements">Object literal enhancements</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/spreades6">spread</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/templatestringses6">template strings</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/symbols">symbols</a>, <a href="https://status.modern.ie/proxieses6">proxies</a>, and <a href="https://status.modern.ie/weaksetes6">weak set</a>.</li>
</ol>


<p>Pretty awesome stuff! What do you want to see in future versions of IE? You can <a href="https://wpdev.uservoice.com/forums/257854-internet-explorer-platform">post your thoughts and votes on UserVoice</a>.</p>

<p>If—like me—you’re on a Mac, you can run the latest version of IE via <a href="https://remote.modern.ie/">RemoteIE</a>. Haven’t heard of it? Rey Bango has <a href="http://blog.reybango.com/2014/11/03/a-new-way-to-test-internet-explorer-on-os-x-ios-and-android/">a great write-up of how to set up RemoteIE on Macs, iOS, and even Android</a>.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/ie/archive/2014/11/11/living-on-the-edge-our-next-step-in-interoperability.aspx">Read on IE Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Gogo Wi-Fi Is Using Man-in-the-Middle Malware Tactics on Its Own Users]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/gogo-is-using-man-in-the-middle-malware-tactics-on-its-own-users/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-06T18:02:57-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/gogo-is-using-man-in-the-middle-malware-tactics-on-its-own-users</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So earlier, <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/the-network-effect/">when I said the only way we could trust that the content we delivered was what we sent was via HTTPS</a>? I stand corrected. Even HTTPS can’t guarantee it.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://gizmodo.com/gogo-is-using-man-in-the-middle-malware-tactics-on-its-1677559652">Read on Gizmodo&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Revisiting (and Releasing) <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite>]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/revisiting-and-releasing-adaptive-web-design/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-05T14:10:49-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/revisiting-and-releasing-adaptive-web-design</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As you probably know, back in 2011 Easy Readers published my first solo book: <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info"><cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite></a>. It was an immediate hit and the response to continues to be tremendous even though it will turn four this coming May (which has to be like 80 in technology book years… many are outdated before they are even released).</p>

<!-- more -->




<div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Time and again, I return to <a href="https://twitter.com/AaronGustafson">@AaronGustafson</a>’s “Adaptive Web Design”. Like a North Star for user-focused web design.&#10;&#10;<a href="http://t.co/K1tbm6qAON">http://t.co/K1tbm6qAON</a></p>&mdash; Mark Llobrera (@dirtystylus) <a href="https://twitter.com/dirtystylus/status/530756679286423552">November 7, 2014</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>


<p>I think one of the main reasons the book has remained relevant for so long is because at its core, <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> is a <em>philosophy</em> book. Sure, there are some code examples here and there, but they only serve to demonstrate how you can apply progressive enhancement in your work. The philosophy of progressive enhancement works and only continues to demonstrate its brilliance with each new Web-enabled screen that debuts in the ever-expanding global marketplace. In fact, I’ll go out on a limb and declare that progressive enhancement is probably even more relevant today than it was when I wrote <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> in 2010.</p>

<p>As such, I’ve been thinking a lot about an update. So much has happened since mid-2010 when I was writing the book. Heck, I didn’t even address Responsive Web Design and only touched a little on mobile. Then there are things like single-page apps &amp; isomorphic JavaScript I’d love to discuss. <a href="http://opengraphprotocol.org/">Open Graph</a> &amp; <a href="http://schema.org/">Schema.org</a>… new tweaks to <a href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/intro/aria.php">the ARIA spec</a>… <a href="http://www.w3.org/html/wg/drafts/html/master/embedded-content.html#the-picture-element"><code>picture</code></a>, <a href="http://www.w3.org/html/wg/drafts/html/master/embedded-content.html#attr-img-srcset"><code>srcset</code></a> &amp; <a href="http://www.w3.org/html/wg/drafts/html/master/embedded-content.html#attr-img-sizes"><code>sizes</code></a>… the <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/shadow-dom/">shadow DOM</a>… <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/components-intro/">web components</a>… the list goes on and on. Progressive enhancement can help you better understand the pros and cons of all of these new advances and help you employ them while simultaneously keeping your projects on time and on budget.</p>

<p>My hope is that the second edition of <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> will be out an in your hands by the end of 2015. But in the meantime, <a href="https://adactio.com/journal/4956">taking a page from Jeremy</a>, I felt it was time to give away the first edition. You can now <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info/1st-edition/">read <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite></a>, in it’s entirety, from the comfort of your own browser… for free.</p>

<p>The HTML version of <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> is a nearly direct port of the XHTML I wrote for the hand-coded ePub. I made a few tweaks to make it a little more readable in the browser, but it’s all there including the videos. And yes, it makes use of progressive enhancement.</p>

<p>I hope you enjoy reading it as much as I enjoyed writing it and I look forward to getting you the revised and expanded second edition in the not to distant future.</p>

<p>PS &ndash; Easy Readers closed up shop at the end of 2014 and delivered the remaining paperback copies—of which there are only 50 or so—to me. If you missed out on getting a copy and would like to purchase one, <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/contact/">drop me a line</a> and I can sell you one. I’ll even sign it for you!</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Researching the Performance Costs of JavaScript MVC Frameworks]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/researching-the-performance-costs-of-javascript-mvc-frameworks/"/>
				<updated>2014-12-30T09:36:18-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/researching-the-performance-costs-of-javascript-mvc-frameworks</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I often talk about the negative performance impact of using front-end MVC frameworks like Angular and Ember to generate your HTML. It should be pretty obvious why: a framework must be downloaded, interpreted, and executed before any HTML is generated and eventually rendered in the browser. The one thing I had yet to do was actually see how the various frameworks stack up side-by-side. Now the <a href="http://www.filamentgroup.com">Filament Group</a> has done just that.</p>

<p>If you are using or are considering a front-end Javascript framework, you need to read this report.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.filamentgroup.com/lab/mv-initial-load-times.html">Read on Filament Group&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[A Maintainable Style Guide]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/a-maintainable-style-guide/"/>
				<updated>2014-12-29T18:29:18-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/a-maintainable-style-guide</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a fantastic overview of the modular architecture Lonely Planet is using to run their website and their style guide, keeping both perfectly in sync. The system that drives all of this, Rizzo, is <a href="https://github.com/lonelyplanet/rizzo">available on Github</a>.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://ianfeather.co.uk/a-maintainable-style-guide/">Read on Ian Feather’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[We Need More Empathy]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/we-need-more-empathy/"/>
				<updated>2014-12-28T11:17:21-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/we-need-more-empathy</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a while now I’ve been <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/AaronGustafson/designing-with-empathy-breaking-development-nashville-2013">beating the “empathy” drum</a> (<a href="http://www.lukew.com/ff/entry.asp?1810">notes</a>), trying to get folks in our industry to understand the importance of creating connections with the people for whom we build software, websites, etc. After all, we design and build tools to solve the needs of actual people, not some generic “user”.<!-- more --><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>It’s tough to connect with other people and we often fall into the trap of designing products for us and people like us. Jeffrey Zeldman characterizes the problem perfectly in <a href="http://www.zeldman.com/2014/12/28/unexamined-privilege-is-the-real-source-of-cruelty-in-facebooks-your-year-in-review/">his recent post</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>If we keep throwing only young, mostly white, mostly upper middle class people at the engine that makes our digital world go, we’ll keep getting camera and reminder and hookup apps—things that make an already privileged life even smoother—and we’ll keep producing features that sound like a good idea to everyone in the room, until they unexpectedly stab someone in the heart.</p></blockquote>

<p>Empathy is difficult when we are surrounded by others like us. We need to be surrounded by different people. Certainly gender and ethnic diversity is incredibly important here, but so is diversity of experience. As Jeffrey astutely points out, diversity in the room where Facebook’s “Year in Review” concept was given the green light would have—I have to hope—helped create some safeguards to keep some of their actual customers from being reminded of tragedies they experienced this year.</p>

<p>In all likelihood, the worst thing they probably discussed was an embarrassing hookup being celebrated, but I’ve had several friends lose children and loved ones this year, other friends battling serious illnesses, and still others who have suffered losses of different sorts. All bore their souls on Facebook in the past year and this feature has brought it back and, in some cases, <a href="http://meyerweb.com/eric/thoughts/2014/12/24/inadvertent-algorithmic-cruelty/">celebrated these tragic events in a very uncanny and dispassionate way</a>.</p>

<p>And Facebook isn’t the only company to blame for this sort of thing. Pretty much every social network suffers from similar issues. Reading the comments on the various press accounts of this story have revealed similar problems at <a href="http://arstechnica.com/business/2014/12/facebook-apologizes-for-morbid-results-with-its-year-in-review-nag/?comments=1&amp;post=28196195#comment-28196195">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="http://arstechnica.com/business/2014/12/facebook-apologizes-for-morbid-results-with-its-year-in-review-nag/?comments=1&amp;post=28196709#comment-28196709">Google+</a>, <a href="http://www.deathanddigitallegacy.com/2010/08/05/twitter-recommends-dead-friends/">Twitter</a>, and others. We can and need to do better.</p>

<p>In order to address these issues, we need to flex our empathetic muscles. We need to create connections with people who are not like us. People who live in different neighborhoods. People who come from different countries. People who require alternate means to accessing our sites and services. We need to see that the world is full of differences.</p>

<p>Life is full of great joy as well as great tragedy. When we acknowledge diversity of experience and actually embrace it, we become better designers.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I don’t mind the aggregate “users”, but “user” is too clinical and distanced for my tastes. Terms like “the user” keep us from connecting with the people who actually use our software and when we are disconnected from our users, we will not do a great job of solving their problems. And solving problems is the whole point of design.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[I Am Not Broken: The Language of Disability]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/i-am-not-broken-the-language-of-disability-bookworm-blues/"/>
				<updated>2014-12-23T12:49:09-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/i-am-not-broken-the-language-of-disability-bookworm-blues</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love this!</p>

<blockquote><p>The world we live in isn’t defined by two versions of reality. There isn’t the “normal” reality for all the normal people, and the slightly skewed reality for all of the rest of us who yearn for normalcy. Our fiction should reflect that. King George VI wasn’t any less of a powerful speaker or ruler for all of his stuttering. Odetta Holmes wasn’t slowed down by her wheelchair.</p>

<p>I’m not broken and neither are you.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.bookwormblues.net/2014/09/10/i-am-not-broken-the-language-of-disability/">Read on Bookworm Blues&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Autoplay, Don’t Do It]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/autoplay-dont-do-it/"/>
				<updated>2014-12-21T15:12:50-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/autoplay-dont-do-it</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back <a href="https://gigaom.com/2014/09/04/facebooks-autoplay-has-led-to-a-60-boost-in-traffic-on-mobile-networks/">GogOm reported on how Facebook’s decision to autoplay videos led to a 60% increase in mobile data usage</a>. It was a business decision with the intent of increasing engagement, but it was a bad decision from a user experience. It’s a tax on users and they weren’t to happy about it.</p>

<p>You may be wondering <em>Why is this a bad thing for users? They want to see videos, so we’re just giving them what they want.</em> Well, let me share a little story.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I was in Lisbon for <a href="http://lanyrd.com/2013/uxlx/">UxLx</a> last year and was on roaming data through my mobile provider. At the hotel, the Wifi was giving me trouble, so I opted to tether my computer so I can pull down a document I needed. Chrome crashed. Lame, but no big deal. I relaunched it and, Chrome being the helpful browser that it is, all of my tabs were restored and I got back to work.</p>

<p>A few minutes later I got a text message from my provider: I’d just used a tremendous amount of my data in a very short amount of time. And I had only landed an hour before. I was understandably concerned. And perplexed. What happened?</p>

<p>Well, it turns out one of the tabs that re-spawned after Chrome crashed was a page on YouTube. And on that page was an hour-long video. In HD. And it auto-played. I had the volume off and it was in background tab, so I had no idea.</p>

<p>YouTube’s “business decision” to autoplay their videos cost me real money. A lot of it.</p>

<p>Don’t autoplay. Any benefits you might see in user engagement are probably going to be drowned out by legitimate complaints from your users. Just don’t do it.</p>

<p>Incidentally, you can <a href="https://www.facebook.com/help/633446180035470">disable auto-play in Facebook</a>, but first of all you have to know it’s an option. Facebook gives you the choice of turning it on or off entirely or to turn it on only over Wifi. That may seem like a great compromise, but I’d like to put forward a few arguments as to why it’s not:</p>

<ol>
<li><em>Tethering:</em> If I am tethered to my phone, it is likely being done over Wifi. Even if my browser is aware that I am on Wifi and even if the website is paying attention to that (using the <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/netinfo-api/">Network Informaion API</a>), the website is probably going to get a false positive for Wifi even though the <em>actual</em> data connection is over a mobile network.</li>
<li><em>Metered Wifi:</em> Hotels and other providers often limit how much data you can use. You could be on an awesomely fast Wifi network, but if you are limited to 100MB—it happens—being on Wifi doesn’t matter.</li>
</ol>


<p>So again: Autoplay, don’t do it.</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Visualizing CSS3 Transformations]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/visualizing-css3-transformations/"/>
				<updated>2014-12-18T16:53:18-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/visualizing-css3-transformations</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s pretty amazing what you can do with <a href="http://dev.w3.org/csswg/css-transforms">CSS3 transforms</a> these days, but I often struggle with explaining the importance of function order when I am training people on how to use them. Transformation functions are a visual thing, so they require a visual tool to fully understand them and the implications of your function order decisions.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>To address this need, I put together <a href="http://codepen.io/aarongustafson/full/jEryLV/">a tool that dissects CSS3 transforms</a> so the transform process would be more clear for my students. I decided to throw it up on Codepen so you could learn from it as well. Why don’t you open that link and I’ll explain how it works. (Obviously, you’ll need to be in <a href="http://caniuse.com/#feat=transforms2d">a browser that supports transforms</a> for the tool to be useful to you.)</p>

<p>The tool starts you off with a simple three-function <code>transform</code> that includes both <code>translate</code> and <code>rotate</code> functions. If you hit the &ldquo;Show Me&rdquo; button, the browser will draw a box and step you through the application of the <code>transform</code> functions, one by one, animating their application so it’s easy to follow. This makes it pretty clear why an element ends up where it does.</p>

<p>Beside the &ldquo;Show Me&rdquo; button is the &ldquo;Rearrange&rdquo; button. It does exactly what you’d think: It rearranges the functions into a new, random order. If you press it and then press &ldquo;Show Me&rdquo; again, you can see if (and why) the element ends up in a different place. The original box remains ghosted out so you can see any differences.</p>

<p>Here’s a video of me playing around with the default <code>transform</code> stack:</p>

<p><figure id="fig-114921831" class="figure figure--video"><div class="video-embed video-embed--vimeo video-embed--16x9"><a class="video-embed__lazy-link" style="background-image:url(http://i.vimeocdn.com/video/500772734_1280.jpg)" href="//vimeo.com/114921831" data-lazy-video-src="//player.vimeo.com/video/114921831?autoplay=1"><div class="video-embed__lazy-div"></div><div class="video-embed__lazy-info">Dissecting CSS3 Transforms</div></a></div></figure></p>

<p>Have a play and let me know your thoughts. I hope you find this tool as helpful as I (and my students) have.</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Indecisiveness and URLs]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/indecisiveness-and-urls/"/>
				<updated>2014-12-16T10:23:15-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/indecisiveness-and-urls</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you know me, you know I am a pretty indecisive guy. It is not uncommon for <a href="https://twitter.com/shirleytemper">Kelly</a> and I to spend 15 minutes or more just trying to figure out where we want to grab a meal.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>What I’m trying to say (or rather excuse) is that I have been struggling with some of my initial decisions with respect to URLs on this site and finally decided to make some changes before too many links to its content get out there. I was a bit reluctant to do so as we all know <a href="http://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI.html">what Sir Tim Berners-Lee says</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Cool URIs don’t change.</p></blockquote>

<p>Well, consider me uncool as I decided to change some things around here:</p>

<ol>
<li>I dropped the year indicator from blog post URLs. I realized that the likelihood of me having two posts with the same name was pretty much nil, so it was unnecessary to disambiguate like that. Plus it would save me from having to create the annual archives I would feel compelled to make in order to justify the “2014” directory in the URL.</li>
<li>I consolidated my book and article pages to <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/publications">a single page or publications</a>. I thought it might be nice to maintain them separately, but in retrospect that seems unnecessarily complicated.</li>
<li>I changed the URL to my speaking engagements from “events” to “speaking-engagements” as it just made more sense.</li>
</ol>


<p>On the off chance you ever consider changing URLs on a Jekyll or Octopress site, I thought I’d share my process.</p>

<h2>Redirecting Old Links</h2>

<p>I was quite concerned concerned about old links being broken in this site. It’s just not a good thing to do.</p>

<p>In a traditional hosting scenario, I could use <code>.htaccess</code> to set up <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_302">302 redirects</a>, but I am hosting on Github so that isn’t an option. On top of that, this site is built using Octopress (and Jekyll), so there is no dynamic system in place to programmatically manage those redirects.</p>

<p>Thankfully, there is <a href="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll-redirect-from">a plugin for Jekyll to manage redirects</a>. With it, you can redirect from an an existing page in the YAML front matter using the <code>redirect_to</code> key or you can use the <code>redirect_from</code> key in the YAML front matter on the destination page. I ended up using the former for old pages (articles, books, and events), and the latter for blog posts.</p>

<p>The plugin covers all the bases. It generates pages at the old URLs that redirect using the good old <code>meta</code> refresh, a JavaScript redirect, and a fallback link just in case neither of those work. Oh, and it sets the new URL as the <a href="https://support.google.com/webmasters/answer/139066?hl=en">canonical reference</a> to boot.</p>

<p>Done and done.</p>

<h2>Keeping Webmentions</h2>

<p>As I mentioned a few weeks back, I wrote <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/enabling-webmentions-in-jekyll/">a Jekyll plugin to enable webmentions</a>. As web mentions are tied to the “mentioned” URL, changing a post’s URL was going to cause me to lose any previous webmentions. I didn’t like that idea, so <a href="https://github.com/aaronpk/webmention.io/issues/31">I talked to Aaron about adding multiple URL support to the webmention.io API</a> and he agreed it was a good idea.</p>

<p>The feature landed late last week and I adjusted <a href="https://github.com/aarongustafson/jekyll-webmention_io">my Jekyll Webmention.io plugin</a> to allow you to supply multiple URLs. While I was at it, I did some other upgrades: I added caching, downloading of webmention titles if the API didn’t supply one, and a test for the existence of avatars before inserting them (so you don’t end up with missing images).</p>

<p>If you were using the plugin, I definitely recommend upgrading as it performs a lot better now. I also added <a href="https://github.com/aarongustafson/jekyll-webmention_io/blob/master/webmention.Rakefile">a Rake task for sending webmentions</a> which is super handy.</p>

<h2>Pardon My Dust</h2>

<p>I apologize for changing URLs on you, but I am hopeful this will be the last major change on the site. As it (currently) says at the top, <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/a-grand-experiment/">this is an open redesign</a>, so there are bound to be a few bumps here and there. That said, I will try to keep them to a minimum in the future.</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Update Your SSH Keys on Github]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/update-your-ssh-keys-on-github/"/>
				<updated>2014-12-16T08:21:08-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/update-your-ssh-keys-on-github</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Honestly, it’s probably good to get into the habit of updating your SSH keys regularly anyway, but in case you needed a reminder:</p>

<blockquote><p>Back in February, we improved the security audit trail for SSH keys. Soon, organizations will be able to block access for SSH keys that were created prior to those improvements. If your application relies on deploy keys or user keys for repository access, we recommend replacing any keys created before February 24, 2014.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="https://developer.github.com/changes/2014-12-12-replace-older-ssh-keys-created-by-your-application/">Read on Github Developer&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
</feed>
