<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson - Latest Links]]></title>
	<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/atom-latest-links.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
	<updated>2015-05-26T15:21:27-04:00</updated>
	<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
	<author>
		<name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
		
	</author>
	<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Web vs. Native: Let’s Concede Defeat]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/web_vs_native_l/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-26T13:38:20-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/web_vs_native_l</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I could not agree more with PPK on this: Native apps and websites shouldn’t be in competition. Each has its pros and cons.</p>

<blockquote><p> If the user doesn’t want your icon on his home screen, if the user wants a just-in-time interaction, it’s the web they want — not because of any inherent technological superiority, but because it’s hassle-free. Go there, read, forget. No junk left on your phone.</p>

<p>Most businesses don’t stand a chance of ending up on the users’ home screens. So they need the web — but not a web that emulates native to no particular purpose.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.quirksmode.org/blog/archives/2015/05/web_vs_native_l.html">Read on QuirksBlog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Even Tiny Updates to Tech Can Be Obstacles for the Disabled]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/even-tiny-updates-tech-can-obstacles-disabled/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-26T13:33:43-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/even-tiny-updates-tech-can-obstacles-disabled</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://twitter.com/pdkotler">Paul Kotler</a> shares some of his struggles as a technology user with both autism and apraxia, including those you may not have considered:</p>

<blockquote><p>For me, every step forward in making things lighter and smaller is a new obstacle. Often, the buttons I need to hit are too small, the screen too sensitive, or the glare off the screen too distracting to allow me to make use of my device. Updates to operating systems or apps that create slight changes to the size and position of buttons throw me off for days. While these changes might go unnoticed by a typical user, I endure a relearning process that slows me down and makes it more difficult to communicate.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.wired.com/2015/05/even-tiny-updates-tech-can-obstacles-disabled/">Read on Wired&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Want to Become an Expert? Study (Web) History]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/want-to-become-an-expert-study-web-history/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-26T13:07:31-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/want-to-become-an-expert-study-web-history</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I could not agree more:</p>

<blockquote><p>This is about getting other web professionals to better understand our field. To be correct in what they say about the past, when trying to educate others. To not make false statements, based on lack of knowledge or direct experience, which lead to wrong assumptions and misinformed decisions about code and architectures.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.obiwankimberly.com/2013/09/17/want-to-become-an-expert-study-web-history/">Read on Obi-Wan Kimberly Blessing&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[World White Web]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/worldwhiteweb/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-26T12:36:38-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/worldwhiteweb</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This project—from a Swedish student—seeks to address the issue of the dominance of &ldquo;whiteness&rdquo; online by asking you to share pictures of non-white hands in order to make them more visible in Google Image Search. Admittedly, it’s a drop in the bucket when it comes to increasing the visibility of colored people online, but as Ovid famously said: “Dripping water hollows out stone, not through force but through persistence” (<i lang="la">Gutta cavat lapidem, non vi, sed saepe cadendo</i>).</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://worldwhiteweb.net">Read on World White Web - Take part in changing the search results for hand on Google.&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Tracking Protection in Firefox for Privacy and Performance (PDF)]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/tracking-protection-in-firefox-for-privacy-and-performance/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-26T12:24:11-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/tracking-protection-in-firefox-for-privacy-and-performance</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>New research from Columbia University and Mozilla reveals that Firefox’s &ldquo;Tracking Protection&rdquo; privacy tech has an added benefit of speeding up the web:</p>

<blockquote><p>Since Firefox does not download and render content from tracking domains, Tracking Protection also enjoys performance benefits of a 44% median reduction in page load time and 39% reduction in data usage in the Alexa top 200 news sites.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://ieee-security.org/TC/SPW2015/W2SP/papers/W2SP_2015_submission_32.pdf">Read on IEEE Security&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing for and With Windows Phone]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/testing-for-windows-phone/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-22T10:23:50-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/testing-for-windows-phone</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Testing on Windows phones can be tough. Tools like Adobe’s Edge Inspect don’t support it (yet… I hope that changes at some point) and if you aren’t a Visual Studio user, emulating a Windows phone can also be a challenge. Thankfully, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/BrowseEmAll">Daniel Herken</a> has put together this no-nonsense guide for testing Windows devices.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.smashingmagazine.com/2015/05/19/testing-for-windows-phone/">Read on Smashing Magazine&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Show Password: Lessons From a Failed Experiment in JavaScript Accessibility]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/show-password-javascript-accessibility/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-22T10:16:39-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/show-password-javascript-accessibility</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The brilliant James Edwards recounts the trials and tribulations of trying to make an accessible version of &ldquo;Show Password&rdquo; functionality.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.sitepoint.com/show-password-javascript-accessibility/">Read on SitePoint&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifold JS]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/manifoldjs/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-21T15:12:48-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/manifoldjs</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Write a web app once, deploy it as a hosted app to Android, iOS, Chrome OS, Firefox OS, and Windows. And it follows the W3C standard for web apps. It’s almost too easy.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://manifoldjs.com/">Read on &nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[15 Years Ago in ALA: Much Ado About 5]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/fifteen-years-ago-in-ala-much-ado-about-5k/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-21T14:56:10-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/fifteen-years-ago-in-ala-much-ado-about-5k</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this brief post, <a href="https://twitter.com/zeldman">Jeffrey Zeldman</a> reminds us of the importance of simplicity by deftly showing us where we’ve gotten ourselves:</p>

<blockquote><p>[D]riven by fear that apps would make the web irrelevant, we began relying on frameworks that made even the simplest website act and feel like a mind-blowing application. Serving reams of code we didn’t need because, hell, it came with the frameworks, and abandoning principles like progressive enhancement because, hell, everybody uses JavaScript, we soon fell in love with high-resolution, full-screen background images, then fell even harder when those images quadrupled in weight thanks to Retina.
And still the little article memorializing the little 5K contest sat online, its lessons forgotten in an arms race wherein the average home page now weighs over 2MB. Put that in your Edge network and smoke it.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://alistapart.com/blog/post/fifteen-years-ago-in-ala-much-ado-about-5k">Read on A List Apart&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Microsoft Wants to Keep Your Online Data Secure While You’re Using It]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/microsoft-vc3/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-20T15:11:08-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/microsoft-vc3</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I joined Microsoft, I had to go through &ldquo;privacy training&rdquo;. I was all <em>meh</em> about it, but then I took the course and realized just how much Microsoft cares about privacy. The training was thorough and insightful; it’s not an overstatement to say it truly blew my mind a little. I wish more companies cared as much. In fact, I wish every startup had to go through similar training before they could collect any user data.</p>

<p>Anyway, this new initiative seems pretty cool and I am proud to see Microsoft leading the charge in securing your files online, all the time.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.engadget.com/2015/05/18/microsoft-vc3/">Read on Engadget&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Facebook and the Media: United, They Attack the Web]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/media-websites-vs-facebook/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-20T14:59:35-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/media-websites-vs-facebook</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post from <a href="https://twitter.com/fakebaldur">Baldur Bjarnason</a> hits the nail on the head when it comes to the web vs. native. If you work on the web (as I suspect you do since you’re reading this blog), convert &ldquo;you&rdquo; and &ldquo;your&rdquo; to &ldquo;we&rdquo; and &ldquo;our&rdquo;:</p>

<blockquote><p>The web doesn’t suck. Your websites suck.</p>

<p><em>All of your websites suck</em>.</p>

<p>You destroy basic usability by hijacking the scrollbar. You take native functionality (scrolling, selection, links, loading) that is fast and efficient and you rewrite it with ‘cutting edge’ javascript toolkits and frameworks so that it is slow and buggy and broken. You balloon your websites with megabytes of cruft. You ignore best practices. You take something that works and is complementary to your business and turn it into a liability.</p>

<p>The lousy performance of your websites becomes a defensive moat around Facebook.</p>

<p>Of course, Facebook might still win even if you all had awesome websites, but you can’t even begin to compete with it until you fix the foundation of your business.</p></blockquote>

<p>This article is long and full of choice quotes and embodied wisdom. You should read it. Twice.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/notes/media-websites-vs-facebook/">Read on Baldur Bjarnason’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Desktop Conundrum]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/desktop-conundrum/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-20T14:52:10-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/desktop-conundrum</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this brief post, Dave Rupert muses about the future of &ldquo;desktop&rdquo;.</p>

<blockquote><p>I think there’s still value in knowing the upper limit of a website, but am filled with growing concern that the time and effort spent on that upper limit might prove to be all in vain.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://daverupert.com/2015/05/desktop-conundrum/">Read on daverupert.com&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Our Approach to Mobile-friendly Search]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/our-approach-to-mobile-friendly-search/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-20T14:09:40-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/our-approach-to-mobile-friendly-search</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bing cares about mobile-friendliness now too:</p>

<blockquote><p>Our approach to mobile friendliness as a ranking signal balances the need to improve the ranking for mobile-friendly pages, with the continued focus on delivering the most relevant results for a given query. This means that for mobile searches on Bing, you can always expect to see the most relevant results for a search query ranked higher, even if some of them are not mobile-friendly. While the changes will improve ranking for mobile-friendly pages, webpages that are highly relevant to the given query that are not yet mobile-friendly will not get penalized.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://blogs.bing.com/webmaster/2015/05/14/our-approach-to-mobile-friendly-search/">Read on Bing Webmaster Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Choosing Performance]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/choosing-performance/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-20T14:06:14-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/choosing-performance</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tim Kadlec nails it again in this piece on performance in light of Facebook’s &ldquo;Instant Articles&rdquo; announcement:</p>

<blockquote><p>Is the web just inherently slow and destined to never be able to compete with the performance offered by a native platform? (Spoiler: No. No it is not.)</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://timkadlec.com/2015/05/choosing-performance/">Read on Tim Kadlec’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Woah, I Can Test Edge & IE on a Mac & Linux!]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/woah-i-can-test-edge-ie-on-a-mac-linux/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-20T13:52:56-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/woah-i-can-test-edge-ie-on-a-mac-linux</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My colleague Rey Bango’s talk from <a href="http://devchannel.modern.ie/websummit2015">#msEdgeSummit</a> on how to test Microsoft Edge when you don’t work on Windows.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://blog.reybango.com/2015/05/15/woah-i-can-test-edge-ie-on-a-mac-linux/">Read on Rey Bango’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[The JavaScript Framework Bandwagonism]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/the-javascript-framework-bangwagonism/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-18T16:29:06-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/the-javascript-framework-bangwagonism</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Gold from <a href="https://twitter.com/teylorfeliz">Teylor Feliz</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>A lot of front-end developers don’t have a very strong resistance to change like website users, which is a good thing. But, some developers just need a Todo list demo to get excited and crazy to built an app with the new framework or tool. Some don’t wait for a framework to get out of beta or reach version 1.0 in order to build something with it. We need to learn to wait and let the tools mature so we can take full advantage or have a better idea of the path they are going to take.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://admixweb.com/the-javascript-framework-bangwagonism/">Read on admixweb&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Automatic Text Contrast With CSS Blend Modes]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/automatic-text-contrast-with-css-blend-modes/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-18T16:24:45-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/automatic-text-contrast-with-css-blend-modes</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Brilliant work by <a href="http://twitter.com/dudleystorey">Dudley Storey</a> on how to ensure text is always legible even when the background is unknown. Check out <a href="http://codepen.io/dudleystorey/pen/Xbdmjv">the accompanying CodePen</a> as well.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://demosthenes.info/blog/1029/Automatic-Text-Contrast-with-CSS-Blend-Modes">Read on demosthenes.info&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Financial Times Rolls Out ‘cost Per Hour’ Advertising Metric]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/financial-times-rolls-out-cost-per-hour-advertising-metric/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-18T16:21:02-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/financial-times-rolls-out-cost-per-hour-advertising-metric</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This could change the way we design pages by allowing us to move away from the NASCAR-esque badged web design employed by most major media outlets.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://aboutus.ft.com/2015/05/18/financial-times-rolls-out-cost-per-hour-advertising-metric/">Read on FT.com&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing the 12-inch MacBook’s Performance With Windows 10]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/12_inch_macbook_and_windows_10/"/>
				<updated>2015-05-18T00:01:53-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/12_inch_macbook_and_windows_10</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This was in interesting read from <a href="https://twitter.com/Alex_V_King">Alex King</a>. My favorite quote?</p>

<blockquote><p>[I]t&rsquo;s ironic that in some regards, the new MacBook runs Windows 10 (a prerelease version, at that) better than it runs OS X. But it&rsquo;s a testament to two things: Apple&rsquo;s fantastic MacBook hardware, which is forward-thinking yet surprisingly agile; and Microsoft&rsquo;s excellent Windows software, which entices and excites with its beautiful interface, useful new features, and rock-solid UI transitions.</p></blockquote>

<p>I have Windows 10 running in a VM. I haven’t tried it as a Bootcamp partition yet, but Alex’s finding are intriguing.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.alexvking.com/12_inch_macbook_and_windows_10.html">Read on Alex King’s Personal Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
</feed>
