<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson - Latest Links]]></title>
	<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/atom-latest-links.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
	<updated>2015-01-28T20:27:30-05:00</updated>
	<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
	<author>
		<name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
		
	</author>
	<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on Pagination]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/thoughts-on-pagination/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-28T17:51:36-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/thoughts-on-pagination</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pagination is pretty arbitrary. Could it be better? Probably.</p>

<blockquote><p>For example, take your average photo site that displays the content in a reverse chronological order: that is, newest to oldest. Let&rsquo;s say your friend has posted 2000 photos to this site. The site shows the viewer 10 things per page. With our prolific user, this gives us 200 pages.</p>

<p>Going to the middle of this content takes us to page 100. What does this mean, beyond we&rsquo;re at the middle? Not much.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="https://nolancaudill.com/2012/03/24/pagination/">Read on Nolan Caudill’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Why All Three Game Consoles Have Now Ditched the TV]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/why-all-three-game-consoles-have-now-ditched-the-tv/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-28T17:48:16-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/why-all-three-game-consoles-have-now-ditched-the-tv</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I hadn’t really thought about it with respect to gaming, but this has definitely been an interesting trend:</p>

<blockquote><p>More and more so, the programming we once watched on TV is migrating to our tablets and phones. Cable providers have apps that let customers access live television, and even the contents of their DVRs, on their personal devices. Comcast et al realize they must let you access that content where your eyeballs are, or you’ll find other content. Ditto Nintendo, Microsoft and Sony. Game consoles cannot be married to the TV.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.wired.com/2015/01/xbox-streaming-windows-10/">Read on Wired&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[WhatsApp Doesn't Understand the Web]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/whatsapp-doesnt-understand-the-web/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-27T11:35:18-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/whatsapp-doesnt-understand-the-web</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am not a WhatsApp user, but I have long been impressed with the way they embrace operating systems others ignore. I think it has been a key to their success and speaks to the &ldquo;accessibility&rdquo; (in the broader sense) of their service.</p>

<p>I am completely baffled by the design decisions they made in their Web client, as is Andre Alves Garzia.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://andregarzia.com/posts/en/whatsappdoesntunderstandtheweb/">Read on Andre Alves Garzia’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Inside Microsoft’s New Rendering Engine for the &quot;Project Spartan&quot;]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/inside-microsofts-new-rendering-engine-for-the-project-spartan-smashing-magazine/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-27T11:32:05-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/inside-microsofts-new-rendering-engine-for-the-project-spartan-smashing-magazine</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is Microsoft’s Jacob Rossi on how “Project Spartan” came to be and what is going on inside the browser that comes after Internet Explorer.</p>

<p>On that elated feeling of removing legacy code:</p>

<blockquote><p>[S]wathes of IE legacy were deleted from the new engine. Gone were document modes. Removed was the subsystem responsible for emulating IE8 layout quirks. VBScript eliminated. Remnants like attachEvent, X-UA-Compatible, currentStyle were all purged from the new engine. The codebase looks little like Trident anymore (far more diverged already than even Blink is from WebKit).</p></blockquote>

<p>On a faster dev cycle for the new browser:</p>

<blockquote><p>[W]e’ll treat Windows 10 as a service—keeping users up to date and delivering features when they are ready (“auto-update”), not waiting for the next major release. This means the new rendering engine will always be truly evergreen.</p></blockquote>

<p>On opening up the process:</p>

<blockquote><p>Another welcomed change that we’ve been rolling out over the past year is a promise for increased openness about our web platform plans and roadmap. Over the last year, you’ve hopefully experienced some of this through our open standards roadmap15 (one of my personal side projects), our Reddit AMA16, regular dialog through @IEDevChat17, and sharing preview builds18 very early in our development process. You’ll see more of this over the next year.</p></blockquote>

<p>Promising stuff all around. I am still wondering if we’ll eventually see the new browser appear on other operating systems (even if it’s  just the browser chrome and not the rendering engine—like Chrome on iOS). Time will tell.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.smashingmagazine.com/2015/01/26/inside-microsofts-new-rendering-engine-project-spartan/">Read on Smashing Magazine&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Flash of Faux Text]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/flash-of-faux-text/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-27T08:56:47-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/flash-of-faux-text</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In his continuing exploration of font loading optimization, Zach Leatherman proposes loading a Roman (i.e. normal weight, non-italic) font first and letting the browser synthesize (i.e. fake) the bold, italic, etc. variants to reduce the load time and reflow of the document and let users start reading as soon as possible. Then he lazy loads the additional font weights and styles so the browser can swap out the synthesized glyphs for the actual ones.</p>

<p>Super clever stuff Zach!</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://www.zachleat.com/web/foft/">Read on Zach Leatherman’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[All of This Has Happened Before and Will Happen Again]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/all-of-this-has-happened-before-and-will-happen-again/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-27T08:49:25-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/all-of-this-has-happened-before-and-will-happen-again</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another awesome post from Adrian Roselli on the perils of pushing for a one-browser (a.k.a. WebKit) world:</p>

<blockquote><p>Everyone who calls for WebKit in Internet Explorer is exactly the same kind of developer who would have coded to Internet Explorer 15 years ago (and probably happily displayed the best viewed in badge).</p>

<p>If you are that developer, then it will all be your fault when it happens again. When WebKit is no longer the hot engine. When Chrome loses its dominance. When Apple&rsquo;s market share falls to match the developing world. You will be to blame.</p>

<p>Do you think that won&rsquo;t happen? Just look to Android browser fragmentation, or WebKit failing to support a standard that Firefox and IE have nailed, or Chrome introducing its own proprietary features (can&rsquo;t find the link; it&rsquo;s coming), or failing to use best practices as it tries to carry the next big thing forward, or the complete lack of developer relations from Apple. We&rsquo;ve had over half a decade of warning signs.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s happening again, and every petulant, lazy developer who calls for a WebKit-only world is responsible.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://blog.adrianroselli.com/2015/01/all-of-this-has-happened-before-and.html">Read on Adrian Roselli’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Meet Vivaldi, a New Browser From the Former CEO of Opera]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/meet-vivaldi-a-new-browser-from-the-former-ceo-of-opera/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-27T08:45:00-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/meet-vivaldi-a-new-browser-from-the-former-ceo-of-opera</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>And here we have yet another new browser. Vivaldi is inspired by the Opera of old and is pretty feature-rich according to the article. I’ll give it a shot.</p>

<p>Vivaldi runs Blink under the hood (like Opera and Chrome), which lends credence to my theory that <a href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/competing-on-chrome/">soon browsers will compete on chrome, rather than standards implementations</a>.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://thenextweb.com/apps/2015/01/27/meet-vivaldi-new-browser-former-ceo-opera/">Read on The Next Web&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Web Devvy Ways to Practice Gratitude and Empathy]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/web-devvy-ways-practice-gratitude-empathy/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-26T12:43:01-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/web-devvy-ways-practice-gratitude-empathy</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A great post from Chris Coyier:</p>

<blockquote><p> I&rsquo;m starting to think empathy really is one of the most valuable skills (if you can call it a skill) that you can have. If you can put yourself in another persons shoes, you can imagine what it&rsquo;s like to use the things you make. That gives you mad UX skills. It means you can write a damn fine support email. You can make a meeting worth having. You can communicate clearly, because you can imagine what it&rsquo;s like to receive that communication.</p></blockquote>

<p>Empathy is where it’s at. Check out his list for ways to increase your &ldquo;devvy&rdquo; empathy.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://css-tricks.com/web-devvy-ways-practice-gratitude-empathy/">Read on CSS Tricks&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[CSS Bookmarklets for Testing and Fixing]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/css-bookmarklets-for-testing-and-fixing/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-26T11:38:34-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/css-bookmarklets-for-testing-and-fixing</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another fantastic resource from Adrian Roselli. This is a collection of diagnostic tools that</p>

<ul>
<li>Restore Link Underlines,</li>
<li>Restore Focus Outlines,</li>
<li>Find Inline Styles,</li>
<li>Find Duplicate ARIA Roles, and</li>
<li>Find Missing Alt Attributes.</li>
</ul>


<p>If this sounds cool, you may also like his <a href="http://blog.adrianroselli.com/2012/06/accessibility-bookmarklets-and-tools.html">Accessibility Bookmarklets and Tools</a>.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://blog.adrianroselli.com/2015/01/css-bookmarklets-for-testing-and-fixing.html">Read on Adrian Roselli’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[What's New in CSS Selectors 4]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/whats-new-in-css-selectors-4/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-26T11:32:16-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/whats-new-in-css-selectors-4</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Matt offers us a nice round-up of new selectors that will likely be a part of the <a href="http://dev.w3.org/csswg/selectors-4/">CSS 4 Selectors Module</a>. Notable additions:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://grack.com/blog/2015/01/11/css-selectors-4/#has"><code>:has</code></a> &ndash; select an element based on children it contains,</li>
<li><a href="https://grack.com/blog/2015/01/11/css-selectors-4/#matches"><code>:matches</code></a> &ndash; a more compact way to select elements via alternate selector paths,</li>
<li><a href="https://grack.com/blog/2015/01/11/css-selectors-4/#not"><code>:not()</code> in a stack</a> &ndash; lets you combine multiple selectors not to match, using commas.</li>
<li><a href="https://grack.com/blog/2015/01/11/css-selectors-4/#column-combinator--and-nth-column">Column selection</a></li>
</ul>

<p><a rel="full-article" href="https://grack.com/blog/2015/01/11/css-selectors-4/">Read on Matt Mastracci’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[On Use of the `lang` Attribute]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/on-use-of-the-lang-attribute/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-26T11:32:05-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/on-use-of-the-lang-attribute</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Adrian has put together a great overview of why <code>lang</code> is important and how many sites are using it. Here are a few takeaways:</p>

<blockquote>
    <ol>
        <li>VoiceOver on iOS uses the attribute to auto-switch voices.</li>
        <li>VoiceOver can speak a particular language using a different accent when specified.</li>
        <li>Leaving out the `lang` attribute may require the user to manually switch to the correct language for proper pronunciation.</li>
        <li>JAWS uses it to load the correct phonetic engine/phonologic dictionary — Handy for sites with multiple languages.</li>
        <li>NVDA (Windows) uses it in the same way as VoiceOver and JAWS.</li>
        <li>When used in HTML that is used to form an ePub or Apple iBooks document, it affects how VoiceOver will read the book.</li>
        <li>Firefox, IE10, and Safari (as of a year ago) only support CSS `hyphens: auto` when the `lang` attribute is set.</li>
    </ol>
</blockquote>


<p>Thanks for putting this together Adrian!</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://blog.adrianroselli.com/2015/01/on-use-of-lang-attribute.html">Read on Adrian Roselli’s Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Longdesc Alternatives in HTML5]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/longdesc-alternatives-in-html5/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-26T11:31:53-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/longdesc-alternatives-in-html5</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The insightful James Craig is compiling a list of alternatives to the <a href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-html-a11y/2014Jun/0115.html">troublesome <code>longdesc</code> attribute</a>. You should follow along.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://cookiecrook.com/longdesc/">Read on James Craig’s Website&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[How We Use Progressive Enhancement to Improve Our Email Templates]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/how-we-use-progressive-enhancement-to-improve-our-email-templates/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-26T11:31:38-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/how-we-use-progressive-enhancement-to-improve-our-email-templates</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Great stuff from some folks who know an awful lot about email:</p>

<blockquote><p>If there&rsquo;s a medium that lends itself to progressive enhancement, it&rsquo;s email. Given the contexts in which email content is parsed and displayed (and will be in the future), it pays to consider content first and independently from the presentation.</p>

<p>Traditionally, email designers have taken all sorts of scrappy approaches to ensuring that text in email &ldquo;looks the same across all clients&rdquo;. Your Gmail experience should be the same as your Outlook experience and so-forth. I&rsquo;d argue that &ldquo;reading the same across all clients&rdquo; is vastly more important and that when possible, visually lovely flourishes should be added, for the environments that support them.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="https://www.campaignmonitor.com/blog/post/4401/progressive-enhancement-in-email">Read on Campaign Monitor Blog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Angular Momentum]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/angular-momentum/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-26T11:28:38-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/angular-momentum</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jeremy perfectly captures my feelings on most client-side MVC frameworks:</p>

<blockquote><p>Angular is for making (possibly enterprise) applications that happen to be on the web, but are not of the web.</p></blockquote>

<p>It is possible to have your cake and eat it too if you go <a href="http://nerds.airbnb.com/isomorphic-javascript-future-web-apps/">the isomorphic JavaScript route</a> though.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="https://adactio.com/journal/8245">Read on Adactio’s Journal&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Project Spartan and the Windows 10 January Preview Build]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/project-spartan-and-the-windows-10-january-preview-build/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-22T14:21:33-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/project-spartan-and-the-windows-10-january-preview-build</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.jasonweber.com/">Jason Weber</a>, Group Program Manager of Internet Explorer, provides a little more insight into “Project Spartan” and how Microsoft plans to balance consumer and enterprise needs.</p>

<p>Because a picture is worth a thousand words:</p>

<figure id="2015-01-22-1" class="media-container">
    <img src="http://blogs.msdn.com/cfs-file.ashx/__key/communityserver-blogs-components-weblogfiles/00-00-00-38-71-metablogapi/3644.psatwjpb_2D00_image3.gif" alt="Dual rendering engine architecture animation">
</figure>

<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/ie/archive/2015/01/22/project-spartan-and-the-windows-10-january-preview-build.aspx">Read on IEBlog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Browsers, Services and the OS &#8211; Oh My…]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/browsers-services-and-the-os-oh-my-dot-dot-dot/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-22T14:19:02-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/browsers-services-and-the-os-oh-my-dot-dot-dot</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://christianheilmann.com">Christian Heilmann</a>’s take on <a href="http://news.microsoft.com/windows10story/">yesterday’s IE announcement</a>, including a bit of historical context and a look toward the future of browsers killing stand-alone apps.</p>

<blockquote><p>For me, however, the whole thing was a bit of an epiphany about browsers. I’ve always seen browsers as my main playground and got frustrated by lack of standards support across them. I got annoyed by users not upgrading to new ones or companies making that hard. And I was disappointed by developers having their pet browsers to support and demand people to use the same. What I missed out on was how amazing browsers themselves have become as tools for end users.</p></blockquote>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://christianheilmann.com/2015/01/22/browsers-services-and-the-os-oh-my/">Read on Christian Heilmann&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Yawn, &#8220;IE6 Must Die&#8221;, Yawn&#8230;]]></title>
				<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/yawn-ie6-must-die-yawn-dot-dot-dot/"/>
				<updated>2015-01-22T08:17:26-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/links/yawn-ie6-must-die-yawn-dot-dot-dot</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Way back in 2010, <a href="https://twitter.com/getify">Kyle Simpson</a> proposed that a new version of IE should live beside an older version to allow the new IE to prosper while the old one remains stable for enterprises that require its proprietary features:</p>

<blockquote><p>The IE (Consumer Edition) would at its heart be a very different browser than the IE (Platform Edition). Instead of releasing once every couple of years, IE-CE could release every couple of months. IE-CE could ditch all that legacy JScript extension junk (and ActiveX!) and fully conform to open web standards. They could embrace SVG, <code>canvas</code>, <code>video</code>, CSS3, and all the other amazing things that IE9 is only barely now giving us a glimpse of. Microsoft could stop being the joke of the open web community, stop playing catch up, and actually take the lead in helping innovate in the consumer browser space.</p>

<p>And all the while, they could keep (and from time to time, back-port to) IE-PE stable and reliable for the Platform world. IE-PE would be Microsoft’s proprietary extensions on the open-web consumer browser experience. IE-PE would serve the needs of corporations and sysadmins by giving them stability and security and not be bothered by all the “noise” of the rapidly changing consumer browser market.</p></blockquote>

<p>I wonder if he called it. Will “Project Spartan” live alongside IE11? I guess time will tell.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>PS &ndash; I love this opening rant from that post. I still feel this way, nearly five years later:</p>

<blockquote><p>I am so entirely bored by the “IE6 must die” movement External Link. All you people out there who think you’re on some high horse of morality and rightness for the web’s future — this is a complete waste of effort. It’s useless windbaggery and nonsense. To date, I don’t think a single user has ever upgraded their IE6 simply because some douche-bag developer told them to. You live in a bubble if that’s how you think the real world works.</p>

<p>And while we’re at it, you sites out there who intentionally abandon IE6 support, not because it makes sense for your site (and not because you’ve provided a reasonable fallback graceful degradation for the less fortunate), but instead just because you want to flip the finger at Microsoft… well, you suck. And you know who else sucks? The sites who intentionally employ techniques they know will cause IE6 to crash External Link, as sort of a holier-than-thou “screw you” to a user who still surfs any of the web with IE6.</p>

<p>Then there are those who feel that we can create self-fulfilling prophecies and that will make this problem go away. Or the nagging site banners and twitter icon overlays reminding everyone just how much of a jack ass you are about IE6. Yeah right. Amusing, I guess, but not productive.</p>

<p>Get over yourselves, already. There, I said it. Deal with it.</p></blockquote>

<p>I just give IE6 the mobile layout and no JS and call it a day.</p>
<p><a rel="full-article" href="http://blog.getify.com/yawn-ie6-must-die-yawn/">Read on getiblog&nbsp;&rarr;</a></p>]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
</feed>
