<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson - Latest Posts]]></title>
	<link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/atom-latest-posts.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
	<updated>2015-10-21T11:14:07-04:00</updated>
	<id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
	<author>
		<name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
		
	</author>
	<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

	
		
	
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[On Adaptive Web Design’s Second Edition]]></title>
				<link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/on-adaptive-web-designs-second-edition/"/>
				<updated>2015-10-20T11:43:16-04:00</updated>
				<id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/on-adaptive-web-designs-second-edition</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote the bulk of <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> in early 2010 while taking a much-needed break from client projects. I had originally slated for it to be released just before the holidays that year, but life happened and the book did not make it out into the world until mid-2011. Six months is a long time in the technical world, and especially on the Web. A year is forever.</p>

<!-- more -->

<style media="only screen">.figure--cover img{width:50%;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;}@media (min-width:37.5em){.figure--cover img{float:right;width:250px;margin:0 0 1em 1em;}}</style>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="figure figure--cover"><a href="https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/"><img src="https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/cover-320.jpg" srcset="https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/cover-320.jpg 320w, https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/cover-600.jpg 600w, https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/cover-800.jpg 800w, https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/cover-1024.jpg 1024w" sizes="(min-width:37.5em) 250px, 50%" class="book__cover" alt="" /></a></figure></notextile></div>

<p>Thankfully, <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> was never meant to be a technique book. As web design books go, technique books have perhaps the shortest lifespan. Heck, some are even out of date before they come off the press. Rather than going down that road, I consciously positioned my book as a web design philosophy book—the code samples were merely there to demonstrate how the philosophy could be applied to your work. That simple choice is probably why <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> continued to have strong sales year-after-year and it’s the reason that book continues to rank highly on many recommended reading lists.</p>

<p>Despite the accolades and the obvious longevity the First Edition has enjoyed, I’ve had the itch to update it for the last year and a half. It’s not that the content is stale, it’s more that I’ve adjusted how I frame certain ideas within the topic of progressive enhancement. For instance, I regret my decision to sequester accessibility within its own chapter in the First Edition; it made it too easy to skip, to consider an after thought, a bolt-on. I wish I had integrated it into every chapter. Because of when I wrote it, there was also a lot of stuff I didn’t get the chance to cover. For instance, HTML5 was also pretty new (and not yet a Recommendation) at the time and ARIA was still largely in flux, so I was only able to touch on bits and pieces of those. Ethan Marcotte’s seminal article “<a href="http://alistapart.com/article/responsive-web-design">Responsive Web Design</a>”—and <a href="http://abookapart.com/products/responsive-web-design">his follow-up book by the same name</a>—came out after I’d written my CSS chapter, so I didn’t have the opportunity to demonstrate how that approach aligned with progressive enhancement.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">1</a></sup> Similarly, there were a lot Ajax-driven sites out there, but the “single-page app” movement hadn’t quite begun yet, so I hadn’t been able to square it with the progressive enhancement philosophy either. Similarly, the argument for progressive enhancement hadn’t yet been boiled down to “no JavaScript”, so I hadn’t even thought to address that.</p>

<p>When I mused about the Second Edition, I knew I wanted it to be more comprehensive and thorough. I had skimmed over content strategy the first time round—another regret—so I opted to give content its own chapter this time. I integrated accessibility into each and every chapter, showing how considering the “special needs” of your users can be accomplished with the copy you author, HTML you write, CSS you apply, and JavaScript enhancements you make. (Accessibility is important and everyone needs to be exposed to its considerations, so I am very happy about that decision.) Finally, from an organizational standpoint, I knew I didn’t want to focus the lessons around a “project site”—I wanted to pull great examples of progressive enhancement from the wild and celebrate them.</p>

<p>My target length for the Second Edition was a modest increase from 135 pages to around 160. When all is said and done, it’ll be closer to 250. It’s a lot of content, but I did my best to keep it approachable, like a really good conversation we might share over a few drinks.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>I finished writing the Second Edition about a month and a half ago and have read and re-read it several times since then. I’m quite happy with the end result and I hope you will be too. I plan to get some of the content out there for you to read before deciding whether to purchase it, but in the meantime you can <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/">read more about it on the updated book site</a>. I also encourage you to check out <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/read/foreword.html">Jeremy Keith’s amazing Foreword</a>—which, admittedly, made me a little misty—and <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/reviews/">the sweet things Ethan and Tim Kadlec had to say about the book</a> after reading it.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Interestingly enough, Ethan’s book came out around the same time as <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite>, leading many people to think they were conflicting approaches, <a href="http://blog.easy-designs.net/archives/on-adaptive-vs-responsive-web-design/">which is hardly the case</a>. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>I like boozy cocktails, in case you were wondering. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Strapless]]></title>
				<link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/strapless/"/>
				<updated>2015-10-19T11:33:37-04:00</updated>
				<id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/strapless</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On Friday, <a href="https://twitter.com/ShirleyTemper">Kelly</a> and I were having a conversation over lunch about the ubiquity of Bootstrap. It’s a topic we’ve been kvetching about for the the last few years—we’ve grown tired of seeing the same site everywhere we look.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>It’s not that we have any issues with Bootstrap specifically. It’s a solid framework for rapidly prototyping an idea before deciding if it’s got legs. It’s also a great tool to learn from when considering your own pattern library. That said, we don’t think it should be used in the way it so often is: as the entirety of your front end design with only a teensiest amount of theming applied.</p>

<p>The reasons we aren’t big Bootstrap fans are manifold. <a href="https://twitter.com/hellofisher">Steve Fisher</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/yeseniaa">Yesenia Perez-Cruz</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/samanthatoy">Samantha Warren</a> and I hashed out a bunch of them in our SXSW panel <a href="http://schedule.sxsw.com/2013/events/event_IAP137">“The Real Responsive Process?”</a>. Here are a few of the highlights:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Bootstrap doesn’t solve your problems.</strong> Design is problem solving. The design decisions made by the creators/maintainers of Bootstrap solve <em>their</em> problems, not <em>yours</em>. You may share some of those problems—a need for responsive layouts, for example—but not others. You need a system that is tailored to solve your problems and only you (and your team) know what those problems are. Have you ever tried on an article of clothing that’s “one size fits all”? How well did it fit your body type? Unless you are absolutely average in all respects, probably not all that well. Solve <em>your</em> problems with <a href="http://daverupert.com/2013/04/responsive-deliverables/"><em>your own</em> Bootstrap-esque pattern library</a>.</li>
  <li><strong>Bootstrap offers more than you’ll need.</strong> Bootstrap contains a lot of components and design patterns. It was created to address a wide array of project needs (“one size fits all”, see above). As such, there’s a lot of code in there. The defaults with some basic theming put you at a minimum of around 200KB for the CSS, JavaScript, and fonts (and that doesn’t include jQuery, which is also required). <a href="http://getbootstrap.com/customize/">Customizing your Bootstrap build can help</a>, but if you’re gonna use Bootstrap in production, you need to ruthlessly rip out anything you aren’t using. That takes time. And then you need to maintain your customized version of Bootstrap, making upgrading to new versions of the framework painful.</li>
  <li><strong>Differentiating yourself from you competition is harder.</strong> Bootstrap sites have a very common look to them. You can easily pick them out of a lineup and they are especially prolific within the startup space. If you’re trying to separate your company from the pack, having a site that looks just like every other startup (including your competition) is probably not a great idea. Spend some time (and, yes, money) creating a design that matches your brand and reflects who <em>you</em> are.</li>
</ol>

<p>I’m not saying these things because I’m a Bootstrap hater. I’m not, I just think it’s a crutch for a lot of people and it’s led to an era of bland, look-alike design on the web I’d love to see us transcend.</p>

<p>In my conversation with Kelly, I jokingly said it would be funny to create a browser extension that removed Bootstrap’s CSS and JavaScript from any page that included it. Something subversive along the lines of <a href="http://archive.oreilly.com/pub/a/network/2000/07/21/magazine/css_anarchist.html">Eric Meyer’s hilariously destructive table layout and <code>font</code> demolishing user stylesheet</a> or <a href="https://github.com/richardharrington/disrupt-to-bullshit">Richard Harrington’s “disrupt” to “bullshit” converter</a>. On Friday I decided to see what I could throw together in 15 minutes and I dubbed the result “Strapless”. Using <a href="https://crossrider.com/">Crossrider</a>, I converted <a href="https://gist.github.com/aarongustafson/081d6e950c1f2cc57e22">some simple JavaScript</a> into an extension for <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/strapless/ninnlimehlghihnalgelhhafbmhlhojg">Chrome</a> and <a href="http://crossrider.com/download/ff/79799">Firefox</a>. I didn’t bother with Safari as I couldn’t justify spending $99 to add a prank extension to their catalog. I have a version for Internet Explorer, but the installer is failing, which I suspect is an issue with Crossrider.</p>

<p>Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
</feed>
