<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson - Latest Links]]></title>
	<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/atom-latest-links.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
	<updated>2014-12-30T10:11:15-05:00</updated>
	<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
	<author>
		<name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
		
	</author>
	<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Researching the Performance Costs of JavaScript MVC Frameworks]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.filamentgroup.com/lab/mv-initial-load-times.html"/>
				<updated>2014-12-30T09:36:18-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/researching-the-performance-costs-of-javascript-mvc-frameworks</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I often talk about the negative performance impact of using front-end MVC frameworks like Angular and Ember to generate your HTML. It should be pretty obvious why: a framework must be downloaded, interpreted, and executed before any HTML is generated and eventually rendered in the browser. The one thing I had yet to do was actually see how the various frameworks stack up side-by-side. Now the <a href="http://www.filamentgroup.com">Filament Group</a> has done just that.</p>

<p>If you are using or are considering a front-end Javascript framework, you need to read this report.</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[A Maintainable Style Guide]]></title>
				<link href="http://ianfeather.co.uk/a-maintainable-style-guide/"/>
				<updated>2014-12-29T18:29:18-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/a-maintainable-style-guide-ian-feather</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a fantastic overview of the modular architecture Lonely Planet is using to run their website and their style guide, keeping both perfectly in sync. The system that drives all of this, Rizzo, is <a href="https://github.com/lonelyplanet/rizzo">available on Github</a>.</p>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[I Am Not Broken: The Language of Disability]]></title>
				<link href="http://www.bookwormblues.net/2014/09/10/i-am-not-broken-the-language-of-disability/"/>
				<updated>2014-12-23T12:49:09-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/i-am-not-broken-the-language-of-disability-bookworm-blues</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love this!</p>

<blockquote><p>The world we live in isn’t defined by two versions of reality. There isn’t the “normal” reality for all the normal people, and the slightly skewed reality for all of the rest of us who yearn for normalcy. Our fiction should reflect that. King George VI wasn’t any less of a powerful speaker or ruler for all of his stuttering. Odetta Holmes wasn’t slowed down by her wheelchair.</p>

<p>I’m not broken and neither are you.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Update Your SSH Keys on Github]]></title>
				<link href="https://developer.github.com/changes/2014-12-12-replace-older-ssh-keys-created-by-your-application/"/>
				<updated>2014-12-16T08:21:08-05:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/update-your-ssh-keys-on-github</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Honestly, it’s probably good to get into the habit of updating your SSH keys regularly anyway, but in case you needed a reminder:</p>

<blockquote><p>Back in February, we improved the security audit trail for SSH keys. Soon, organizations will be able to block access for SSH keys that were created prior to those improvements. If your application relies on deploy keys or user keys for repository access, we recommend replacing any keys created before February 24, 2014.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[Celebrating CSS]]></title>
				<link href="https://adactio.com/journal/7653"/>
				<updated>2014-10-14T19:07:18-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/celebrating-css</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As usual, Jeremy sums up my thoughts perfectly:</p>

<blockquote><p>Personally, I don’t think there’s any reason to have variables in the CSS language; it’s enough to have them in pre-processing tools. Variables add enormous value for developers, and no value at all for end users.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
			<entry>
				<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Demons of On-Demand]]></title>
				<link href="http://techcrunch.com/2014/09/20/the-demons-of-on-demand/"/>
				<updated>2014-09-21T19:08:27-04:00</updated>
				<id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/the-demons-of-on-demand</id>
				<content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>We were promised flying cars; we were added to mailing lists.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
			</entry>
		
	
		
	
		
	
		
	
</feed>
