<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Browse by Tag: Wai-aria | Aaron Gustafson]]></title>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/tags/wai-aria/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-03T16:36:57-04:00</updated>
  <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ARIA Quicktip: Labelledby vs. Describedby]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/aria-quicktip-labelledby-vs-describedby/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-05T10:45:22-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/aria-quicktip-labelledby-vs-describedby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night, while we were enjoying a cool evening and a few drinks outside after day 1 of <a href="http://bdconf.com">BDConf</a>, <a href="http://adactio.com">Jeremy</a> asked me for some clarification on the ARIA attributes I had demoed as part of <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/AaronGustafson/falling-in-love-with-forms-bdconf-2014">my forms presentation</a> earlier in the afternoon. In particular, he was confused by how <code>aria-labelledby</code> and <code>aria-describedby</code> differ.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I hadn’t really thought about it before, but it’s a good question. They seem pretty similar in function, right? And both support a space separated list of one or more <code>id</code> references. It’s downright confusing.</p>

<p>My simple explanation was that, at least in terms of form fields, they differ in when they are read. The <code>aria-labelledby</code> attribute replaces the associated <code>label</code> element (which is, of course, associated with the field via the <code>label</code>’s <code>for</code> attribute). The <code>aria-describedby</code> attribute, on the other hand, is read after the field type is stated.</p>

<p>To demonstrate how all of this plays out, I threw together <a href="http://codepen.io/aarongustafson/pen/dmuoe/">a quick CodePen demo</a> that takes you through numerous ways you can use and combine these attributes. I also did a <a href="http://youtu.be/U8_VjI-Z1LA">screen recording to demonstrate how ChromeVox exposes these attributes</a>:</p>

<p><figure id="fig-U8_VjI-Z1LA" class="figure figure--video"><div class="video-embed video-embed--youtube video-embed--16x9"><a class="video-embed__lazy-link" style="background-image:url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/U8_VjI-Z1LA/0.jpg);" href="//www.youtube.com/watch?v=U8_VjI-Z1LA" data-lazy-video-src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/U8_VjI-Z1LA?autoplay=1&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;iv_load_policy=3"><div class="video-embed__lazy-div"></div><div class="video-embed__lazy-info">aria-labelledby vs. aria-describedby</div></a></div></figure></p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> <a href="https://twitter.com/stevefaulkner">Steve Faulkner</a> shared a doc that discusses <a href="http://rawgit.com/w3c/aria/master/html-aam/html-aam.html#accessible-name-and-description-calculation">how accessible names and descriptions are calculated</a>. Thanks Steve!</p>

<p><em>Note: I did discover a bug in ChromeVox wherein the content of the elements referenced in <code>aria-describedby</code> are not read when the field receives focus via the keyboard (using the <kbd>tab</kbd> key), but it does when it receives focus via the mouse. I’ve submitted <a href="https://code.google.com/p/google-axs-chrome/issues/detail?id=158&amp;thanks=158&amp;ts=1415202123">a bug report</a> to to the powers that be.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
