<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Browse by Tag: Adaptive Web Design | Aaron Gustafson]]></title>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/tags/adaptive-web-design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-18T22:33:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adaptive Web Design: Folded &amp; Gathered]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/adaptive-web-design-folded-and-gathered/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-12T13:16:27-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/adaptive-web-design-folded-and-gathered</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just got this photo from <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pub/tracey-croom/13/a6/985">Tracey Croom</a>, my production editor on <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/">the Second Edition of <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite></a> and I wanted to share it with you. Production is almost done and I should be getting my bound copies soon. I’m so excited!</p>

<figure id="fig-2015-11-12-01" class="media-container"><img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-11-12/01.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-11-12/01.jpg&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-11-12/01.jpg&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-11-12/01.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt=""><figcaption>A photo of the folded &amp; gathered pages of <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite>’s Second Edition.</figcaption></figure>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Adaptive Web Design’s Second Edition]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/on-adaptive-web-designs-second-edition/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-20T11:43:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/on-adaptive-web-designs-second-edition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote the bulk of <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> in early 2010 while taking a much-needed break from client projects. I had originally slated for it to be released just before the holidays that year, but life happened and the book did not make it out into the world until mid-2011. Six months is a long time in the technical world, and especially on the Web. A year is forever.</p>

<!-- more -->

<style media="only screen">.figure--cover img{width:50%;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;}@media (min-width:37.5em){.figure--cover img{float:right;width:250px;margin:0 0 1em 1em;}}</style>

<figure class="figure figure--cover"><a href="https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/"><img src="https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/cover-320.jpg" srcset="https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/cover-320.jpg 320w, https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/cover-600.jpg 600w, https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/cover-800.jpg 800w, https://aarongustafson.github.io/adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/cover-1024.jpg 1024w" sizes="(min-width:37.5em) 250px, 50%" class="book__cover" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>Thankfully, <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> was never meant to be a technique book. As web design books go, technique books have perhaps the shortest lifespan. Heck, some are even out of date before they come off the press. Rather than going down that road, I consciously positioned my book as a web design philosophy book—the code samples were merely there to demonstrate how the philosophy could be applied to your work. That simple choice is probably why <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> continued to have strong sales year-after-year and it’s the reason that book continues to rank highly on many recommended reading lists.</p>

<p>Despite the accolades and the obvious longevity the First Edition has enjoyed, I’ve had the itch to update it for the last year and a half. It’s not that the content is stale, it’s more that I’ve adjusted how I frame certain ideas within the topic of progressive enhancement. For instance, I regret my decision to sequester accessibility within its own chapter in the First Edition; it made it too easy to skip, to consider an after thought, a bolt-on. I wish I had integrated it into every chapter. Because of when I wrote it, there was also a lot of stuff I didn’t get the chance to cover. For instance, HTML5 was also pretty new (and not yet a Recommendation) at the time and ARIA was still largely in flux, so I was only able to touch on bits and pieces of those. Ethan Marcotte’s seminal article “<a href="http://alistapart.com/article/responsive-web-design">Responsive Web Design</a>”—and <a href="http://abookapart.com/products/responsive-web-design">his follow-up book by the same name</a>—came out after I’d written my CSS chapter, so I didn’t have the opportunity to demonstrate how that approach aligned with progressive enhancement.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">1</a></sup> Similarly, there were a lot Ajax-driven sites out there, but the “single-page app” movement hadn’t quite begun yet, so I hadn’t been able to square it with the progressive enhancement philosophy either. Similarly, the argument for progressive enhancement hadn’t yet been boiled down to “no JavaScript”, so I hadn’t even thought to address that.</p>

<p>When I mused about the Second Edition, I knew I wanted it to be more comprehensive and thorough. I had skimmed over content strategy the first time round—another regret—so I opted to give content its own chapter this time. I integrated accessibility into each and every chapter, showing how considering the “special needs” of your users can be accomplished with the copy you author, HTML you write, CSS you apply, and JavaScript enhancements you make. (Accessibility is important and everyone needs to be exposed to its considerations, so I am very happy about that decision.) Finally, from an organizational standpoint, I knew I didn’t want to focus the lessons around a “project site”—I wanted to pull great examples of progressive enhancement from the wild and celebrate them.</p>

<p>My target length for the Second Edition was a modest increase from 135 pages to around 160. When all is said and done, it’ll be closer to 250. It’s a lot of content, but I did my best to keep it approachable, like a really good conversation we might share over a few drinks.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>I finished writing the Second Edition about a month and a half ago and have read and re-read it several times since then. I’m quite happy with the end result and I hope you will be too. I plan to get some of the content out there for you to read before deciding whether to purchase it, but in the meantime you can <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/">read more about it on the updated book site</a>. I also encourage you to check out <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/read/foreword.html">Jeremy Keith’s amazing Foreword</a>—which, admittedly, made me a little misty—and <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/reviews/">the sweet things Ethan and Tim Kadlec had to say about the book</a> after reading it.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Interestingly enough, Ethan’s book came out around the same time as <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite>, leading many people to think they were conflicting approaches, <a href="http://blog.easy-designs.net/archives/on-adaptive-vs-responsive-web-design/">which is hardly the case</a>. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>I like boozy cocktails, in case you were wondering. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Revisiting (and Releasing) <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite>]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/revisiting-and-releasing-adaptive-web-design/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-05T14:10:49-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/revisiting-and-releasing-adaptive-web-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As you probably know, back in 2011 Easy Readers published my first solo book: <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info"><cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite></a>. It was an immediate hit and the response to continues to be tremendous even though it will turn four this coming May (which has to be like 80 in technology book years… many are outdated before they are even released).</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><div class='embed tweet'><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Time and again, I return to <a href="https://twitter.com/AaronGustafson">@AaronGustafson</a>’s “Adaptive Web Design”. Like a North Star for user-focused web design.&#10;&#10;<a href="http://t.co/K1tbm6qAON">http://t.co/K1tbm6qAON</a></p>&mdash; Mark Llobrera (@dirtystylus) <a href="https://twitter.com/dirtystylus/status/530756679286423552">November 7, 2014</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div></p>

<p>I think one of the main reasons the book has remained relevant for so long is because at its core, <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> is a <em>philosophy</em> book. Sure, there are some code examples here and there, but they only serve to demonstrate how you can apply progressive enhancement in your work. The philosophy of progressive enhancement works and only continues to demonstrate its brilliance with each new Web-enabled screen that debuts in the ever-expanding global marketplace. In fact, I’ll go out on a limb and declare that progressive enhancement is probably even more relevant today than it was when I wrote <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> in 2010.</p>

<p>As such, I’ve been thinking a lot about an update. So much has happened since mid-2010 when I was writing the book. Heck, I didn’t even address Responsive Web Design and only touched a little on mobile. Then there are things like single-page apps &amp; isomorphic JavaScript I’d love to discuss. <a href="http://opengraphprotocol.org/">Open Graph</a> &amp; <a href="http://schema.org/">Schema.org</a>… new tweaks to <a href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/intro/aria.php">the ARIA spec</a>… <a href="http://www.w3.org/html/wg/drafts/html/master/embedded-content.html#the-picture-element"><code>picture</code></a>, <a href="http://www.w3.org/html/wg/drafts/html/master/embedded-content.html#attr-img-srcset"><code>srcset</code></a> &amp; <a href="http://www.w3.org/html/wg/drafts/html/master/embedded-content.html#attr-img-sizes"><code>sizes</code></a>… the <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/shadow-dom/">shadow DOM</a>… <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/components-intro/">web components</a>… the list goes on and on. Progressive enhancement can help you better understand the pros and cons of all of these new advances and help you employ them while simultaneously keeping your projects on time and on budget.</p>

<p>My hope is that the second edition of <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> will be out an in your hands by the end of 2015. But in the meantime, <a href="https://adactio.com/journal/4956">taking a page from Jeremy</a>, I felt it was time to give away the first edition. You can now <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info/1st-edition/">read <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite></a>, in it’s entirety, from the comfort of your own browser… for free.</p>

<p>The HTML version of <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite> is a nearly direct port of the XHTML I wrote for the hand-coded ePub. I made a few tweaks to make it a little more readable in the browser, but it’s all there including the videos. And yes, it makes use of progressive enhancement.</p>

<p>I hope you enjoy reading it as much as I enjoyed writing it and I look forward to getting you the revised and expanded second edition in the not to distant future.</p>

<p>PS - Easy Readers closed up shop at the end of 2014 and delivered the remaining paperback copies—of which there are only 50 or so—to me. If you missed out on getting a copy and would like to purchase one, <a href="/contact/">drop me a line</a> and I can sell you one. I’ll even sign it for you!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
