<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Browse by Tag: Personal | Aaron Gustafson]]></title>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/tags/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-18T14:37:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ch-ch-ch-changes]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/ch-ch-ch-changes/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-30T10:14:40-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/ch-ch-ch-changes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Monday, February 2nd will be the start of a new chapter in my professional career: I will joining Microsoft as a standards evangelist.</p>

<p><em>Wha?!</em></p>

<p>The reasons for the move are manifold, but I will do my best to summarize by taking you on the journey I’ve been on and hopefully that will help you understand why I will be leaving agency life behind and joining a browser maker (and the makers of Internet Explorer at that).</p>

<!-- more -->

<hr />

<p>I’ve been working on the Web since 1996. That’s nearly 20 years of building everything from simple marketing campaign sites to emails to complex transactional websites and custom content management systems. In that time, I’ve gained skills on both the front end and the back end and rolled the 10,000 hour odometer at least a couple of times.</p>

<p>It’s been great. I love building things and I love helping our amazing clients put awesome information and services on the Web. But at the same time, I’ve enjoyed working with teams to help <em>them</em> solve their own problems even more than I’ve enjoyed solving them directly. It’s why I love speaking at conferences and running workshops: I love to see the lightbulbs come on over people’s heads!</p>

<p>Over the last few years, <a href="http://easy-designs.net">Kelly and I</a> have made a conscious effort to reduce the amount of production work we’ve been doing in favor of more consulting. And early last year we came to a sort of crossroads: We knew we could keep doing what we’d been doing and things would be good, but we weren’t feeling challenged anymore.</p>

<p>And so we began to brainstorm ideas of what we’d like to do in the next phase of our lives.</p>

<hr />

<p>Kelly came to the Web from an education and community organizing background, so she wanted to find a way to incorporate those with her technical knowledge. And about two months ago, she got that opportunity and she took a position as the Program Manager for <a href="http://techgoeshomecha.org/">Tech Goes Home Chattanooga</a>, an organization committed to bridging the digital divide in our fair city.</p>

<p>When I close my eyes and think about what makes me happiest, it’s writing, speaking, and spreading the word about web design best practices. The folks I know who get to do that full-time tend to be developer evangelists (or <a href="http://adactio.com">Jeremy</a>). And so I began pondering that possibility.</p>

<p>As I went through the list of browser makers in my mind, Microsoft stuck out.</p>

<p>Some of you might think that’s odd. I mean come on, IE has been the red-headed stepchild of the web design world for the better part of a decade. Why on earth would I want to work there?</p>

<p>Well, I’ll tell you: Despite its market largesse, IE (and in many ways Microsoft) is operating like the scrappy upstart. And I root for underdogs.</p>

<hr />

<p>I think back to the early days of the Web when I would need a Windows license for every virtual machine I wanted to run in order to test each browser version. It was a pain in the ass and made me curse Microsoft on a regular basis.</p>

<p>But things have changed. A lot.</p>

<p>A few years back, the IE team launched <a href="http://modern.ie">modern.IE</a>, an awesome resource with VMs that were free for the taking. They also launched <a href="https://www.modern.ie/en-us/report">a free tool for identifying coding issues and checking cross-browser interoperability</a>. Then they opened up <a href="http://status.modern.ie">the roadmap for standards implementations in IE</a>. And just recently they gave us <a href="https://remote.modern.ie/">RemoteIE</a> and did away with the need for VMs altogether (at least to test our stuff on the latest version of IE).</p>

<p>This is a very different Microsoft.</p>

<p>Now sure, there’s still more they could open up, but this is progress. Big ships are slow to turn, but this ship is turning.</p>

<p>I want to be a part of that.</p>

<hr />

<p>I will be joining Microsoft as a “Senior Program Manager”, but titles don’t matter much to me. I see my job boiling down to a few key things:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Helping web designers and developers better understand the possibilities of the Web;</li>
  <li>Advocating for interoperable, accessible web design best practices;</li>
  <li>Being a voice for the web design and development community to communicate their needs to the IE team in order to improve the browser; and</li>
  <li>Being an internal advocate for Web standards implementations in other Microsoft products (think Visual Studio, Outlook, Word).</li>
</ol>

<p>Microsoft is not hiring me to be a salesman—<em>thank god, they’d be pretty disappointed</em>—they are hiring me to continue being me. I will continue writing, I will continue speaking, and I will continue educating. The only thing that has changed is that I can spend all of my time doing that, rather than having to balance it with client work.</p>

<hr />

<p>So Monday starts a new chapter in my career. It’s a little scary (I haven’t worked for someone else for over a decade), but it is also exciting. I am comforted by the fact that I am joining an amazing team: As he announced yesterday, <a href="http://christianheilmann.com/2015/01/29/on-towards-my-next-challenge-2/">Christian Heilmann will also join Microsoft on the 2nd</a> and the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YAIPCp_BOGU">charismatic Rey Bango</a> will be leading our merry little conga line.</p>

<p>I’m excited about the future and I’m thrilled to be given the opportunity to focus on making the Web better… for everyone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sending Birthday Well-wishes to Molly]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/sending-birthday-well-wishes-to-molly/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-25T10:20:25-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/sending-birthday-well-wishes-to-molly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is the birthday of an amazing woman, <a href="http://molly.com">Molly Holzschlag</a>, and she needs our help!</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>If you’re relatively new to the Web, you may not recognize her name, but you are benefiting from her legacy. You see, Molly has been a force of nature on the Web for the better part of two decades. She was an <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20000229205046/http://www.molly.com/molly/news.html">early blogger</a>. She was our fearless leader at the <a href="http://webstandards.org">Web Standards Project</a> for three years. <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/search?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;index=books&amp;keywords=molly%20holzschlag&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;tag=easydesign-20&amp;linkId=BDCVT2YGNT7BNCHR">Molly wrote <em>35 books</em> on Web design, CSS, and other Web standards-related topics</a>. She’s presented at conferences the world over and educated thousands of Web designers and developers during her tenure. And Molly was way ahead of us when it came to understanding the Web:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Everyone has something to contribute to the World Wide Web. Why? Because the Web is of us. Whatever we are as humans is now manifest in the Web: Our beauty, hatred, fragility and ferocity; our kindness, cruelty, confusion and clarity. Our wars. Our peace.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You might think that with all this acclaim, Molly must be pretty well off. Well, that’s not the case. Molly was far more concerned about the good of the Web than fancy jobs, lofty titles, and hefty paychecks. She did much of her work for free. In fact, she even ran a free “train the trainer” camp wherein she hosted a group of college-level educators <em>at her home</em> to get them up to speed on what they needed to know and what they should be teaching the next generation of Web designers.</p>

<p>I met Molly in 2003 when I was invited to speak at COMDEX. It was my first conference talk (and professional speaking gig) ever. I gave a talk on XHTML and she same up and complimented me on it. I had been incredibly nervous, so hearing someone so experienced compliment me on my material, it relieved my stress and made me feel better about by performance. And when she asked me to join her on stage for her next talk—her co-presenter Eric Meyer had to cancel last-minute—I was overjoyed. I don’t know that I added much to her CSS discussion, but I was so appreciative when she took me under her wing.</p>

<p>In 2005 we shared the stage again as we went on a five-city tour, giving 3 days of in-depth HTML, CSS, and JavaScript workshops. I learned a ton from Molly about presenting and she became the big sister I never had. My champion. My mentor.</p>

<p>I know I am not the only one with a story like this. Molly has touched so many Web designers’ and developers’ lives—both directly and indirectly—with her knowledge, compassion, and mentorship.</p>

<p>In 2013, Molly fell ill at a Web conference. She’s spent the last two years in recovery from intense chemotherapy and the damage it did to her body. She is incredibly weak, unable to work, and needs our help to pay for her basic living and medical expenses. So I ask you: Please dig deep and contribute to <a href="http://www.gofundme.com/ThanksMols">the GoFundMe campaign</a> Kimmie Blessing has set up on her behalf.</p>

<p>For all that Molly has done for us, let’s <a href="http://www.gofundme.com/ThanksMols">do something for her</a>.</p>

<p>Happy birthday Molly! We love you, miss you, and hope you come back to us soon!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creepy Namefellow]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/creepy-namefellow/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-22T17:27:27-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/creepy-namefellow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So yeah, this happened:</p>

<figure id="2015-01-22-2" class="media-container">
	<img src="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-01-22/creepy-sm.png" srcset="/i/posts/2015-01-22/creepy-lg.png 1062w, /i/posts/2015-01-22/creepy-md.png 600w, /i/posts/2015-01-22/creepy-sm.png 320w" alt="" />
	<figcaption>
		<p>The @GustafsonAaron Twitter account only follows 5 people, and they are all named “Aaron Gustafson”.</p>
	</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It’s a little creepy, I won’t lie.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
