<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Browse by Tag: Conferences | Aaron Gustafson]]></title>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/tags/conferences/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-06T16:45:40-04:00</updated>
  <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Top Takeaways From the 2016 Edge Web Summit]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/my-top-takeaways-from-the-edge-web-summit-2016/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-06T15:18:15-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/my-top-takeaways-from-the-edge-web-summit-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier this week, my colleagues on the Microsoft Edge team put on the second of what has now become an annual event: The Edge Web Summit. The format was a little different this year, with team members from across the organization delivering quick, punchy 30-minute talks on topics ranging from standard implementations to the user experience of a browser to real-time communications. I live-tweeted quite a few of the talks, but I thought I’d provide a bit of a round-up of what was revealed, discussed, and more so you can read it all in one place.</p>

<!-- more -->

<ul>
  <li>Since launching Edge 8 months ago, the team has pushed 12 update releases, 128 new features, and 6,527 bug fixes!</li>
  <li>The team has launched a new, highly transparent bug tracker for Edge: <a href="https://developer.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-edge/platform/issues/">issues.microsoftedge.com</a>.</li>
  <li>The Edge team has done a ton of research into what specs are being used and how they are being used on the open Web. They are starting to share this information on <a href="https://developer.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-edge/platform/data/">data.microsoftedge.com</a>. It currently consists of 2 parts: 1) <a href="https://developer.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-edge/platform/usage/">usage data</a> from real sites that looks at not only CSS properties in use, but values too; and 2) <a href="https://developer.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-edge/platform/catalog/">a catalog of available APIs</a> and a detailed analysis of browser support, down to specific configuration and property values.</li>
  <li>Hot on the tails of <a href="https://developer.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-edge/tools/remote/">RemoteIE</a> opening up for Linux users, RemoteEdge is coming soon! Jacob Rossi showed <a href="https://twitter.com/aarongustafson/status/717022717652828163">a screenshot of an Edge instance running on Azure, within Chrome</a>. So cool!</li>
  <li><a href="https://dvcs.w3.org/hg/speech-api/raw-file/tip/speechapi.html#tts-section">Text-to-speech</a> directly from within JavaScript!</li>
  <li>The <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Fetch_API">Fetch API</a>!</li>
  <li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Navigator/sendBeacon">Beacons</a> as an alternative to blocking JavaScript requests for telemetry data: <code>navigator.sendBeacon( uri, data )</code>.</li>
  <li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Notifications_API">Web notifications</a>!</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/WOFF2/">WOFF 2</a> font support for better compression and faster downloads/decompression!</li>
  <li>The team is currently prototyping and investigating <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/service-workers/">Service Workers</a>, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Push_API">Push Notifications</a>, <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/shadow-dom/">Shadow DOM</a>, <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/custom-elements/">Custom Elements</a>, <a href="https://www.w3.org/Payments/">Web Payments</a>, <a href="https://www.w3.org/community/webassembly/">Web Assembly</a>, and <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Statements/import">ES Modules</a>.</li>
  <li>Cortana in Edge has gotten some major upgrades, such as being able to “Ask Cortana” about an image to get more information (like a recipe for the cookies you saw on Pinterest that did’t include a link).</li>
  <li>Microsoft open-sourced <a href="https://github.com/MicrosoftEdge/css-usage">the CSS crawler powering their data portal</a> so other browser vendors can run it too.</li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FIDO_Alliance">FIDO</a>-based login (like <a href="http://windows.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-10/getstarted-what-is-hello">Windows Hello</a>) is coming to the Web!</li>
  <li><a href="http://windows.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hear-text-read-aloud-narrator">Microsoft’s Narrator</a> screen reader now supports a “Developer Mode” that blanks out the current app (such as your browser window) in order to enable you to more easily debug accessibility issues.</li>
  <li>The F12 tools in Edge now enable you to view the previously mysterious <a href="https://www.paciellogroup.com/blog/2015/01/the-browser-accessibility-tree/">Accessibility Tree</a> in addition to allowing you to drill more deeply into the various properties of an element that relate to its accessibility.</li>
</ul>

<p>I didn’t take a ton of notes in the second half of the day as I was prepping for <a href="https://channel9.msdn.com/Events/WebPlatformSummit/edgesummit2016/ES1612">my own session on accessibility</a>, but other highlights included building &amp; debugging <a href="https://blogs.windows.com/msedgedev/2016/03/17/preview-extensions/">extensions for Edge</a> (tldr; you can easily port Chrome extensions) and cool things you can do using <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/Continuum">Continuum</a>.</p>

<p>Overall, the event was incredibly informative and has me really excited about the work the Edge team is doing and where the browser is going. The new stuff that‘s ready for prime time will be out for the public in <a href="https://blogs.windows.com/windowsexperience/2016/03/30/windows-10-anniversary-update-brings-new-experiences-and-developer-opportunity/">the Anniversary Update of Windows 10</a> this Summer, but some of it is has already landed in <a href="https://insider.windows.com/">Windows Insider</a> builds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Event Apart Nashville 2016, Day One]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/an-event-apart-nashville-2016-day-one/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-16T10:54:59-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/an-event-apart-nashville-2016-day-one</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Unfortunately, I was unable to spend Tuesday in Nashville for An Event Apart (for reasons that will be revealed in about a month), but I did catch Monday and it was amazing.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The esteemed <a href="http://www.zeldman.com/">Jeffrey Zeldman</a> kicked the day off with a talk entitled <em>Designing with Web Standards in 2016</em>. A theme he touched on repeatedly was that none of the problems we are facing in web design today are new problems. It’s a topic near and dear to my heart, something I wrote about in the closing chapter of <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info/2nd-edition/"><cite>Adaptive Web Design’s</cite> Second Edition</a> and <a href="/notebook/learn-from-the-past-enhance-for-the-future/">recently spoke about at EnhanceConf in London</a>. He knocked this one out of the park and my head was nodding so much my neck began to hurt.</p>

<p>Next up was <a href="http://www.webstandards.org/about/members/">my former WaSP colleague</a> <a href="https://rachelandrew.co.uk/">Rachel Andrew</a> to give us the skinny on CSS Grid Layouts. This is an amazing spec that I’ve always struggled to understand fully (despite the fact that’s i’ve written a Javascript polyfill for it). Rachel made it crystal clear and got me very excited about the future of layout on the Web.</p>

<p><a href="http://jensimmons.com/">Jen Simmons</a> dropped some serious CSS-related design knowledge bombs that perfectly complimented Rachel’s talk. She discussed Flexbox, CSS Shapes, Multi-column layout, viewport units and more, demonstrating how they can be used right now to progressively enhance the design of your sites.</p>

<p>After lunch, <a href="http://bradfrost.com/">Brad Frost</a> took to the stage to talk about Style Guides. I only caught the last half—I’ll admit to doing some last-minute rehearsing in the hallway—but the bits I did catch were good. I’ve seen his Atomic Design talk a few times, which this one builds on. In this talk he touches on a lot of the atomic design concepts, but he also talked a lot more about workflow and the role of the front-end developer. No doubt the evolution of this talk has come in large part through writing <a href="http://atomicdesign.bradfrost.com/">a book on Atomic Design</a> and in hosting <a href="http://styleguides.io/podcast/">a podcast with Anna Debenham on website style guides</a>.</p>

<p>Next, I was given the opportunity to share some thoughts and advice on designing and building. My talk, <em>The Features of Highly Effective Forms</em>, evolved out of several earlier talks on building forms. With this one, I wanted to strike a little more balance between the nuts and bolts of building forms and the hows and whys of building better forms.</p>

<p>The deck, <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/AaronGustafson/the-features-of-highly-effective-forms-an-event-apart-nashville-2016">which I’ve posted to SlideShare</a>, doesn’t stand on its own quite as well as some of my other forms decks simply because the talk contained a lot of storytelling I chose not to pair with slides—instead opting for an black screen so folks could focus—but I did call out the salient points. I’ve begun writing up some of the recommendations as part of my <a href="/notebook/tags/web-forms/">Modern Web Forms Best Practices series</a> and will continue to do so in the future. And one of the stories I told, which I highly recommend you check out, had to do with <a href="/notebook/consider-how-your-forms-read/">a lesson Facebook learned in managing how users report offensive photos</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://bigmedium.com/">Josh Clark</a> wrapped the day up with a discussion of the future of interface as things move from digital back to physical. He talked about a lot of really cool new tech that has me excited about the future, including <a href="https://google.github.io/physical-web/">the Physical Web</a>, which Josh had running as a live demo. I wonder if anyone noticed I had a beacon running too ;-)</p>

<p>All in all, day one was a blast. As always, Jeffrey, Eric, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/toby-malina-6247a028">Toby</a>, and <a href="http://www.escapadeproductions.com/">Marci</a> do an awesome job programming their events. I’m really bummed I could not stick around to see <a href="http://valhead.com/">Val</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/grigs">Jason</a>, <a href="http://www.kryshiggins.com/">Krystal</a>, <a href="http://meyerweb.com/">Eric</a>, <a href="http://braintraffic.com/">Kristina</a>, and <a href="http://cameronmoll.com/">Cameron</a> rock it out though. I’m sure it was amazing.</p>

<p>You can check out attendees thoughts from the event by <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23aeansh&amp;src=typd">searching Twitter using the #aeansh hashtag</a>. I’ve <a href="https://storify.com/AaronGustafson/reactions-and-takeaways-from-my-aeansh-talk">collected reactions to my talk on Storify</a> for posterity as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Planning Adaptive Interfaces: The Workshop]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/planning-adaptive-interfaces-the-workshop/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-21T18:56:05-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/planning-adaptive-interfaces-the-workshop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the last few years I’ve been running a workshop alternately titled “Planning Adaptive Interfaces” or “Beyond Responsive”, depending on the conference. It’s been one of my favorite workshops to run for a number of reasons, but before I get into that, let me explain what it is and how it works.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I think we all recognize how much Ethan’s seminal article <a href="http://alistapart.com/article/responsive-web-design">“Responsive Web Design”</a> (and <a href="https://abookapart.com/products/responsive-web-design">his follow-up book</a>) shook up our industry. It changed the way we look at visual design and kindled (or in some cases re-kindled) an interest in catering an experience to mobile devices. But simply incorporating responsive design’s three core strategies—fluid grids, flexible media, media queries—is not the goal; meeting our user’s needs is. Responsive design is not an end in itself… it’s just the beginning.</p>

<p>We need to embrace the heterogenous nature of the Web—myriad connected devices with vastly different screen sizes (if they even have screens), network connectivity, and capabilities in use by countless individuals, each with their own special needs—and craft experiences that will work anywhere at any time. We need to build robust systems that adapt in ways far beyond aesthetics. I designed this workshop to explore the rich variety of use cases that often get overlooked in the course of building web projects and to show how we can begin considering them as early as possible.</p>

<p>When I was starting out, I gave “workshops” that basically amounted to a half-day or (worse) a full day for folks to listen to me blather on about one topic or another. People liked them, but I wouldn’t call them fun. And, in hindsight, I question how much value people got from an extended survey of what’s possible without the opportunity to put that knowledge to use. Workshops should encourage attendees to get their hand dirty.</p>

<p>I kick this workshop off with a relatively brief discussion of the considerations that we should be aware of—beyond screen size and pixel density. I also provide examples of how to adapt interfaces so they rise to meet our customers’ needs. Then I throw out a list of common interface patterns—modals, tabs, etc.—and turn the floor over to the attendees, asking them to build small teams that each examine a single pattern in detail with these considerations in mind. They then spend the rest of the workshop planning out how that interface would adapt to consider factors like accessibility, screen dimensions, device capabilities, JavaScript availability, and so on. All the while, I circulate among the groups, asking and answering questions, pressing them to go a little further with each iteration. Some teams sketch, some prototype, and all spend a lot of time debating, which is awesome!</p>

<p>I leave the last hour or so for a group discussion of what each team’s accomplished. It gives them a chance to talk through their approach, what they learned, what their pain points were, and how they overcame them. Not does it celebrate their work, but it helps the other attendees discover novel ways to approach these common UI constructs.</p>

<p>It’s been a blast and I have learned so much from the teams I’ve coached. Each workshop is completely different because each group of attendees is completely different. I’ve run it with groups ranging from 12 to 120, for internal teams at large companies to mixed audiences from all over the world. Everyone who has attended one of these workshops has brought a unique perspective and helped us all get better at our jobs. That’s been one of the best parts of this experience for me.</p>

<p>If a workshop like this sounds up your alley, I’ll be giving it a few more times in 2016. Your next opportunity will be at <a href="http://enhanceconf.com/workshop.html">EnhanceConf in London in early March</a>. Later in the year, I’ll be giving it as part of <a href="https://buildright.io/maker-series/2016/aaron-gustafson">Sparkbox’s Build Right: Maker Series</a>. I’d love the opportunity to work with you if you can make it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Progressive Enhancement Gets a Conference]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/progressive-enhancement-gets-a-conference/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-15T10:00:51-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/progressive-enhancement-gets-a-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On March 4th, I’ll be in London to give the closing talk at <a href="http://enhanceconf.com/">EnhanceConf</a>, the first conference dedicated progressive enhancement. Over the last few months, I’ve been talking to the conference’s organizer, <a href="https://twitter.com/simonmcmanus">Simon McManus</a>, quite a lot. He’s put a lot of thought into the conference and I thought it might be interesting to  interview him so he could share his motivations and hopes for the event.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Me:</b> As a philosophy, progressive enhancement has been around for more than a dozen years. Why do you think it needs a conference now?</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Simon:</b> I first started thinking about EnhanceConf in 2014. At the time, Tom Dale had declared progressive enhancement dead and I had just heard Henrik Joreteg telling his Single Page Story.I was hearing lots of talk about progressive enhancement being hard and expensive when my experience showed quite the opposite.</p>

<p>It’s been fascinating to watch how views have changed since, Tom Dale now loves progressive enhancement and Henrik likes to do as much of his rendering at build time as possible.</p>

<p>As the web continues to grow in weird and wonderful ways techniques like progressive enhancement just keep giving more and more value.</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Me:</b> What does progressive enhancement mean to you?</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Simon:</b> I try to build applications that provide the best possible experience to the end user. Regardless of who they are, where they are or what device they are using. For me, that means using progressive enhancement in every part of the stack.</p>

<p>Progressive enhancement is about so much more than whether an app work with JavaScript turned off, realising we don’t have control over the runtime environment and building applications in the most robust way possible is far more important.</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Me:</b> Do you think it’s an approach that everyone should use on every web project?</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Simon:</b> I guess that depends on what you mean by a web project. In my mind to work on the web, you have to give up that illusion of control. You need to assume as little as possible about the device or user and for me that fits very well with progressive enhancement.</p>

<p>Web technologies transcend the capabilities of any one device with their reach alone, it seems strange to me when people use them but don’t take full advantage.</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Me:</b> If a web designer or developer is only passingly familiar with progressive enhancement and is considering coming to the event, what should they expect to get out of it?</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Simon:</b> These are probably the people with the most to benefit from EnhanceConf.</p>

<p>We are going to start the day looking at why progressive enhancement is still important on the modern web, so that should provide a nice intro for anyone who is not already familiar with progressive enhancement.</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Me:</b> What about a seasoned practitioner who already applies this philosophy to their work?</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Simon:</b> Originally, EnhanceConf was a very selfish idea. I wanted to learn more about the tools and techniques being in use in industry: Over the last few years contracting I’ve seen many in use in that just weren’t surfacing at conferences.</p>

<p>EnhanceConf is about the state of the art in progressive enhancement, I’d like to think EnhanceConf will be the perfect event for such people to come together and learn from one another.</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Me:</b> What if the person thinks progressive enhancement is a waste of time?</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Simon:</b> I’d really like to encourage these people to come along to the event, I think it’s important their voice is a part of this discussion so that we can learn from each other and move forward together.</p>

<p>With an open mind I think they should have a really good time, they might hear some viewpoints they disagree with, but there will be lots of opportunities for Q&amp;A to discuss those topics in detail.</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Me:</b> As a hyper-focused event, there’s a risk of it being a bit of an echo chamber. Have you taken steps to mitigate that possibility?</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Simon:</b> I hope by being a hyper-focused event we can move beyond the bikeshedding that so often surrounds such discussions.</p>

<p>But yes. I have taken a couple of steps to mitigate an echo chamber:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Duplicate content</strong>
If you take all the talks about progressive enhancement and put them all on the same day you would end up with a fair amount of similar content. There will be no generic talks about progressive enhancement at EnhanceConf. Each talk will dig into real examples to provide unique tales from the trenches.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Preaching to the choir</strong>
I’ve been reaching out to lots of different communities around London to bring as many voices into the discussions as possible. The other day I was at the Meteor London meetup talking about EnhanceConf. Tableflip (the organisers) even bought tickets for their whole company!</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>The event is also being recorded so anyone not at the event will be able to watch all the talks and Q&amp;A.</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Me:</b> You’re modeling the format of the event—four acts, each comprising three twenty-minute talks and a group Q&amp;A session—on Responsive Day Out. What was the draw of that approach?</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Simon:</b> Yes, we get to hear lots of different viewpoints and then bring the speakers together for a Q&amp;A. This should allow new viewpoints to emerge from discussions and join related threads. It also means we get to spend each section focusing on a particular area.</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Me:</b> Can you talk a bit about your speaker selection process?</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Simon:</b> I had lots of people in mind to talk at EnhanceConf. To ensure we heard a wide range of viewpoints we also opened a call for proposals to which we received some superb submissions.</p>

<p>I was fortunate to have some trusted advisors who helped me out throughout the process. I’m really pleased with how the line-up turned out.</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Me:</b> When the event is done and dusted, what are you hoping will happen?</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Simon:</b> I’d quite like a holiday! :D</p>

<p>But seriously, I hope we can demonstrate how to maximise the benefits and minimise any costs associated with progressive enhancement.</p>

<p>If at the end of EnhanceConf we had a reasoned and nurturing community able to take discussions forward that would be a fine outcome. :)</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Me:</b> Do you think there will be another EnhanceConf?</p>

<p><b class="interview__attribution">Simon:</b> EnhanceConf is the first conference I’ve organised. It’s been an unfathomable amount of work and financial risk to get this far and it’s mostly been done in my evenings and weekends. That said, it has been quite fun.</p>

<p>I’d like to do some traveling this year, maybe 2018?</p>

<hr />

<p>EnhanceConf will take place March 4th at the <a href="http://www.thersa.org/">RSA House</a> in London. <a href="http://enhanceconf.com/tickets.html">Tickets are available on the conference website</a>. I will also be giving <a href="http://enhanceconf.com/workshop.html">a one-day workshop entitled Planning Adaptive Interfaces</a> on March 3rd as part of the conference. Seating is limited.</p>

<p>EnhanceConf is offering a small number of educational scholarships. For more information on the scholarships and how to apply, check out <a href="https://simonmcmanus.wordpress.com/2016/02/14/enhanceconf-scholarship/">Simon’s post about the program</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
