<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Browse by Tag: Progressive Enhancement | Aaron Gustafson]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/tags/progressive-enhancement/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-26T14:34:46-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where Do We Go From Here?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/where-do-we-go-from-here/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-22T10:49:56-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/where-do-we-go-from-here</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I had the great pleasure of delivering the closing keynote for the final Responsive Day Out. Here’s what I had to say.</em></p>

<!-- more -->




<hr>


<p>Today has provided an amazing tour of the world of responsive design. We’ve seen how to level-up our workflows and processes. We’ve learned new ways to improve the accessibility of our products. We’ve grappled with modern CSS and HTML capabilities that help us embrace the hugely variable display sizes that swirl and whirl around us.</p>

<p>We’ve explored the future of modular code and browsers’ capacity for working without network connectivity. And we’ve even taken a trip into the possible future of where the web might go.</p>

<p><figure id="figure-2015-06-22-01">
<img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/01.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/01.jpg&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/01.jpg&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/01.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt="">
</figure></p>

<p>We’ve come a long way since <a href="https://huffduffer.com/adactio/243780">Ethan’s article</a>, fluid grids, flexible media, and media queries. Those three tenets sowed a seed that has grown and flourished as we have come to better understand the implications of device proliferation. We’ve seen that the web is capable of going anywhere and doing pretty much anything.</p>

<p>I would argue that <a href="https://huffduffer.com/adactio/243780">&ldquo;Responsive Web Design&rdquo;</a> was the first article that really managed to capture the concepts that John Allsopp had discussed so many years before in <a href="http://www.alistapart.com/articles/dao/">“A Dao of Web Design”</a> and distilled them into something the design and development community could really sink their teeth into. It provided a concrete example of the web’s ability to flex and mold itself into whatever shape it needed to take on.</p>

<p>It was the first time many designers had come to terms with the idea that &ldquo;experience&rdquo; was not some monolithic thing.</p>

<p>Sure, many of us in the web standards community had been talking the talk and walking the walk with regard to <a href="http://alistapart.com/article/understandingprogressiveenhancement">progressive enhancement</a>. And we were gaining converts, but progress was slow. Ethan demonstrated—directly and succinctly—what the progressive enhancement of visual design could look like.</p>

<p>Providing an identical experience for each and every human being that tries to access our sites would be impossible. There are simply far too many factors to consider. We’ve got screen size, display density, CPU speed, amount of RAM, sensor availability, feature availability, interface methods … <em>breathe</em> … operating system type, operating system version, browser type, browser version, plug-ins installed, network speed, network latency, network congestion, firewalls, proxies, routers, and probably a dozen other factors my mind is incapable of plucking amid the whirlwind of technical considerations.</p>

<p><strong>And that doesn’t even consider our users.</strong></p>

<p>When it comes to the people we need to reach for our work to actually matter, we have to consider literacy level, reading acumen, level of domain knowledge, cognitive impairments like learning disabilities and dyslexia, attention deficit issues, environmental distractions, vision impairment, hearing impairment, motor impairment, how much they understand how to use their device, how much they understand how to use their browser, how well-versed in common web conventions they are, and a ton of other &ldquo;human factors&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Every person is different and everyone comes to the web with their own set of special needs. Some are always with them, blindness for example. Others are transient, like breaking your mousing arm. Still others are purely situational and dependent on the device you are using at the time and its technical capabilities or constraints.</p>

<p>Trying to devise one monolithic experience for each and every person to have in every context that considers every factor would be impossible. And yet, Sir Tim Berners Lee had a vision for a web that was capable of going anywhere. Was he insane?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.w3.org/History/1989/proposal.html">Sir Tim’s vision for the web</a> was that content could be created once and accessed from anywhere. Disparate but related pieces of &ldquo;hypermedia&rdquo; scattered across the globe could be connected to one another via links. Moreover, they would be retrievable by anyone on any device capable of reading HTML. For free.</p>

<p><strong>Ultimately, Sir Tim envisioned universal accessibility.</strong></p>

<p>For a great many of us, ensuring our websites are accessible is an afterthought. We talk a good game when it comes to “user centered” this or that, but often treat the word “accessibility” as a synonym for “screen reader”. It’s so much more than that. “Accessibility” is about people. People consume content and use interfaces in many different ways, some similar and some quite dissimilar to how we do it.</p>

<p>Sure, people with visual impairments often use a screen reader to consume content. But they might also use a braille touch feedback device or a braille printer. They probably also use a keyboard. Or they may use a touchscreen in concert with audio cues. Or they may even use a camera to allow them to &ldquo;read&rdquo; content via OCR and text-to-speech. And yes, visual impairment affects a decent percentage of the populace (especially as we age), but it is only part of the “accessibility” puzzle.</p>

<p>The contrast between text and the background is an important factor in ensuring content remains readable in different lighting situations. Color choice is an accessibility concern.</p>

<p>The language we use on our sites and in our interfaces directly affects how easy it is for our users to understand what we do, the products we are offering, and why it matters. It also affects how we make our users feel about themselves, their experience, and our companies. Language is an accessibility concern.</p>

<p>The size of our web pages has a direct effect on how long our pages take to download, how much it costs our customers to access them, and (sometimes) even whether or not the content can be reached. Performance is an accessibility concern.</p>

<p>I could keep going, but I’m sure you get the point.</p>

<p>Accessibility is about providing good experiences for everyone, regardless of physical or mental abilities, gender, race, or language. It recognizes that we all have special needs—physical limitations, bandwidth limitations, device limitations—that may require us to  experience the same interface in different ways.</p>

<p>When I visit a website on my phone, for example, I am visually limited by my screen resolution (especially if I am using a browser that encourages zooming) and I am limited in my ability to interact with buttons and links because I am browsing with my fingertips, which are larger and far less accurate than a mouse cursor.</p>

<p>On a touchscreen, I may need the experience to be slightly different, but I still need to be able to do whatever it is I came to the site to do. I need <em>an</em> experience, but moreover I need the <em>appropriate</em> experience.</p>

<p>Embracing the reality that experience does’t need to be just one thing will help us reach more people with fewer headaches. Experience can—and should—be crafted as a continuum. This is progressive enhancement: We start with a baseline experience that works for everyone—content, real links, first generation form controls, and forms that actually submit to the server. Then we build up the experience from there.</p>

<p><figure id="figure-2015-06-22-02">
<img src="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/02.gif" alt="">
</figure></p>

<p>Your browser supports HTML5 form controls? Great! You’ll get a better virtual keyboard when you go to type your email address. You can use CSS? Awesome, let me make that reading experience better for you. Oh, you can handle media queries! Let me adjust the layout so those line lengths are a little more comfortable. Wow, your browser supports Ajax?! Here let me load in some teasers for related content you might find interesting.</p>

<p>Imagine sitting down in a restaurant only to have the waiter immediately bring you a steak. But you’re a vegetarian. You ask if they offer something you can eat and they politely reply <em>Oh I’m sorry, meat is a requirement. Why don’t you just eat meat? It’s easy! You’re really missing out on some tasty food.</em> No waiter who actually cares about your experience would do that.</p>

<p>And yet we—as an industry—don’t seem to have any problem telling someone they need to change their browser to accommodate us. That’s just wrong. Our work is meaningless without users. We should be bending over backwards to attract and retain them. This is customer service 101.</p>

<p>This comes back to Postel&rsquo;s law, which Jeremy often recounts:</p>

<blockquote><p>Be conservative in what you do, be liberal in what you accept from others.</p></blockquote>

<p>We need to be lax when it comes to browser support and not make to many (or better yet any) assumptions about what we can send.</p>

<p>Of course this is not an approach everyone in our industry is ready to embrace, so I’ll offer another quote I come back to time and time again…</p>

<blockquote><p>When something happens, the only thing in your power is your attitude toward it; you can either accept it or resent it.</p></blockquote>

<p>We can’t control the world, we can only control our reaction to it.</p>

<p>Now those of you who’ve gathered for this final Responsive Day Out (or who are following along at home) probably understand this more than most. We feel the constant bombardment of new devices, screen sizes, and capabilities. The only way I’ve found to deal with all of this is to accept it, embrace the diversity, and view device and browser proliferation as a feature, not a bug.</p>

<p>It’s up to us to educate those around us who have—either by accident or intent—not accepted that diversity is the reality we live in and things are only going to get crazier. Burying our heads in the sand is not an option.</p>

<p>When I am trying to help folks understand and embrace diversity, I often reach for one of my favorite thought exercises from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Rawls">John Rawls</a>.</p>

<p><figure id="figure-2015-06-22-03">
<img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/03.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/03.jpg&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/03.jpg&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/03.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt="">
</figure></p>

<p>Rawls was a philosopher who used to run a social experiment with students, church groups, and the like.</p>

<p>In the experiment, participants were allowed to create their ideal society. It could follow any philosophy: It could be a monarchy or democracy or anarchy. It could be capitalist or socialist. The people in this experiment had free rein to control absolutely every facet of the society… but then he’d add the twist: They could not control what position they occupied in that society.</p>

<p>This twist is what <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Harsanyi">John Harsanyi</a>—an early game theorist—refers to as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veil_of_ignorance">“Veil of Ignorance”</a> and what Rawls found, time and time again, was that individuals participating in the experiment would gravitate toward creating the most egalitarian societies.</p>

<p>It makes sense: what rational, self-interested human being would treat the elderly, the sick, people of a particular gender, race, creed, or color poorly if they could find themselves in that very same position when the veil is pulled away?</p>

<p>The things we do to accommodate special needs now pay dividends in the future. Look at ramps.</p>

<p><figure id="figure-2015-06-22-04">
<img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/04.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/04.jpg&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/04.jpg&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/04.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt="">
</figure></p>

<p>They’re a classic example of an accessibility feature for people in wheelchairs that also benefit people who aren’t in them: People toting luggage, delivery services hauling heavy things on dollies, parents pushing children (or their dressed up dogs) in strollers, a commuter walking her bike, and that guy who just prefers walking up a gentle incline to expending the effort required to mount a step.</p>

<p>When we create alternative paths to get from Point A to Point B, people can take the one most appropriate for them, whether by choice or necessity. And everyone can accomplish their goals.</p>

<p>We all have special needs. Some we’re born with. Some we develop. Some are temporary. Some have nothing to do with us personally, but are situational or purely dependent on the hardware we are using, the interaction methods we have available to us, or even the speed at which we can access the Internet or process data.</p>

<p>What is responsive web design about if not accessibility? Yes, its fundamental tenets are concerned with visual design, but in terms of the big picture, they’re all about providing the best possible reading experience.</p>

<p>As practitioners of responsive design, we understand the benefits of adapting our interfaces. We understand fallbacks. We understand how to design robust experiences that work under a wide variety of conditions. Every day we broaden the accessibility of our products.</p>

<p>These skills will make us invaluable as technology continues to offer novel ways of consuming and interacting with our websites.</p>

<p>We’re just starting to dip or toes—er, hands—into the world of motion-based gestural controls. Sure, we’ve had them in two dimensions on touch screens for a while now but three dimensional motion-based controls are only beginning to appear.</p>

<p><figure id="fig-VXhhE-l96qQ" class="figure figure--video"><div class="video-embed video-embed--youtube video-embed--16x9"><a class="video-embed__lazy-link" style="background-image:url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/VXhhE-l96qQ/0.jpg);" href="//www.youtube.com/watch?v=VXhhE-l96qQ&amp;start=41&amp;end=78" data-lazy-video-src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/VXhhE-l96qQ?autoplay=1&amp;start=41&amp;end=78&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;iv_load_policy=3"><div class="video-embed__lazy-div"></div><div class="video-embed__lazy-info">Kinect Tips, Part 3: Gesture Controls</div></a></div></figure></p>

<p>The first big leap in this direction was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kinect">Kinect</a> on the Xbox 360 (and later, Windows). With Kinect, we interact with the computer using body movements like raising a hand (which gets Kinect to pay attention), pushing our hand forward to click/tap, and grasping to drag the canvas in a particular direction.</p>

<p>The Kinect ushered in a major revolution in terms of interfacing with computers, but from an interaction perspective, it presents similar challenges to those of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wii#Wii_Remote">Wii controller</a> and Sony’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PlayStation_Move">PlayStation Move</a>. Large body gestures like raising your hand (or a wand controller) can be tiring.</p>

<p><figure id="fig-21LtA5-wiwU" class="figure figure--video"><div class="video-embed video-embed--youtube video-embed--16x9"><a class="video-embed__lazy-link" style="background-image:url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/21LtA5-wiwU/0.jpg);" href="//www.youtube.com/watch?v=21LtA5-wiwU&amp;start=7&amp;end=19" data-lazy-video-src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/21LtA5-wiwU?autoplay=1&amp;start=7&amp;end=19&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;iv_load_policy=3"><div class="video-embed__lazy-div"></div><div class="video-embed__lazy-info">Leap Motion With Windows</div></a></div></figure></p>

<p>They’re also not terribly accurate. If you thought that touchscreen accuracy was an issue, hand gestures like those for the Kinect or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leap_Motion">LEAP Motion</a> pose even more of a challenge.</p>

<p>To accommodate interactions like this (which we currently have no way of detecting) we need to be aware of how easy it is to click on interactive controls. We need to determine if our buttons and links are large enough and whether there is enough space between them to ensure our user’s intent is accurately conveyed to the browser. Two specs which can help address this are Media Queries Level 4 and Pointer Events.</p>

<p>In <a href="http://dev.w3.org/csswg/mediaqueries-4/">Media Queries Level 4</a>, we became able to apply style rules to particular interaction contexts. For instance, when we have very accurate control over our cursor (as in the case of a stylus or mouse) or less accurate control (as in the case of a touch screen or physical gesture):</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/372271534c78cf11d4a6.js?file=mq4-pointer.css'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>@media (pointer:fine) {
  /* Smaller links and buttons are ok */
}
@media (pointer:coarse) {
  /* Larger links and buttons are probably a good idea */
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>Of course, we want to offer a sensible default in terms of size and spacing as a fallback for older browsers and devices.</p>

<p>We also have the ability to determine whether the device is capable of hovering over an element and can adjust the interface accordingly.</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/372271534c78cf11d4a6.js?file=mq4-hover.css'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>@media (hover:hover) {
  /* hover-related interactions are A-OK */
}
@media (hover:on-demand) {
  /* hover-related interactions are potentially difficult,
     maybe do something else instead */
}
@media (hover:none) {
	/* No hover possible :-( */
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>We still need to figure out how well all of this ends up working on multimodal devices like the Surface tablet, however. Will the design change as the user switches between input modes? Should it? To that end, the spec also provides <code>any-pointer</code> and <code>any-hover</code> to allow you to query for whether <em>any</em> supported interaction method meets your requirements, but here’s a word of warning from the spec:</p>

<blockquote><p>Designing a page that relies on hovering or accurate pointing only because <code>any-hover</code> or <code>any-pointer</code> indicate that an input mechanism with these capabilities is available, is likely to result in a poor experience.</p></blockquote>

<p>These media query options are starting to roll out in Chrome, Mobile Safari, and Microsoft Edge, so it’s worth taking a look at them.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/pointerevents/">Pointer Events</a> is another spec that is beginning to gain some traction. It generalizes interaction to a single event rather than forcing us to silo experience into mouse-driven, touch-driven, pen-driven, (sigh) force-driven, and so on.</p>

<p>We can unobtrusively detect support for Pointer Events…</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/372271534c78cf11d4a6.js?file=pointer-test.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>if ( window.PointerEvent ) {
  window.addEventListener( &quot;pointerdown&quot;, detectType, false );
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>…and then handle them all in the same way or create branches based on the <code>pointerType</code>:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/372271534c78cf11d4a6.js?file=pointer-event.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>function detectType( event ) {
  switch( event.pointerType ) {
    case &quot;mouse:
      /* mouse input detected */
      break;
    case &quot;pen&quot;:
      /* pen/stylus input detected */
      break;
    case &quot;touch:
      /* touch input detected */
      break;
    default:
      /* pointerType is empty (could not be detected) or UA-specific custom type */
  }
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>Of course, in addition to considering the level of accuracy our users have while interacting with our screens, we also need to consider the potentially increased distance at which our users are reading our content.</p>

<p>To that end, I’ve been experimenting with the viewport width (<code>vw</code>) unit.</p>

<p>For a long time, I’ve used ems for the layout’s <code>max-width</code> (so the line length is proportional to the font size). I also use relative font sizes. With that as the foundation, I can use a media query that matches the maximum width and set the base font size at the vw equivalent at the max width.</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/372271534c78cf11d4a6.js?file=vw-scaling.css'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>body {
  max-width: 64em;
}

@media screen and (min-width: 64em) {
  body {
    font-size: 1.5625vw; /* ( 1em / 64em ) * 100 */
  }
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>Then the whole design will simply zoom the layout when viewed beyond that size.</p>

<p><figure id="fig-6XoN9mMgI38" class="figure figure--video"><div class="video-embed video-embed--youtube video-embed--16x9"><a class="video-embed__lazy-link" style="background-image:url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/6XoN9mMgI38/0.jpg);" href="//www.youtube.com/watch?v=6XoN9mMgI38" data-lazy-video-src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/6XoN9mMgI38?autoplay=1&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;iv_load_policy=3"><div class="video-embed__lazy-div"></div><div class="video-embed__lazy-info">Using CSS to Scale a Design on Resize</div></a></div></figure></p>

<p>If you don’t want to turn something like that on automatically, you can enable it to be toggled on and off with JavaScript.</p>

<p><figure id="fig-96l_W7ca6SM" class="figure figure--video"><div class="video-embed video-embed--youtube video-embed--16x9"><a class="video-embed__lazy-link" style="background-image:url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/96l_W7ca6SM/0.jpg);" href="//www.youtube.com/watch?v=96l_W7ca6SM" data-lazy-video-src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/96l_W7ca6SM?autoplay=1&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;iv_load_policy=3"><div class="video-embed__lazy-div"></div><div class="video-embed__lazy-info">CSS Couch Mode</div></a></div></figure></p>

<p>Things get even crazier when you start to factor in devices like the HoloLens. And no, I have not gotten to play with one yet.</p>

<p><figure id="fig-3AADEqLIALk" class="figure figure--video"><div class="video-embed video-embed--youtube video-embed--16x9"><a class="video-embed__lazy-link" style="background-image:url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/3AADEqLIALk/0.jpg);" href="//www.youtube.com/watch?v=3AADEqLIALk&amp;start=87&amp;end=117" data-lazy-video-src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/3AADEqLIALk?autoplay=1&amp;start=87&amp;end=117&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;iv_load_policy=3"><div class="video-embed__lazy-div"></div><div class="video-embed__lazy-info">Microsoft HoloLens demo onstage at BUILD 2015</div></a></div></figure></p>

<p>But the idea of being able to drop a resizable virtual screen on any surface presents some interesting possibilities as a user and some unique challenges as a designer. HoloLens, of course, brings with it gesture controls as well, so accounting for a variety of input types should get us pretty far.</p>

<p>In a similar vein, we should begin to think about what experiences can and should look like when we are browsing solely with our gaze. Gaze tracking has its origins in the accessibility space as a means of providing interface control to folks with limited or no use of their hands. Traditionally, gaze tracking hardware has been several thousand dollars, putting it out of the reach of many people, but that is starting to change.</p>

<p>In the last few years, the computational power of our devices has increased as the hardware costs associated with supporting gaze tracking have dropped dramatically. Looking around, you can see gaze tracking beginning to move into the public sphere: Many smartphones and smartwatches can recognize when you are looking at them (or at least they do sometimes). This is only a short step away from knowing where on the screen you are looking. And nearly every high-end smartphone is now equipped with a front-facing camera which makes them perfect candidates to provide this interaction method.</p>

<p><figure id="fig-DEk7PlJWQgI" class="figure figure--video"><div class="video-embed video-embed--youtube video-embed--16x9"><a class="video-embed__lazy-link" style="background-image:url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/DEk7PlJWQgI/0.jpg);" href="//www.youtube.com/watch?v=DEk7PlJWQgI&amp;start=18&amp;end=54" data-lazy-video-src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/DEk7PlJWQgI?autoplay=1&amp;start=18&amp;end=54&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;iv_load_policy=3"><div class="video-embed__lazy-div"></div><div class="video-embed__lazy-info">The Sesame Phone</div></a></div></figure></p>

<p>The <a href="http://sesame-enable.com/phone/">Sesame Phone</a> was designed to allow people to use a smartphone without using their hands. It uses facial tracking to move a virtual cursor around the screen, allowing users to interact with the underlying operating system as well as individual applications. It supports tap, swipe, and other gestures (via a context menu) and is pretty impressive in my experience. Technology like this enables people suffering from MS, arthritis, Muscular Dystrophy, and more to use a smartphone and—more importantly to us—browse the web.</p>

<p><a href="https://theeyetribe.com/">The Eye Tribe</a> and <a href="http://www.fixational.com/">Fixational</a> are similarly working to bring eye tracking to smartphones and tablets. Eye tracking is similar to face tracking, but the cursor follows your focus. Micro gestures—blink, wink, etc.—allow you to interact with the device.</p>

<p>Even though most gaze tracking software mimics a mouse and has adjustable sensitivity, the accuracy of it as a pointer device is not fantastic. When I’ve used the Sesame Phone, for instance, I’ve have a hard time controlling the position of my head in order to hold the cursor still to hover and click a button. I’m sure this would improve with practice, but it’s safe to say that in a gaze interaction, larger, well spaced, and more easily targeted links and buttons would be a godsend.</p>

<p>So far, I’ve focused on interaction methods that facilitate navigation and consuming content. But what about filling out a form? I can tell you that typing an email letter-by-letter on a virtual keyboard using your face, sucks…</p>

<p>Thankfully, most of these gestural implementations are coupled with some form of voice recognition. The Kinect, for instance, will accept verbal commands to navigate and accomplish tasks like filling in forms. The Sesame Phone also supports voice commands for certain basic actions, dictating email, and the like.</p>

<p>Coupled with voice, the alternative interaction methods of Kinect and Sesame Phone work really well. But voice interaction can stand on its own too.</p>

<p>Most of us are familiar with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siri">Apple’s Siri</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Now">Google Now</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_Cortana">Microsoft’s Cortana</a>. These digital assistants are great at retrieving information from select sources and doing other assistant-y things like calculating a tip and setting a reminder. As far as interacting with the web, however, they don’t… yet. We can engage with them, but they can‘t (necessarily) engage with a web page.</p>

<p>Exposing the information stored in our webpages via semantic HTML and structured syntaxes like <a href="http://microformats.org/">microformats</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microdata_(HTML">microdata</a>), and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RDFa">RDFa</a> <em>should</em> eventually make our content available to these assistants, but we don’t really know. Their various makers haven’t really given us any clue as to how to do that and, as it stands right now, none of them can look up a web page and read it to you. For that you need to invoke a screen reader.</p>

<p>Each company offers a first-party screen reader. And all are capable of helping you interact with a page, including helping you fill in forms, without having to see the page. And yet, these technologies have not been coupled with their corresponding assistants. It probably won’t be long before we see that happen.</p>

<p>When we start to consider how our websites will be experienced in a voice context, the readability of our web pages becomes crucial. Clear well-written prose and a logical source order will be an absolute necessity. If our pages don’t make sense when read, what’s the point?</p>

<p>Content strategist Steph Hay views interface as an opportunity to have a conversation with our users. Soon it literally will be.</p>

<p>Interestingly, Microsoft has given us a peek at what it might be like to design custom voice commands for our websites beyond what the OS natively supports with Cortana. In other words, they let us teach their assistant.</p>

<p>In Windows 10, installable web apps can include a <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/dn722331.aspx">Voice Command Definition (VCD) file</a> in the <code>head</code> of the page to enable custom commands:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/372271534c78cf11d4a6.js?file=vcd.html'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>&lt;meta name=“msapplication-cortanavcd&quot; content=&quot;http://myapp.io/vcd.xml&quot;&gt;</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>The referenced VCD file is simply an XML file defining the keyword for the web app and commands that can be issued.</p>

<p>Using very basic syntax, The VCD identifies optional pieces of a given phrase and variables Cortana should extract:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/372271534c78cf11d4a6.js?file=vcd.xml'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>&lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;utf-8&quot;?&gt;
&lt;VoiceCommands xmlns=&quot;http://schemas.microsoft.com/voicecommands/1.2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;CommandSet xml:lang=&quot;en-us&quot; Name=&quot;groupPost&quot;&gt;
    &lt;CommandPrefix&gt;Group Post&lt;/CommandPrefix&gt;
    &lt;Example&gt;Group Post add note&lt;/Example&gt;
    &lt;Command Name=&quot;addNote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;Example&gt;add a note {message} using group post&lt;/Example&gt;
      &lt;ListenFor RequireAppName=&quot;BeforeOrAfterPhrase&quot;&gt;[please] add a note [that] {noteSubject}&lt;/ListenFor&gt;
      &lt;Feedback&gt;adding {noteSubject} to Group Post&lt;/Feedback&gt;
      &lt;Navigate Target=&quot;/addNote.htm&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/Command&gt;
    &lt;PhraseTopic Label=&quot;noteSubject&quot; Scenario=&quot;Dictation&quot;&gt;&lt;/PhraseTopic&gt;
  &lt;/CommandSet&gt;
&lt;/VoiceCommands&gt;</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>This particular app passes the captured information over to JavaScript for processing. That’s right, <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn722330.aspx#handle_activation_and_execute_voice_commands">Cortana has a JavaScript API too</a>. Pretty neat.</p>

<p>But traditional computers and smart mobile devices aren’t the only place we’re starting to see voice based experiences. We also have disembodied voices like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon_Echo">Amazon’s Echo</a> and <a href="http://www.theubi.com/">the Ubi</a> which are completely headless.</p>

<p><figure id="figure-2015-06-22-11">
<img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/05.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/05.jpg&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/05.jpg&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/05.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt="">
</figure></p>

<p>Right now, they both seem squarely focused on helping your house become &ldquo;smarter"—streaming music, adjusting the thermostat, etc.—but it isn’t hard to imagine these devices becoming coupled with the ability to browse and interact with the web.</p>

<p>In the near future, voice-based interactions with the web will be entirely possible. They will likely suck a bit at first, but they&rsquo;ll get better.</p>

<p>I’m going to make a somewhat bold prediction: while touch has been revolutionary in many ways toward improving digital access, voice is going to be even more significant. Voice-based interfaces will create new opportunities for people to interact with and participate in the digital world.</p>

<p>Because we’ve been thinking about how the experiences we create are consumable across a variety of devices, we’ve got the jump on other folks working on the web when it comes to voice. We see experience as a continuum, starting with text.</p>

<p>As voice technology matures, we will be the ones people look to as the experts. We will empower the next generation of websites and applications to become voice-enabled and in so doing, we will improve the lives of billions. Because “accessibility” is not about disabilities, it’s about access and <strong>it’s about people</strong>.</p>

<p>Sure, we’ll make it easier to look up movie times and purchase tickets to see the latest <cite>Transformers</cite> debacle, but we will also empower the nearly 900 million people globally—over 60% of whom are women—that are illiterate. And that’s a population that has been largely ignored on our dominantly textual web.</p>

<p>We will create new opportunities for the poor and disadvantaged to participate in a world that has excluded them. You may not be aware, but 80% of Fortune 500 companies—think Target, Walmart—only accept job applications online or via computers. We will enable people who have limited computer skills or who struggle with reading to apply for jobs with these companies.</p>

<p>We can help bridge the digital divide and the literacy gap. We can create opportunities for people to better their lives and the lives of their families. We have the power to create more equity in this world than most of us have ever dreamed.</p>

<p>This is an incredibly exciting time, not just for the responsive design community, not just the web, but for the world! The future is coming and I can’t wait to see how awesome you make it!</p>

<p><figure id="figure-2015-06-22-12">
<img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/06.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/06.jpg&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/06.jpg&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-06-22/06.jpg&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt="">
</figure></p>

<hr>


<p><em>Responsive Day Out 3: The Final Breakpoint was held in Brighton, UK on 19 June 2015.</em></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://huffduffer.com/adactio/243780">Listen to this presentation on Huffduffer</a>.</li>
<li>Read <a href="https://decadecity.net/blog/2015/06/19/aaron-gustafson-where-do-we-go-here">Orde Saunders’ notes</a> from my talk.</li>
<li>Read <a href="https://hiddedevries.nl/en/blog/2015-06-20-responsive-day-out-3-the-final-breakpoint/">Hidde de Vries’ recap of the day</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bringing Sanity and Order to Device Testing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/bringing-sanity-and-order-to-device-testing/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-05T08:56:03-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/bringing-sanity-and-order-to-device-testing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It seems like every other day the public is granted some new means of accessing the web. Some days it’s <a href="http://www.engadget.com/2015/04/29/microsoft-edge/">a new browser</a>. Others it’s <a href="http://www.pcadvisor.co.uk/reviews/mobile-phone/3504276/yotaphone-2-review-uk-dual-screen-smartphone/">a new smartphone</a>. Or <a href="http://www.engadget.com/products/microsoft/surface/3/">a tablet</a>. Or <a href="http://the-digital-reader.com/2014/10/22/voyage-vs-paperwhite-comparison-review-web-browser/">an e-reader</a>. Or <a href="https://www.nintendo.com/3ds/internetbrowser/specs/">a video game console</a>. Or <a href="http://www.phonearena.com/news/Surf-the-Internet-from-your-Android-Wear-smartwatch-Now-possible-via-this-new-app_id58580">a smartwatch</a>. Or <a href="https://html5test.com/compare/browser/samsungsmarttv-2013.html">a TV</a>. Or <a href="http://www.techradar.com/us/reviews/wearables/microsoft-hololens-1281834/review">a heads-up display</a>. Or <a href="http://www.popularmechanics.com/cars/a13191/the-future-of-car-connectivity-is-a-real-web-browser-in-the-dash-17416796/">a car</a>. Or <a href="http://www.lgblog.lt/2009/10/28/zvilgsnis-atgal-pirmasis-pasaulyje-saldytuvas-su-internetu-lg-internet-digital-dios/">a refrigerator</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I worked on one project where the client provided me with a spreadsheet detailing 1,400 different user agents that accessed the login screen for the m-dot site. In two days!</p>

<p>As further evidence, consider <a href="http://blog.jasonsamuels.net/post/21633531278/analytics-confirm-the-need-for-adaptive-web-design">the enlightening details of this post from Jason Samuels</a> of the National Council on Family relations, a non-profit organization:</p>

<ul>
<li>In 2008, Internet Explorer dominated as the browser for 93.5% of their visitors. By 2014, that percentage had fallen to 19.7%, with Chrome bringing in the lion’s share of the traffic (37%). Firefox narrowly beat out IE with a 20% share of users.</li>
<li>In 2008, visits from &ldquo;mobile&rdquo; devices accounted for only about 0.1% of their traffic. In 2014, that number had skyrocketed to 14.4%.</li>
<li>In 2008, they detected 71 different screen resolutions, which is already a lot to consider. By 2014, however, they were seeing 1,000 unique screen resolutions each and every quarter (with over 200 of those recording 10+ visits per quarter).</li>
</ul>


<p>That last stat blows my mind every time I read it. You can’t design for 200 different screens, let alone 1,000. It’s a fools errand. And don’t even think of trying to test on that many devices.</p>

<p>And yet, here we are designing websites that can (and will) go anywhere. We need to thoroughly test because we can’t make any assumptions about the browsers and devices being used to access our content.</p>

<p>Testing can be tedious, time consuming, and costly. Surely there’s a way to make it easier. There sure is: Instead of getting hung up on creating one experience that needs to be nearly identical on every browser, we can be smarter about how we build things and treat experience as a continuum.</p>

<p>We can build websites that are both nimble enough to work on low powered devices over slow networks <em>and</em> smart enough to take advantage of advanced features and sensors when opportunity knocks.</p>

<p><em>Wha?! We can have our cake and eat it too</em>? Yes. Yes we can.</p>

<h2>Start on Solid Footing</h2>

<p>When dealing with the insane proliferation of web-enabled devices and the great unknown of where our websites will go, it pays to take a step back and focus on what’s important. We need to ask ourselves two simple questions:</p>

<ol>
<li>What is the purpose of this page, this form, this interface?</li>
<li>What is the simplest way to realize that purpose?</li>
</ol>


<p>Then we need to build that <em>first</em>. Typically we’re talking text, some basic HTML, actual links to other pages, and forms that submit to a back-end of some sort. This is our minimum viable product and it will work anywhere.</p>

<p>Then we can look for opportunities to enhance the experience, all while keeping that functional core at the center of the experience.</p>

<p>We can use CSS to add visual hierarchy to the page, provide some visual interest, and adjust the layout to create a good reading experience on a wide range of screen sizes. We should start from the narrowest screen size we can imagine and <a href="https://twitter.com/brad_frost/status/191977076000161793">let the content guide our breakpoint decisions</a>.</p>

<p>We’ll use JavaScript to give real-time feedback to our users. <a href="http://domscripting.com/presentations/xtech2006/">We’ll hijack forms and links</a> to <a href="http://www.filamentgroup.com/lab/ajax-includes-modular-content.html">lazy load additional content</a> or otherwise avoid full-page refreshes. Heck, we can even take over the entire page and <a href="http://nerds.airbnb.com/isomorphic-javascript-future-web-apps/">convert it into a single page app</a>.</p>

<p>But we should never sacrifice the functional core.</p>

<p>This approach to designing for the web is called <a href="http://alistapart.com/article/understandingprogressiveenhancement">progressive enhancement</a> and it’s the number one tool for dealing with the one-two punch of older browsers and device proliferation.</p>

<h2>Be Conservative in Your Delivery</h2>

<p>What makes progressive enhancement so helpful when it comes to dealing with this swirling mass of devices and browsers is that the core experience will <em>always be</em> available. There is nothing precluding our users from accessing it, even on a crappy WAP browser or a text-based browser like Lynx or even some <a href="http://www.theubi.com/">no so far-future talking computer</a> that only &ldquo;sees&rdquo; the web as text.</p>

<p>In order to ensure we don’t accidentally deliver advanced features to less capable browsers like these, we just need to be smart about how we load stuff like CSS and JavaScript.</p>

<p>Some basic CSS—think typography, color, etc.—will be usable by just about anyone, so we can put all that stuff in one CSS file (e.g., <code>basic.css</code>) and include it with a standard <code>link</code>. Then we can tuck all of our layout rules and other advanced CSS into a separate CSS file (e.g., <code>advanced.css</code>) that we link to with an associated media query.</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/166b285a4fe3d854b97b.js?file=css-linking.html'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;default.css&quot; media=&quot;all&quot;&gt;
	&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;advanced.css&quot; media=&quot;only screen&quot;&gt;</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>Any <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/bryanrieger/rethinking-the-mobile-web-by-yiibu/106">browsers that don’t understand media queries will ignore the second CSS file entirely</a> and receive only the linear, mobile view. Easy peasy, and IE8 gets the mobile layout (a baseline level of support that is not likely to cause you any testing headaches).</p>

<p>You can even take things a step further and use <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/@supports">the <code>@supports</code> block</a> within <code>advanced.css</code> to limit certain rule sets to only the browsers that support specific CSS features.</p>

<p>Of course, CSS support issues are nothing compared to JavaScript, so sometimes it’s best not to deliver certain bits of JavaScript-based functionality to browsers that can’t handle it. This is where <a href="http://www.quirksmode.org/js/support.html">feature (and object) detection</a> becomes incredibly useful:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/166b285a4fe3d854b97b.js?file=feature-test.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>if ( &#39;querySelector&#39; in document ) {
	// We can use querySelector!
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>You can also use <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conditional_comment#Downlevel-revealed_conditional_comment">inverted conditional comments</a> to prohibit older versions of IE from getting JavaScript in the first place (which means you don’t even need to worry about debugging JavaScript there). Here’s an example that hides <code>main.js</code> from IE8 and below, but makes it available to IE9 on up and to every other non-IE browser.</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/166b285a4fe3d854b97b.js?file=no-script-in-lte-ie8.html'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>&lt;!--[if gt IE 8]&gt;&lt;!--&gt;
	&lt;script src=&quot;main.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;![endif]--&gt;</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>By being conservative in what we deliver to browsers we <a href="http://bradfrost.com/blog/mobile/support-vs-optimization/">ensure the greatest level of support, but can still optimize for more advanced ones</a>. This makes testing so much easier because we know older browsers will be okay with the basics and we aren’t trying to use JavaScript features unless we know they’re available.</p>

<h2>Test, Test, Test</h2>

<p>Progressive enhancement helps us avoid a lot of rendering and scripting issues before we even get to the testing phase of a project, but eventually we do need to sit down and run our projects through their paces.</p>

<p>In order to keep testing manageable during development, it’s best to test in one browser we know to have good web standards support. It will provide a basic gut-check for our work. Once we are pretty confident things are working as they should be, we can begin more thorough testing on a variety of browsers and devices.</p>

<p>I personally keep several versions of each major browser on my laptop at any given time. I work on a Mac, so I typically have a few versions of Chrome, Firefox, and Opera lying around. You can get older versions of these browsers here:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://commondatastorage.googleapis.com/chromium-browser-continuous/index.html">Chromium Archive</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ftp.mozilla.org/pub/mozilla.org/firefox/releases/">Firefox Archive</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.opera.com/download//?custom=yes">Opera Archive</a></li>
</ul>


<p>It’s near-impossible to get older versions of Safari running on modern versions of OS X, so I typically just have the latest version locally.</p>

<p>For testing on Windows versions of said browsers, I typically have anywhere from 3-5 virtual machines running various Windows versions with their associated browser version and (typically) a copy of Chrome, Firefox, and Opera for good measure. The MS Edge Dev site offers <a href="http://dev.modern.ie/tools/vms/">free Windows VMs for download</a>. If you’re just looking to get a gut-check in the latest and greatest from Microsoft, there’s also <a href="https://remote.modern.ie/">the Remote.IE service</a>, which allows you to connect to a virtualized version of the browser.</p>

<p>If you develop on Windows or Linux, you’ll need access to a Mac or you’ll have to rely on virtualization to test on that platform. I’ll discuss virtualization in a moment.</p>

<p>Once you’ve thoroughly tested in the various desktop browsers, it’s time to take the deep dive into the world of devices. If you’re unsure where to begin, take a look at your analytics, but take them with a grain of salt. Analytics can lead you to make false assumptions. For example, if you see a low percentage of Blackberry users, could that be because your site just doesn’t work well in Blackberry so they don’t stick around (or come back)? Beware the self-fulfilling prophecy.</p>

<p>If you have the budget, by all means pick up some devices to have on hand for testing. You can use tools like <a href="https://creative.adobe.com/products/inspect">Adobe’s Edge Inspect</a>, <a href="http://vanamco.com/ghostlab/">Vanamco’s Ghostlab</a>, or <a href="https://github.com/viljamis/Remote-Preview">Viljami Salminen’s Remote Preview</a> (or a combination of all of the above) to synchronize browsing on a handful of devices. Some of these tools also allow for remote inspection of the device to debug CSS and JavaScript. <a href="http://people.apache.org/~pmuellr/weinre-docs/latest/">Weinre</a> (which Adobe Edge Inspect uses) and <a href="http://vorlonjs.com/">Vorlon.js</a> also provide remote inspection functionality.</p>

<p>If you are lucky enough to have one nearby, you should stop by your local <a href="http://opendevicelab.com/">open device lab (ODL)</a> to run your tests. ODLs are free community resources, typically offered by a web design studio or an individual who happens to be sitting on a ton of devices. Someone at the ODL should be able to help you pick out devices to test on and introduce you to the testing tools they have available in the lab.</p>

<p>If you don’t have an ODL nearby, you can also do some guerrilla-style testing in your local mobile phone or electronics store. Just make sure they have real devices… you won’t get far on the fake plastic ones.</p>

<p>If none of these are options for you, there’s always virtualization. You can download and install <a href="http://www.mobilexweb.com/emulators">emulators for a variety of mobile browsers and devices</a>. Additionally, services like <a href="https://www.browserstack.com/">Browserstack</a> and <a href="http://crossbrowsertesting.com/">CrossBrowserTesting</a> offer access to hundreds of virtual desktops and devices for a nominal fee.</p>

<p>Virtualization will never give you the same experience as holding a real device in your hand. The performance is rarely the same and you don’t get any sort of feel for how the device responds to your input. I once stumbled on an Android 2.3 bug wherein generated content was being re-generated and re-inserted every time the device was rotated. I doubt I would have discovered that using an emulator. That said, emulators can help you get a rough idea of whether your interface works or not.</p>

<p>Regardless of the means by which you procure your testing devices, try to cover a good cross-section. Pick some low-end ones, a couple older high-end devices, and handful of the latest flagships, and a wide variety of screen sizes and resolutions. Make sure you have good coverage in terms of operating systems too—the latest iOS and Android versions are a given, but make sure you have a Windows device or two, a few Blackberry options, and some older Android and iOS versions in the mix. Then throw in <a href="http://www.geekwire.com/2013/microsoft-kin-resurfaces-25-daily-deals-site/">an oddball</a> <a href="http://www.windowscentral.com/have-39-spare-then-pick-odd-sylvania-7-netbook-windows-ce">or two</a> to see if your interfaces hold up.</p>

<p>It’s important to bear in mind that we will never be able to give each user on each device exactly the same experience. We need to be okay with that—experience is a continuum. As long as our users can accomplish what they need to on our sites, they will be well-served.</p>

<h2>Bonus Points: Embrace Patterns</h2>

<p>If we really want to make things easy on ourselves (and our team), we should consider building a <a href="http://alistapart.com/blog/post/getting-started-with-pattern-libraries">pattern library</a> before we build a single page of our website.</p>

<p>Breaking our interfaces down into discrete, repeatable patterns (e.g., a label and form control, a tabbed interface, etc.) lets us look at each in isolation and test it that way too. Testing in isolation is far easier than trying to debug a page with a lot of moving parts.</p>

<p>Gathering our patterns into a live, web-based pattern library  allows anyone on our team to collect the patterns they need to build a given interface as easily as they’d assemble a plate at a smörgåsbord. And if we really want to streamline the building and testing process, we can even <a href="http://ianfeather.co.uk/a-maintainable-style-guide/">make the patterns importable into the live site</a> so everything stays in sync.</p>

<h2>Don’t Fear the Zombie Apocalypse</h2>

<p>With the constant onslaught of new devices, form factors, and considerations, it’s tempting to throw up our hands and find another line of work. The pace of advancement is so brisk, it’s just hard to keep up, let alone feel like we’re on top of where things are headed.</p>

<p>Thankfully, however, all is not lost. By taking a step back and focusing on what matters, embracing experience as a continuum, and being deliberate in how (and when) we deliver certain features and functionality to browsers, we’ll head most issues off at the pass.</p>

<p>This relieves some of the pressure (and frustration) from the testing process and frees us up to test on a wider variety of devices and browsers, which means we’ll be able to provide a solid experience for more users, no matter what marvel of technological wizardry they happen to be using at the time.</p>

<p>Everybody wins.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interface Experience Maps]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/interface-experience-maps/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-28T07:43:20-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/interface-experience-maps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the greatest challenges of progressive enhancement lies not with the coding, but with the planning. It can be incredibly challenging to articulate how a single interface might adapt to a wide variety of situations. Interface Experience Maps (Ix Maps) can help.</p>

<!-- more -->




<hr>


<p>Back in 2007, I was presented with this challenge while putting together a talk called <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20070515221318/http://2007.sxsw.com/interactive/programming/panels/?action=show&amp;id=IAP060214">Ruining the User Experience</a> (which I co-presented for the first time with at SXSW with <a href="https://twitter.com/sarahbeee">Sarah B. Nelson</a>). In the talk, Sarah and I discussed how to treat JavaScript as an enhancement and what happens when you don’t—in 2007, I know!</p>

<p>Anyway, in the talk I was struggling to convey the various decision points and interface adjustments that would happen as a result of those decisions. I don’t remember which of us came up with the idea—it was probably Sarah—but we opted to use a flowchart to visually describe what we were talking about on stage. Here was the first one we did:</p>

<p><figure id="fig-2015-05-28-01" class="media-container"><img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/01.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/01.png&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/01.png&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/01.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt=""><figcaption>An early flowchart used to describe progressive enhancement with JavaScript</figcaption></figure></p>

<p>It was pretty rudimentary, but it got the point across.</p>

<p>In future iterations of the talk, I expounded upon the idea of a flowchart for describing how an interface might adapt to different circumstances and browser capabilities. Here’s a particularly complex one I used to describe how a FAQ might function:</p>

<p><figure id="fig-2015-05-28-02" class="media-container"><img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/02.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/02.png&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/02.png&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/02.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt=""><figcaption>A flowchart describing the progressive enhancement and interaction options for an FAQ.</figcaption></figure></p>

<p>Over the years I found more and more ways to put these artifacts to use. And at a certain point, &ldquo;flowchart&rdquo; didn’t seem to cut it, so I began calling them &ldquo;UI construction flows"—which, admittedly, was a mouthful—and then finally settled on the name "Interaction Experience Maps&rdquo; with the help of a client.</p>

<h2>The Benefits of Ix Maps</h2>

<p>Ix Maps have become an invaluable tool to me and the teams I’ve worked with. They excel at articulating the different ways in which a given interface might adapt and what the end results of each adaptation might be.</p>

<p>This sort of documentation is invaluable to just about everyone on the team:</p>

<ul>
<li>Copywriters get a clear picture of the different experience possibilities so they can craft the copy accordingly;</li>
<li>Designers can see the different experience possibilities and can create wireframes and visual designs that account for each;</li>
<li>Developers get a clear outline of what functionality is expected and know exactly what features and capability detection to employ in generating each experience; and</li>
<li>The quality assurance team has a clear picture of what they should be looking for in each component of an interface.</li>
</ul>


<p>In short, Ix Maps ensure everyone on the team has a clear picture of what’s expected so they can work toward the common goal. One company I worked with found Ix Maps so useful that they created one for each and every pattern in their pattern library. Then they included the drawings as part of each pattern’s documentation.</p>

<h2>Ix Maps Facilitate Collaboration and Iteration</h2>

<p>An Ix Map is a pretty simple concept for anyone to come to grips with, making it a fantastic tool for enabling mixed teams—designers, developers, content folks, business strategists, etc.—to brainstorm ideas and build a strategy around progressive enhancement.</p>

<p>Time and time again, I have seen these simple diagrams bring a diverse team together and help them quickly and easily come up with very creative ways to address complex interface problems. That’s why I frequently use them as a tool in the workshops I lead.</p>

<p>Because they are so basic, Ix Maps can be sketched out quickly on paper, a whiteboard, or in software like OmniGraffle. And their simplicity also makes it quite easy to explore different ideas of how to adapt things and you don’t have to worry about throwing away an idea that doesn’t play out because it’s only a few boxes and arrows… you haven’t invested any time in design or production.</p>

<p>Here’s an example from <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/804756366246427/">my Beyond Responsive workshop</a> that illustrates the evolution of a tabbed interface Ix Map from basic into something that is far more appropriate for differently-sized screens:</p>

<p><figure id="fig-2015-05-28-03" class="media-container"><img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/03.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/03.png&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/03.png&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/03.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt=""><figcaption>Pass 1: If JavaScript’s available, make a tabbed interface out of linear content. If not, leave it as it was.</figcaption></figure></p>

<p><figure id="fig-2015-05-28-04" class="media-container"><img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/04.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/04.png&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/04.png&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/04.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt=""><figcaption>Pass 2: Add a live width test into the mix to see if there’s enough room for the tabs and make it an accordion if the screen is too narrow.</figcaption></figure></p>

<p><figure id="fig-2015-05-28-05" class="media-container"><img  src="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/05.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" srcset="https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/05.png&amp;resize_w=1920&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 1920w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/05.png&amp;resize_w=600&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 600w,https://images1-focus-opensocial.googleusercontent.com/gadgets/proxy?url=http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2015-05-28/05.png&amp;resize_w=320&amp;container=focus&amp;refresh=2592000 320w" sizes="100vw" alt=""><figcaption>Pass 3: Test for native <code>details</code>/<code>summary</code> support and use the native functionality if available.</figcaption></figure></p>

<h2>Simple, Powerful</h2>

<p>Ix Maps have been incredibly useful to me and the dozens of teams I’ve worked with. They’ve helped us explore innovative ways to solve design challenges and have been an amazing touchstone to organize our work around. Give them a shot an I’m sure you’ll discover lots of ways to put them to use in your own projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips for Surviving Google’s “Mobilegeddon”]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/tips-for-surviving-googles-mobilegeddon/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-21T08:10:12-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/tips-for-surviving-googles-mobilegeddon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is the day <a href="http://www.economist.com/news/business-and-finance/21648947-worlds-biggest-search-engine-shakes-up-its-algorithms-mobilegeddon">Google updates it algorithm to take into account mobile-friendliness</a>. Here are a few tips that will help you embrace mobile without tearing your hair out.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>1. Embrace mobile-first CSS</h2>

<p>This is a quick win. I’ve done the mobile-first overhaul on a number of existing sites over the last few years and the best strategy I’ve found is this:</p>

<ol>
<li>Create two CSS files. Name the first something like &ldquo;basic.css&rdquo; and link to it with <code>media="all"</code>. Name the second something like &ldquo;advanced.css&rdquo; and link to it with <code>media="only screen"</code>.</li>
<li>Move all of your existing desktop-only CSS into advanced.css and wrap the rules in a media query corresponding to your design width (e.g. <code>@media (min-width:60em)</code> for a 960px max width).</li>
<li>Open a page from your site in a new browser window and make it as small as possible. Move any basic typographic and color styles from advanced.css to default.css and refresh the page. How does it look? Make the browser wider. Still acceptable? Awesome! This is the CSS you’ll serve to older browsers that don’t understand media queries and it forms the basis of your larger screen styles.</li>
<li>Shrink the browser back down to the smallest it can go and create a breakpoint for that size in advanced.css (e.g. <code>@media (min-width:10.5em)</code> if you want to small target devices like the <a href="https://getpebble.com/">Pebble</a>). Move any styles you want applied in this scenario from your &ldquo;full screen&rdquo; breakpoint and add any new rules you need to make things look good.</li>
<li>Increase the browser width until the layout looks odd, then make a new breakpoint and move in or add the necessary styles.</li>
<li>Rinse &amp; repeat until you get up to the &ldquo;full screen&rdquo; layout.</li>
<li>Move your print styles—you do have print styles, right?—into default.css and wrap them in a print <code>@media</code> block.</li>
</ol>


<p>For another approach to responsive retrofitting, check out <a href="http://webstandardssherpa.com/reviews/responsive-retrofitting/">this piece from Ben Callahan</a>.</p>

<h2>2. Focus on key tasks</h2>

<p>Every page has a purpose. If it doesn’t, you don’t need it. Find the page’s purpose and make that the focus. Eliminate distractions and reduce the amount of friction a user encounters when trying to accomplish the task.</p>

<p>If company or client politics preclude you from getting rid of all distractions on a page, consider <a href="http://www.filamentgroup.com/lab/ajax-includes-modular-content.html">a lazy-loading strategy</a> to bring them in with JavaScript only when there is more screen real estate.</p>

<h2>3. Get smarter about images</h2>

<p>Images are great, but they often comprise the majority of a web page’s bulk. To slim things down, first consider whether a given image is actually needed. If it isn’t, get rid of it. If it offers an enhancement, but isn’t crucial, consider lazy-loading it after page load. If the image is really important, <a href="https://ericportis.com/posts/2014/srcset-sizes/">use <code>srcset</code> and <code>sizes</code></a> (or the <code>picture</code> element) to deliver the smallest and yet most appropriate image to your users, based on their device.</p>

<h2>4. Embrace the continuum</h2>

<p>As designers and developers, we often try to control everything. But we have to realize that we can’t control everything on the Web. People on different devices have different capabilities and considerations. They will need your website to be flexible enough to allow them to accomplish their goals no matter what.</p>

<p>Understanding that is key to building experiences that move seamlessly across devices. You know, <a href="http://alistapart.com/article/understandingprogressiveenhancement">progressive enhancement</a>. It’s key to embracing the Web for all of its inherent web-iness.</p>

<hr>


<p>And there you have it: 4 simple, but effective guidelines for creating awesome websites that will fair well under Google’s new algorithm. And guess what: Your users will benefit too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Apply Progressive Enhancement When JavaScript Seems Like a Requirement]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/how-to-apply-progressive-enhancement-when-javascript-seems-like-a-requirement/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-02T09:14:40-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/how-to-apply-progressive-enhancement-when-javascript-seems-like-a-requirement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On Stack Overflow last week, <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/users/4719194/jamham">JamHam</a> asked how to apply progressive enhancement in interfaces that seem to require JavaScript. Unfortunately he deleted the question before I could post my response, so I thought I would post it all here for posterity.</p>

<!-- more -->


<blockquote><p>I&rsquo;ve been trying to make my site (a content publishing &ldquo;web app&rdquo;) work fully without JavaScript, however, I&rsquo;ve found myself in situations where I can&rsquo;t honestly think how I would do some features without it.</p>

<p>For instance:</p>

<ul>
<li>I have a form submission page where you change certain settings, and the form changes accordingly.This is alright, I can apply query strings in the url and have some logic in my layout so that certain fields are shown/hidden according to the query string. The thing is, I also need to update a &ldquo;price&rdquo; dynamically, according to what fields are filled in, how they are filled in, and some other factors, and I don&rsquo;t honestly see how I could do that without JavaScript.</li>
<li>I have a messaging section where I&rsquo;m using WebSockets (with the help of Socket.io). The UI of the messaging (and of course, the
WebSockets) stuff pretty much depends on JavaScript, with &lsquo;messages&rsquo; being created as they arrive and appended into DOM and also a form that allows you to quickly look up an user via AJAX so you can send a message easily, among many other things.</li>
</ul>


<p>I mean, I could probably come up with very complicated solutions for each situation, and obviously the functionality wouldn&rsquo;t be the same. I&rsquo;m thinking I might as well just require JavaScript for the whole thing</p>

<p>But it kinda sucks, since I&rsquo;ve been making everything work without JavaScript, up until this point. And I would like some consistency across the whole site. In these kind of situations, is it acceptable to not support non-js clients? What would you suggest in this case?</p></blockquote>

<p>My response (which I was drafting when he deleted the question):</p>

<blockquote><p>First off, I applaud your interest in using progressive enhancement. It will ensure the most users possible have access to your content and will also result in a more robust application overall. As a general guiding principle, look to the past. How did we solve these issues before widespread JavaScript availability? Those &ldquo;Web 1.0&rdquo; solutions will still work and can be overtaken by supplanted by your JavaScript solution whenever it is possible to do so.</p>

<p>Every situation is different, but it is even possible to reuse a lot of code in both scenarios.</p>

<p>Now to address your interfaces…</p>

<p><strong>Your Submission Page</strong> &ndash; I could be wrong, but this sounds like a shopping cart to me (at least in essence). You are on the right track with query parameters, but you could also store info about the cart (and the user’s capabilities) in a session or cookie.</p>

<p>In terms of updating the &ldquo;cart&rdquo;, a simple &ldquo;update&rdquo; submit button that posts the form and triggers a redirection back to this page with the updated info would be sufficient. And if you need to show or hide fields based on choices made, you simply apply that logic on the server side. You could even have the server generate that same markup into the page, but hidden for situations where JavaScript is available.</p>

<p><strong>Your Messaging App</strong> &ndash; This can seem like a daunting challenge, but before we had web sockets and even Ajax, we relied on a small form which posts messages to the back end and a running feed of messages being sent from the back-end. One of the most common way to handle this involved frames and a &ldquo;meta refresh&rdquo; like this one:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;meta http-equiv="refresh" content="30"&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>That simple <code>meta</code> tag will make any browser refresh the page every 30 seconds. Now if you put that in an <code>iframe</code> to keep it from causing a refresh of the entire interface, any new messages would be picked up and displayed automatically at that interval (which you should tune to be appropriate for your app).</p>

<p>Once that is in place the page itself could even post to that frame by using the non-standard but well-supported <code>_target</code> attribute on the <code>form</code>.</p>

<p>Obviously with JavaScript enabled, you’d probably throw away that <code>iframe</code>, but the rest of the setup (including the templates for displaying the messages) could certainly be reused with WebSockets.</p></blockquote>

<p>I hope this helps. Progressive enhancement may seem like a huge challenge, but when you take a few moments to think about how we handled these challenges in the past, the way forward becomes clear.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
