<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Browse by Tag: Web Design | Aaron Gustafson]]></title>
  <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/tags/web-design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-25T21:20:29-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sending Birthday Well-wishes to Molly]]></title>
    <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/sending-birthday-well-wishes-to-molly/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-25T10:20:25-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/sending-birthday-well-wishes-to-molly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is the birthday of an amazing woman: <a href="https://twitter.com/mollydotcom">Molly Holzschlag</a>.</p>

<p>If you’re relatively new to the Web, you may not recognize her name, but you are benefiting from her legacy. You see, Molly has been a force of nature on the Web for the better part of two decades. She was an <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20000229205046/http://www.molly.com/molly/news.html">early blogger</a>. She was our fearless leader at the <a href="http://webstandards.org">Web Standards Project</a> for three years. <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/search?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;index=books&amp;keywords=molly%20holzschlag&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;tag=easydesign-20&amp;linkId=BDCVT2YGNT7BNCHR">Molly wrote <em>35 books</em> on Web design, CSS, and other Web standards-related topics</a>. She’s presented at conferences the world over and educated thousands of Web designers and developers during her tenure. And Molly was way ahead of us when it came to understanding the Web:</p>

<blockquote><p>Everyone has something to contribute to the World Wide Web. Why? Because the Web is of us. Whatever we are as humans is now manifest in the Web: Our beauty, hatred, fragility and ferocity; our kindness, cruelty, confusion and clarity. Our wars. Our peace.</p></blockquote>

<p>You might think that with all this acclaim, Molly must be pretty well off. Well, that’s not the case. Molly was far more concerned about the good of the Web than fancy jobs, lofty titles, and hefty paychecks. She did much of her work for free. In fact, she even ran a free &ldquo;train the trainer&rdquo; camp wherein she hosted a group of college-level educators <em>at her home</em> to get them up to speed on what they needed to know and what they should be teaching the next generation of Web designers.</p>

<p>I met Molly in 2003 when I was invited to speak at COMDEX. It was my first conference talk (and professional speaking gig) ever. I gave a talk on XHTML and she same up and complimented me on it. I had been incredibly nervous, so hearing someone so experienced compliment me on my material, it relieved my stress and made me feel better about by performance. And when she asked me to join her on stage for her next talk—her co-presenter Eric Meyer had to cancel last-minute—I was overjoyed. I don’t know that I added much to her CSS discussion, but I was so appreciative when she took me under her wing.</p>

<p>In 2005 we shared the stage again as we went on a five-city tour, giving 3 days of in-depth HTML, CSS, and JavaScript workshops. I learned a ton from Molly about presenting and she became the big sister I never had. My champion. My mentor.</p>

<p>I know I am not the only one with a story like this. Molly has touched so many Web designers’ and developers’ lives—both directly and indirectly—with her knowledge, compassion, and mentorship.</p>

<p>In 2013, Molly fell ill at a Web conference. She’s spent the last two years in recovery from intense chemotherapy and the damage it did to her body. She is incredibly weak, unable to work, and needs our help to pay for her basic living and medical expenses. So I ask you: Please dig deep and contribute to <a href="http://www.gofundme.com/ThanksMols">the GoFundMe campaign</a> Kimmie Blessing has set up on her behalf.</p>

<p>For all that Molly has done for us, let’s <a href="http://www.gofundme.com/ThanksMols">do something for her</a>.</p>

<p>Happy birthday Molly! We love you, miss you, and hope you come back to us soon!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Competing on “Chrome”]]></title>
    <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/competing-on-chrome/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-21T15:20:40-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/competing-on-chrome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Watching the <a href="http://news.microsoft.com/windows10story/">Windows 10 announcement</a> today and the “unveiling” of its new browser, codenamed “Project Spartan”, I was amazed… not by what was said so much as what wasn’t.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Let me back up a bit here. As many of you know, I’ve been working on the Web for a long time and, like many old codgers, lived through the first browser wars and remember not only the unveiling of Internet Explorer 6—which was pretty amazing for its time—but I also worked on the Web for the entire 5 years that browser sat on the shelf.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>By the time Internet Explorer 7 came out in late 2006, there had been a number of advancements on the Web. And there was more competition for user and developer mindshare. Safari popped up shortly after IE6’s launch and was gaining traction on the Mac with its port of Konqueror’s layout engine, KHTML, which they renamed WebKit. Netscape was in it’s death throes, but Firefox arose from the ashes<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> and was capturing an ever-growing share of the market with its improved security, extensibility through browser plug-ins, and tabbed browsing. Not only that, but the Mozilla core of Firefox had also been spun into several other browsers that were similarly taking off: Camino, Flock, SeaMonkey, Galeon, and Epiphany. And then, of course, the Opera browser was still going strong on the desktop and growing rapidly in the mobile space.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p>When IE7 finally made it out into the world, developers were at peak frustration when it came to dealing with standards-compatibility issues in IE. So it’s no surprise that the messaging focus for IE7 was, at least in terms of the Web designer/developer audience, focused on <a href="http://www.zdnet.com/article/ie7-and-standards-compliance-microsofts-chris-wilson-charts-progress/">apologizing for the past and promising that they cared about (and were supporting) interoperable Web standards</a>.</p>

<p>And this was an earnest sentiment, it wasn’t bullshit. I remember <a href="https://twitter.com/cwilso">Chris Wilson</a>—then Platform Architect of Internet Explorer Platform team—telling me he had personally printed out <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS2/">the entire CSS 2.1 spec</a> and put it on the desk of each developer working on Trident, the browser’s rendering engine.</p>

<p>And IE7, for all of its faults, was an improvement over IE6. A few years later, IE8 was an improvement over that. And, a little later, IE9 gave us a completely reborn Internet Explorer, largely free of the layout and rendering quirks we had earned so much grey hair fighting. And so on. And so on. But all the while, the drumbeat from the IE team was this: Now with more standards support!</p>

<p>And it wasn’t just IE that was making this claim. Other browsers began to tout their support of one particular standard or another that the others didn’t in hopes of getting developers to pay more attention to them.</p>

<p>Some time before the launch of IE8, I remember having a conversation with Chris Wilson over drinks at a conference. We talked at length about the state of Web standards, browsers, and the like. During the course of our chat, he offered up his dream:</p>

<blockquote><p>I’ll be happy when browsers stop competing on standards support and start competing on chrome.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p></blockquote>

<p>It stuck with me because what he was saying made a lot of sense: Standards-compliance should be a given; browsers should be competing on the extra stuff they offer.</p>

<p>Which brings me back to today’s announcement. Standards-compliance wasn’t mentioned<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> by <a href="https://twitter.com/joebelfiore">Joe Belfiore</a> in his walkthrough of “Project Spartan”. Instead, Joe focused on the value adds in the browser: in-app note taking, a focused reading mode, cross-device synchronization, and Cortana integration.</p>

<p>This is a major milestone for IE in my opinion and it makes me wonder if we’ve finally reached the place that Chris dreamed about all those years ago. I certainly hope so.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I was told that, internally, decision-makers felt the browser was “done” and there would be no more advancements on the Web that would require a new browser.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>An apt metaphor, Firefox was originally Phoenix, then later Firebird, before eventually becoming Firefox. <a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>You may not realize it, but Opera Mobile predated even IE6. And it’s Opera Mini variant touts big numbers too: In April 2014, there were over 267 million Opera mobile browser users (244 million of whom used Opera Mini) and Opera Mini users viewed over 177 billion pages in that same month. (<a href="http://www.operasoftware.com/smw/2014-04">Source</a>)<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>The Chrome browser, from Google, did not exist at this time. By &ldquo;chrome&rdquo; he meant the window around a webpage—it toolbars, buttons, menus, and other browser-based functionality.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>The only phrases that even hint at standards compliance were “modern Web” and “a new rendering engine… that is compatible with how the Web is written today” (starting at around 59:05 in <a href="https://ll.ms-studiosmedia.com/events/2015/1501/Windows10CP/live/Windows10CP.html?title=Windows10CP-mscom">the video</a>).<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Egalitarianism]]></title>
    <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/egalitarianism/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-19T10:32:20-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/egalitarianism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is Martin Luther King Day in the United States, so I thought I’d take a moment to reflect on one aspect of equality I think is incredibly important: egalitarianism.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>According to <a href="http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/egalitarianism"><cite class="book">Merriam Webster</cite></a>, egalitarianism is:</p>

<blockquote>
    <ol>
        <li>a belief in human equality especially with respect to social, political, and economic affairs;</li>
        <li>a social philosophy advocating the removal of inequalities among people.</li>
    </ol>
</blockquote>


<p>It’s a simple philosophy inspired by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Rule">the Golden Rule</a>, an ethical code which is central to most major religions:</p>

<dl>
    <dt>Buddhism</dt>
    <dd>Hurt not others in ways that you yourself would find harmful.</dd>
    <dt>Christianity</dt>
    <dd>Do unto others as you would have  them do unto you.</dd>
    <dt>Islam</dt>
    <dd>No one of you is a believer until he desires for his brother that which he desires for himself.</dd>
    <dt>Judaism</dt>
    <dd>What is hateful to you, do not to your fellow man. That is the entire law; all the rest is commentary.</dd>
</dl>


<p>Heck, even Confucius said “Never impose on others what you would not choose for yourself”.</p>

<p>With so much emphasis on treating others with the sort of respect that we would like to be given, you’d think that inequality would be a non-issue. Obviously that’s not the case.</p>

<p>For centuries, we humans—even those of us who ascribe to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Rule#Religion_and_philosophy">these and the other countless Golden Rule abiding religions and philosophies</a>—have failed to recognize ourselves in others and have erected barriers (both physical and societal) to their ability to lead the sort of happy, fulfilled life that we want for ourselves and our families.</p>

<p>Almost every way we mistreat others—from rude or snarky comments to genocide—stems from our inability to empathize with another person or group of people. It’s hard to connect with people who are different than us—people who have different life experiences, people who have different perspectives, people who are challenged in ways we have never been—and when we struggle to create a connection, it becomes easy for us to view them as “the other”. And when we begin to look at other people this way, we lose sight of their humanity and we lose sight of all of the things that make us similar.</p>

<p>While it is completely true that I have a very different life than a woman growing up in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dharavi">Dharavi</a>, I have to believe that we have a lot in common too. We both want a good life for our families. We both want to feel safe. We both crack jokes. We’re both human. Our respective societies may view us very differently, but she is no less valuable than I am.</p>

<p>And this is why I am so passionate about the philosophy of egalitarianism. It grounds us in the notion that we are all equally valuable and should be granted equal opportunity to all that life has to offer.</p>

<hr>


<p>John Rawls has a great thought experiment that I often cite in <a href="http://vimeo.com/70018634">my talks on empathy</a>. In it, he would ask you to imagine your ideal society. It could be a monarchy, anarchy, capitalist, or communist. It could be ruled by people of one particular gender or color. It could be governed by people of a particular tribe. It could be <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hunger_Games_universe#Panem">Panem</a>. It could be <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erewhon">Erewhon</a>. It could be <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brobdingnag">Brobdingnag</a>. The choice is yours.</p>

<p>Once you’ve been ruminating on this a bit, he drops the bombshell: You have no control over or knowledge of where you fit in this society. This is called the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veil_of_ignorance">Veil of Ignorance</a>, a creation of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Harsanyi">John Harsanyi</a> (an economist and early father of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Game_theory">game theory</a>). Rawls found that, with the Veil of Ignorance in play, people who participated in this thought experiment gravitated toward creating the most egalitarian societies possible.</p>

<p>It makes complete sense: What rational human being would create a society that enslaves people if they themselves could turn out to be a slave? Who would create a society that excludes women if they might be female? Who would build a world full of stairs if they could be in a wheelchair?</p>

<p>I love this exercise because it makes it easy to create at least basic connections between you and a wide variety of people who are different than you. It helps you realize that we are all equal and all worthy of consideration.</p>

<hr>


<p>What is interesting about egalitarianism, as opposed to similar sounding philosophies like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Communist_Manifesto">modern communism</a>, is that it recognizes that equality of opportunity does not necessitate equality of outcome. In other words, while pushing for equality,  it simultaneously recognizes that we have differences in capability, capacity, and interest.</p>

<p>We are different. We are similar in more ways than we are different, but to ignore our differences is to deny us our  individuality, our personhood, our true selves. But recognizing differences is not the same as assigning a value to those differences. That’s an incredibly important distinction and bears repeating: Just because you recognize that someone is different does not imply you should view or treat them as any more or less human on account of what makes them different. That said, recognizing differences is the first step towards being able to create equality of opportunity.</p>

<p>This is such an important concept in life, but I was not a philosophy major, so I’ll stick to discussing it in terms of what I know a lot about: The Web. Specifically, Web accessibility.</p>

<p>For a great many of us, ensuring our websites are accessible is an afterthought. We talk a good game when it comes to “user centered” this or that, but often treat the word “accessibility” as a synonym for “screen reader”. It’s so much more than that. “Accessibility” is about people. People consume content and use interfaces in many different ways, some similar and some not so similar to how we do it.</p>

<p>Sure, people with visual impairments often use a screen reader to consume content. They might also use a braille touch feedback device or a braille printer. They probably also use a keyboard. Or they may use a touchscreen in concert with audio cues. And yes, visual impairment affects a great percentage of people, but they are only part of the “accessibility” puzzle.</p>

<p>The dimensions of interactive elements—links, buttons, etc.—and their proximity to one another is an important factor in ensuring an interface actually registers our intent (i.e. it helps us avoid <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Typographical_error">fat fingering</a>). <em>Design</em> is an accessibility concern.</p>

<p>The color contrast between text and the background is an important factor in ensuring content remains readable in different lighting situations. <em>Color</em> is an accessibility concern.</p>

<p>The language we use on our sites and in our interfaces directly affects how easy it is for our users to understand what we do, the products we are offering, and why it matters. It also affects how we make our users feel. <em>Language</em> is an accessibility concern.</p>

<p>The size of our Web pages and their associated assets has a direct affect on how long our pages take to download, how much it costs our customers to access them, and (sometimes) even whether or not the content can be reached. <em>Performance</em> is an accessibility concern.</p>

<p>I could keep going, but I’m sure you’re starting to get the point. “Accessibility” is ultimately about ensuring people have equal opportunity to access your content while simultaneously recognizing that we all have special needs—physical limitations, bandwidth limitations, device limitations, etc.—that lead us to have different experiences of the same Web page.</p>

<p>Accessibility <em>is</em> egalitarianism.</p>

<hr>


<p>We are all different, but we all human. We all deserve respect. We all deserve to be treated equally. To be treated fairly.</p>

<p>We need more egalitarianism in this world and the good news is that <em>we</em> can make it happen.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spelling Errors, Exclusions, and Packages, Oh My—Working Drafts at the W3C]]></title>
    <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/spelling-errors-exclusions-and-packages-oh-my/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-16T07:15:12-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/spelling-errors-exclusions-and-packages-oh-my</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week the W3C published a couple of really cool new Working Drafts I wanted to bring to your attention (just in case you missed them).</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css-pseudo-4-20150115">CSS 4 Pseudo-elements</a>.</h2>

<p>Most of this is stuff you know: <code>::first-line</code>, <code>::first-letter</code>, and <code>::selection</code>. But what magic is this? <code>::spelling-error</code> and <code>::grammar-error</code> too! What?! Now I know I may be a little too excited about this, but it’s not because spelling and grammar errors are going to solve all of our design problems; I am excited about this because it points to us being granted more control over how more of the internals of browser operations are rendered to our users.</p>

<p>Obviously <a href="/notebook/native-vs-stylable-tug-of-war/">this is a double edged sword</a> and could be abused to the detriment of the user experience, but it may also lead to someone coming up with clearer conventions for indicating spelling and grammar errors than the ones we’ve been using since the early days of Microsoft Word.</p>

<h2><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css3-exclusions-20150115/">CSS 3 Exclusions</a></h2>

<p>This has been a long time coming. The idea is pretty simple: Within a flow-type element (think <code>p</code>, <code>div</code>, etc.) you can apply <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css3-exclusions-20150115/#wrap-flow-property">the <code>wrap-flow</code> property</a> to children in order to control where content can go in relation to them. Here’s an example from the spec:</p>

<p><figure id="fig-2015-01-16-1"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;img src="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css3-exclusions-20150115/images/exclusions-illustration.png" alt="Four boxes layed out roughly diagonally from the upper left to the lower right within a larger container. A flow of blue color shows where text is allowed to flow."&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></figure></p>

<p>In this example, child A is set to <code>wrap-flow: both</code>, allowing content to flow on both sides of it. Child B is set to <code>wrap-flow: start</code> meaning content should only be allowed on the starting side of the element (based on text direction, in this case left to right). Child C is set to <code>wrap-flow: end</code> meaning content can only appear after it in terms of text-direction. And child D is set to <code>wrap-flow: clear</code> which, as you might expect based on your existing CSS knowledge, ensures no content appears on either side of it.</p>

<p>There is <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css3-exclusions-20150115/#wrap-flow-property">another, more thorough example in the Working Draft</a> (scroll down a little bit), but it uses grid layout as well and is a little more complicated that I want to get into today.</p>

<p>On the flip side of the equation, there is <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-css3-exclusions-20150115/#wrap-through-property">the <code>wrap-through</code> property</a> which allows other elements to control whether or not they pay attention to the <code>wrap-flow</code> property of another element. A <code>wrap-through</code> value of &ldquo;wrap&rdquo; adheres to what they are calling the &ldquo;wrapping context&rdquo; of the parent element (which basically means it behaves as you’d expect, being a child element). Setting a <code>wrap-through</code> value of &ldquo;none&rdquo; on the child element, however, would make it ignore the parent element’s wrapping context and allow this child’s content to flow through (hence <code>wrap-through</code>) the excluded element.</p>

<p>It’s a lot to take in and (of course) still subject to change, but I just wanted to bring this concept to your attention as it is pretty cool stuff and is a nice complement to <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/css-shapes-1/">CSS Shapes</a>, which landed early last year.</p>

<h2><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-web-packaging-20150115/">Streamable Package Format</a></h2>

<p>This one is pretty crazy and I am still tucking into it, but here’s the gist: You could provide a &ldquo;package&rdquo; or rolled up collection of files necessary to render your page—think CSS, images, fonts, etc.—in <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-web-packaging-20150115/#streamable-package-format">Streamable Package Format</a> which would allow a browser to download them all in one go rather than having to request each resource individually. This could be really useful from a performance standpoint on high-latency connections as it cuts down on the number of round-trips the browser must make to the server before it can render the page. And, since the package can be streamed, we can optimize the contents to provide the most important bits first so the browser can go about rendering the document as quickly as possible.</p>

<p>This is a very cool concept with a lot of potential benefit to our users. Of course, as the document acknowledges, it’s also possible to abuse this and adversely affect performance by including a lot of unnecessary content. Kinda like <a href="https://www.polymer-project.org/articles/spa.html">that guy who made his whole single-page app into a Web Component</a>. Just because you can do something doesn’t make it a good idea.</p>

<p>Still, there’s a lot of potential here and I’m excited to see where it goes.</p>

<hr>


<p>Now the caveat: all of these are Working Drafts, not Technical Recommendations, so <em>they are not final by any means</em>. That said, they do point to a pretty interesting not to distant future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Onslaught of Low-cost Smartphones]]></title>
    <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/an-onslaught-of-low-cost-smartphones/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-15T11:58:11-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/an-onslaught-of-low-cost-smartphones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It seems every week we are seeing more and more low-cost devices being launched in an effort to connect the unconnected. For instance, this past week  saw the announcement of <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2015/1/14/7544107/microsoft-lumia-435-532-launch-specs-price-release-date">two new entries in the Microsoft Lumia line, the 435 and the 532</a>, and the announcement of <a href="http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2015/01/samsung-finally-puts-tizen-on-a-smartphone-launches-the-z1-in-india/">Samsung’s first Tizen phone, the Z1</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The two Lumia devices are the cheapest Windows Phone offerings to date: The Lumia 435 is €69 (about US$80) and the Lumia 532 is just slightly more expensive at €79 (about US$94). By comparison, the Lumia 535 was the previous low-cost Windows Phone winner at US$135. And Samsung’s Z1, which is aimed at the Indian market, runs a mere Rs 5,700 (roughly US$92).</p>

<p>Now if you’ve read this far, you are probably wondering why this matters. Well, spec-wise, many of these lower-end devices are far from what we are used to. All of these devices are running a resolution of 800×480. And their processing speeds are slower than the device you likely have in your pocket. But they are all far cheaper too. And remember that people in China and India have <a href="#fig-2015-01-15-01">far less disposible income than we do</a>.</p>

<p><figure id="fig-2015-01-15-01" class="media-container"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;img src="http://aaron-gustafson.com/i/posts/2014-11-06/05-sm.jpg"
     srcset="/i/posts/2014-11-06/05-lg.jpg 1920w, /i/posts/2014-11-06/05-md.jpg 600w, /i/posts/2014-11-06/05-sm.jpg 320w"
     alt="A bar chart comparing the average monthly incomes of people living in the U.S., Canada, China, and India."
     &gt;
</code></pre>

<p></figure></p>

<p>If you only earned US$295 a month, a US$799 smartphone would likely be out of the question.</p>

<p>As Web designers and developers, we need to expose ourselves to the Web as others see it. This is why we need to view our sites and applications on lower-end devices and over lower-speed—2G, 3G, etc.—connections. Only by testing our wares can we truly ensure our content and services are available and accessible by anyone, anywhere, on any device. You know, <a href="http://webfoundation.org/about/vision/">the vision for the Web</a>.</p>

<p>Of course you probably don’t have the budget to purchase a bunch of devices, no matter how cheap they are. So how do you test on them? <a href="http://opendevicelab.com/">Visit a local Open Device Lab</a> like <a href="http://chadevicelab.org">the one we have here in Chattanooga</a>. Or if you don’t have one near you, consider getting together with some colleagues and <a href="http://lab-up.org/">starting an ODL in your area</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
