<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Browse by Tag: Web Development | Aaron Gustafson]]></title>
  <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/tags/web-development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-03T16:16:00-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Gustafson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The One Weird Trick That Takes the Pain Out of Cross-browser Testing]]></title>
    <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/the-one-weird-trick-that-takes-the-pain-out-of-cross-browser-testing/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-26T11:24:25-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/the-one-weird-trick-that-takes-the-pain-out-of-cross-browser-testing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Love this!</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We Need More Empathy]]></title>
    <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/we-need-more-empathy/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-28T11:17:21-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/we-need-more-empathy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a while now I’ve been <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/AaronGustafson/designing-with-empathy-breaking-development-nashville-2013">beating the “empathy” drum</a> (<a href="http://www.lukew.com/ff/entry.asp?1810">notes</a>), trying to get folks in our industry to understand the importance of creating connections with the people for whom we build software, websites, etc. After all, we design and build tools to solve the needs of actual people, not some generic “user”.<!-- more --><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>It’s tough to connect with other people and we often fall into the trap of designing products for us and people like us. Jeffrey Zeldman characterizes the problem perfectly in <a href="http://www.zeldman.com/2014/12/28/unexamined-privilege-is-the-real-source-of-cruelty-in-facebooks-your-year-in-review/">his recent post</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>If we keep throwing only young, mostly white, mostly upper middle class people at the engine that makes our digital world go, we’ll keep getting camera and reminder and hookup apps—things that make an already privileged life even smoother—and we’ll keep producing features that sound like a good idea to everyone in the room, until they unexpectedly stab someone in the heart.</p></blockquote>

<p>Empathy is difficult when we are surrounded by others like us. We need to be surrounded by different people. Certainly gender and ethnic diversity is incredibly important here, but so is diversity of experience. As Jeffrey astutely points out, diversity in the room where Facebook’s “Year in Review” concept was given the green light would have—I have to hope—helped create some safeguards to keep some of their actual customers from being reminded of tragedies they experienced this year.</p>

<p>In all likelihood, the worst thing they probably discussed was an embarrassing hookup being celebrated, but I’ve had several friends lose children and loved ones this year, other friends battling serious illnesses, and still others who have suffered losses of different sorts. All bore their souls on Facebook in the past year and this feature has brought it back and, in some cases, <a href="http://meyerweb.com/eric/thoughts/2014/12/24/inadvertent-algorithmic-cruelty/">celebrated these tragic events in a very uncanny and dispassionate way</a>.</p>

<p>And Facebook isn’t the only company to blame for this sort of thing. Pretty much every social network suffers from similar issues. Reading the comments on the various press accounts of this story have revealed similar problems at <a href="http://arstechnica.com/business/2014/12/facebook-apologizes-for-morbid-results-with-its-year-in-review-nag/?comments=1&amp;post=28196195#comment-28196195">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="http://arstechnica.com/business/2014/12/facebook-apologizes-for-morbid-results-with-its-year-in-review-nag/?comments=1&amp;post=28196709#comment-28196709">Google+</a>, <a href="http://www.deathanddigitallegacy.com/2010/08/05/twitter-recommends-dead-friends/">Twitter</a>, and others. We can and need to do better.</p>

<p>In order to address these issues, we need to flex our empathetic muscles. We need to create connections with people who are not like us. People who live in different neighborhoods. People who come from different countries. People who require alternate means to accessing our sites and services. We need to see that the world is full of differences.</p>

<p>Life is full of great joy as well as great tragedy. When we acknowledge diversity of experience and actually embrace it, we become better designers.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I don’t mind the aggregate “users”, but “user” is too clinical and distanced for my tastes. Terms like “the user” keep us from connecting with the people who actually use our software and when we are disconnected from our users, we will not do a great job of solving their problems. And solving problems is the whole point of design.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Autoplay, Don’t Do It]]></title>
    <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/autoplay-dont-do-it/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-21T15:12:50-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/autoplay-dont-do-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back <a href="https://gigaom.com/2014/09/04/facebooks-autoplay-has-led-to-a-60-boost-in-traffic-on-mobile-networks/">GogOm reported on how Facebook’s decision to autoplay videos led to a 60% increase in mobile data usage</a>. It was a business decision with the intent of increasing engagement, but it was a bad decision from a user experience. It’s a tax on users and they weren’t to happy about it.</p>

<p>You may be wondering <em>Why is this a bad thing for users? They want to see videos, so we’re just giving them what they want.</em> Well, let me share a little story.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I was in Lisbon for <a href="http://lanyrd.com/2013/uxlx/">UxLx</a> last year and was on roaming data through my mobile provider. At the hotel, the Wifi was giving me trouble, so I opted to tether my computer so I can pull down a document I needed. Chrome crashed. Lame, but no big deal. I relaunched it and, Chrome being the helpful browser that it is, all of my tabs were restored and I got back to work.</p>

<p>A few minutes later I got a text message from my provider: I’d just used a tremendous amount of my data in a very short amount of time. And I had only landed an hour before. I was understandably concerned. And perplexed. What happened?</p>

<p>Well, it turns out one of the tabs that re-spawned after Chrome crashed was a page on YouTube. And on that page was an hour-long video. In HD. And it auto-played. I had the volume off and it was in background tab, so I had no idea.</p>

<p>YouTube’s “business decision” to autoplay their videos cost me real money. A lot of it.</p>

<p>Don’t autoplay. Any benefits you might see in user engagement are probably going to be drowned out by legitimate complaints from your users. Just don’t do it.</p>

<p>Incidentally, you can <a href="https://www.facebook.com/help/633446180035470">disable auto-play in Facebook</a>, but first of all you have to know it’s an option. Facebook gives you the choice of turning it on or off entirely or to turn it on only over Wifi. That may seem like a great compromise, but I’d like to put forward a few arguments as to why it’s not:</p>

<ol>
<li><em>Tethering:</em> If I am tethered to my phone, it is likely being done over Wifi. Even if my browser is aware that I am on Wifi and even if the website is paying attention to that (using the <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/netinfo-api/">Network Informaion API</a>), the website is probably going to get a false positive for Wifi even though the <em>actual</em> data connection is over a mobile network.</li>
<li><em>Metered Wifi:</em> Hotels and other providers often limit how much data you can use. You could be on an awesomely fast Wifi network, but if you are limited to 100MB—it happens—being on Wifi doesn’t matter.</li>
</ol>


<p>So again: Autoplay, don’t do it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CSS Variables Are a Bad Idea]]></title>
    <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/css-variables-are-a-bad-idea/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-04T14:58:01-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/css-variables-are-a-bad-idea</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ll level with you: I used to think I wanted variables in CSS.</p>

<p>As a programmer, I love the idea of being able to abstract reusable bits like colors, border widths, font sizes, and the like to obviously named variables. It’s a far more <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don't_repeat_yourself">DRY</a> approach and makes maintenance far easier.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Before I made the leap to using a CSS preprocessor, I was convinced we needed CSS variables, but I always wondered how we might make it possible without breaking one of the fundamental <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS21/intro.html#design-principles">design principles of CSS</a>: Forward and backward compatibility. Take a look at this example (which is based on <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/css-variables/">the working draft spec</a>) and I think you’ll spot the problem:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/c3ddcb792eb69e0703e1.js?file=css-vairables.css'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>:root {
  --foreground-color: #333;
  --background-color: #fff;
}

body {
  background: var(--background-color);
  color: var(--foreground-color);
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>For a browser that understands CSS variables, the interpreted stylesheet would look like this:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/c3ddcb792eb69e0703e1.js?file=desired-result.css'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>body {
  background: #fff;
  color: #333;
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>But any browser that doesn’t understand the variables would never get the color values because browsers follow <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS21/syndata.html#parsing-errors">the rules of fault tolerance in CSS</a> and ignore anything they don’t understand. The introduction of variables to CSS would effectively build a wall between older browsers and new ones. (For the record, as of this writing, <a href="http://caniuse.com/#feat=css-variables">only Firefox has implemented CSS variables</a>).</p>

<p>In order to serve the broadest spectrum of devices, we’d have to provide a fallback like this:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/c3ddcb792eb69e0703e1.js?file=css-variables-fallback.css'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>:root {
  --foreground-color: #333;
  --background-color: #fff;
}

body {
  background: #fff;
  background: var(--background-color);
  color: #333;
  color: var(--foreground-color);
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>But that kinda defeats the whole purpose, right?</p>

<p>Preprocessors already give us this access to variables today (along with nesting, mixins, and programmatic structures like conditionals, loops, etc.). Here’s a SASS example:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/c3ddcb792eb69e0703e1.js?file=sass-variables.scss'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>$foreground-color: #333;
$background-color: #fff;
 
 
body {
  background: $background-color;
  color: $foreground-color;
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>The big difference here is that this document is a source file, it is not what is sent to the browser. This file is compiled by the preprocessor into actual CSS, which is what we send to the browser and is exactly what we wanted in the first place:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/c3ddcb792eb69e0703e1.js?file=desired-result.css'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>body {
  background: #fff;
  color: #333;
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>And it works on every browser that supports CSS, all the way back to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cascading_Style_Sheets#Difficulty_with_adoption">IE 3</a>.</p>

<p>With a preprocessor like SASS, Less, or Stylus, I get all of the maintainability benefits without sacrificing browser support. It’s a no-brainer. But even if that were not true, there’s another issue to consider: If I push CSS variables to browsers, they have to parse the CSS and substitute the variables before they can apply the styles.</p>

<p>Now I’m sure browser makers can find ways to optimize this process, but it’s bound to affect the rendering time. And not in a positive way. I don’t even want to think about how bad it would be on a mobile chipset, especially on a low-end device.</p>

<p>Honestly, I love using variables… in the source files I use with a preprocessor. Given the potential loss of browser support, the pointless fallbacks I’d have to use if I wanted to continue supporting older browsers, the existence of numerous preprocessor options that solve the abstraction problem in a backward- and forward-compatible way, and the fact that CSS variables would make browsers have to work even harder to achieve the desired result, I’m not convinced we need them.</p>

<p>CSS variables are a bad idea.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Embraces Progressive Enhancement]]></title>
    <link href="http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/google-embraces-progressive-enhancement/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-28T21:07:35-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://aaron-gustafson.com/notebook/google-embraces-progressive-enhancement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In case you missed it, <a href="http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.com/2014/10/updating-our-technical-webmaster.html">yesterday Pierre Far updated Google’s Webmaster Guidelines</a>. In his post, Pierre lays out their case for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive_enhancement">progressive enhancement</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Just like modern browsers, our rendering engine might not support all of the technologies a page uses. Make sure your web design adheres to the principles of progressive enhancement as this helps our systems (and a wider range of browsers) see usable content and basic functionality when certain web design features are not yet supported.</p></blockquote>

<!-- more -->


<p>As someone who has been beating the drum for progressive enhancement for over a decade, this sort of support from such an influential company gets me a little teary-eyed.</p>

<p>It’s nice to see Steve Champeon’s philosophy for web design finally beginning to gain traction outside of the ivory tower of Web standards. It is a fantastic philosophy that has been guiding our work since Steve unveiled it. And it has paid some handsome dividends for both us and our clients.</p>

<p>If you need help wrapping your head around progressive enhancement, you should read <a href="#fn-2014-10-28">my introductory series for <cite>A List Apart</cite></a>. If you want more, there’s also <a href="http://adaptivewebdesign.info">my book on progressive enhancement: <cite>Adaptive Web Design</cite></a>. And if you need help getting your team up to speed, I’m more than happy to hop on a plane and come to you. Just <a href="/contact/">drop me a line</a>. I have helped many companies embrace this philosophy and have seen it improve their productivity, increase their reach by supporting more devices, and improve the accessibility of their products. Oh… and <a href="http://blog.easy-designs.net/archives/the-true-cost-of-progressive-enhancement">progressive enhancement has saved our clients real money and reduced their time to market</a>.</p>

<p>I don’t tend to be a “magic pill” kind of believer, but I can honestly say that embracing progressive enhancement can radically change your business for the better. And I’m glad to see Google agrees with me.</p>

<h2 id="fn-2014-10-28">My (still-relevant) 2008 series on Progressive Enhancement</h2>


<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.alistapart.com/articles/understandingprogressiveenhancement/">Understanding Progressive Enhancement</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.alistapart.com/articles/progressiveenhancementwithcss/">Progressive Enhancement with CSS</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.alistapart.com/articles/progressiveenhancementwithjavascript/">Progressive Enhancement with JavaScript</a></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
